Chapter 4 Governance In the words of the
Bletchley
Declaration, substantial risks may arise
from potential intentional misuse
or unintended issues of control relating
to alignment with
human intent. These issues are in part
because those
capabilities are not fully understood.
There is potential for
serious, even catastrophic harm, either
deliberate or unintentional, stemming
from the most significant capabilities of
these AI models.
Artificial intelligence has the potential
to revolutionize numerous aspects
of society, from healthcare to
transportation to scientific research.
Through the previous chapters, you have
seen AI's ability
to defeat world champions at go, generate
photorealistic images
from text descriptions, and even discover
new antibiotics. However,
these developments also raise significant
challenges and risks, including
job displacement, privacy infringements,
and the potential for AI
systems to make consequential mistakes or
be misused. See
the chapter two on risks for the full
spectrum.
Technical AI safety research is necessary
to ensure AI
behaves reliably and aligns with human
values, especially as
it becomes more capable and autonomous.
Even though technical
research is necessary, it alone is not
sufficient to
address the full spectrum of challenges
posed by advanced
AI systems. The scope of AI governance is
broad,
so this chapter will primarily focus on
large-scale risks
associated with frontier AI. As a
reminder, Frontier AIs
are highly capable models that could
possess dangerous capabilities
sufficient to pose severe risks to public
safety. Although
in recent history, many state-of-the-art
advancements have been driven
by LLMs or foundation models, Frontier AI
as a
term is not limited to just these types of
models. We will examine why governance is
necessary, how
it complements technical AI safety
efforts, and the key
challenges and opportunities in this
rapidly evolving field. We
will focus on the governance of commercial
and civil
AI applications, as military AI governance
involves a dist...
There is figure 4.1 in the textbook here.
It
depicts distinguishing AI models according
to their level of
potential harm and generality. We focus
here on frontier
AI models.