Section 4.7 Conclusion The governance
frameworks examined throughout this
chapter provide essential tools for
managing AI risks. But
tools alone don't determine outcomes.
Success requires choosing the
right priorities, building necessary
capabilities, and maintaining frameworks
that
evolve with the technology. Technical
expertise in government needs
dramatic expansion across every major
economy. The UK and
US AI safety institutes demonstrate what's
possible with sufficient
resources and political support. This
requires competitive compensation to
attract top talent, career paths that
value public service,
exchange programs with industry and
academia, and protection from
political interference. Currently,
properly aligning advanced AI systems with
human values will require resolving many
uncertainties related to
the psychology of human rationality,
emotion and biases. And
most government agencies lack even basic
technical literacy about
AI systems. Audit and assessment
capabilities must professionalize into
a distinct field. As AI systems become
more complex,
evaluation requires specialized expertise
that goes beyond traditional software
testing. Building this profession involves
developing certification programs for
AI auditors, creating standard
methodologies and tools, establishing
professional
organizations and ethics codes, and
ensuring independence from both
developers and regulators. International
coordination mechanisms need dedicated
resources
and authority. Current efforts rely
heavily on voluntary participation
and limited budgets. Effective
coordination requires dedicated
secretariat with
technical expertise, funding for
participation from developing countries,
translation
and communication services, and
infrastructure for secure information
sharing.
Governance frameworks must evolve as fast
as the technology
they govern. Static regulations will
quickly become either irrelevant
or obstructive. Building adaptive capacity
into governance systems is
essential for long-term effectiveness.
This means mandatory annual reviews
of capability thresholds, evaluation
methodologies, enforcement priorities and
lessons
from incidents. Scenario planning helps
prepare for discontinuous change
in AI development. Current governance
assumes relatively continuous AI
progress, but development could accelerate
suddenly through algorithmic
breakthroughs,
decelerate due to technical barriers, or
bifurcate with different
regions pursuing incompatible approaches.
Governance systems need contingency plans
for rapid capability jumps. major AI
accidents, breakdown of
international cooperation, and emergence
of artificial general intelligence.
Learning
from implementation enables continuous
improvement over the critical next
few years. The coming period will generate
enormous amounts
of data about what works in AI governance.
Systematic
learning requires tracking governance
interventions and outcomes, sharing best
practices across jurisdictions,
acknowledging and correcting failures, and
updating
frameworks based on evidence. The
temptation will be to
lock in current approaches. We must resist
this in
favour of evidence-based evolution. The
choices made in the
next few years will shape humanity's
relationship with artificial
intelligence for decades to come. As AI
capabilities advance
and become more deeply embedded in
critical systems, retrofitting
governance becomes increasingly difficult.
We have the tools, knowledge
and warning signs needed to build
effective governance. What
remains is the collective will to act
before events
force our hand. The path forward requires
acknowledging uncomfortable
truths. Voluntary corporate measures won't
suffice for systemic risks.
National approaches need unprecedented
coordination despite geopolitical tensions
and
international governance faces enormous
technical and political challenges. Yet
history shows that humanity can rise to
meet technological
challenges when the stakes become clear
and immediate. With
AI, the stakes could not be higher, and
the
timeline could not be shorter. The
question is not
whether we need comprehensive governance.
The evidence presented throughout
this chapter makes that case definitively.
The question is
whether we'll build it in time, with the
technical
sophistication and institutional authority
required to govern humanity's most
powerful technology, and the window for
answering that question
is narrowing with each new model release.