Section 4.8 Appendix Data Governance What
role does data
play in AI risks? Data fundamentally
shapes what AI
systems can do and how they behave. For
Frontier
Foundation models, training data
influences both capabilities and
alignment.
What systems can do and how they do it?
Low quality or harmful training data could
lead to
misaligned or dangerous models. Garbage
in, garbage out. while
carefully curated datasets might help
promote safer and more
reliable behavior. How well does data meet
our governance
target criteria? Data as a governance
target presents a
mixed picture when evaluated against our
key criteria. Let's
look at each. Measurability. While we can
measure raw
quantities of data, assessing its quality,
content, and potential
implications is far more difficult. Unlike
physical goods, like
semiconductors, data can be copied,
modified, niched, demystified and
transmitted in ways that are hard to
track. This
makes comprehensive measurement of data
flows extremely challenging.
Controllability,
data's non-rival nature means it can be
copied and
shared widely. Once data exists,
controlling its spread is
very difficult. Even when data appears to
be restricted,
techniques like model distillation can
extract information from trained
models. Andolong et al. 2023. However,
there might still
be some promising control points,
particularly around original data
collection and the initial training of
foundation models. Meaningfulness.
Data is particularly meaningful when it
comes to AI
development. The data used to train models
directly shapes
their capabilities and behaviors. Changes
in training data can
significantly impact model performance and
safety. This makes data
governance potentially powerful. but only
if we can overcome
the challenges of measurement and control.
What are the
key data governance concerns? Several
aspects of data require
careful governance to promote safe AI
development. Training data
quality and safety is fundamental. Low
quality or harmful
data can create unreliable or dangerous
models. For instance,
technical data about biological weapons in
training sets could
enable models to assist in their
development. data poisoning
and security pose increasingly serious
threats. Malicious actors could
deliberately manipulate training data to
create models that behave
dangerously in specific situations while
appearing safe during testing.
This might involve injecting subtle
patterns that only become
apparent under certain conditions.
Longpray et al. 2024. Data
provenance and accountability help ensure
we can trace where
model behaviors come from, without clear
tracking of training
data sources and their characteristics. It
becomes extremely difficult
to diagnose and fix problems when models
exhibit concerning
behaviors. Longpray et al. 2023 Consent
and rights frameworks
protect both data creators and users. Many
current AI
training practices operate in legal and
ethical grey areas
regarding data usage rights. Clear
frameworks could help prevent
unauthorized use while enabling legitimate
innovation. Longpray et al.
2024 Bias and representation in training
data directly impact
model behaviour. Skewed or
unrepresentative data sets can lead
to models that perform poorly or make
harmful decisions
for certain groups, potentially amplifying
societal inequities at a
massive scale. Ruel et al. 2024. Data
access and
sharing protocols shape who can develop
powerful AI systems.
Without governance around data access, we
risk either overly
concentrated power in a few actors with
large datasets
or, conversely, uncontrolled proliferation
of potentially dangerous capabilities heim
et al. 2024. How does data governance fit
into
overall AI governance? Even with strong
governance frameworks, alternative
data sources or synthetic data generation
could potentially circumvent
restrictions. Additionally, many
concerning capabilities might emerge from
seemingly
innocuous training data through unexpected
interactions or emergent behaviors.
While data governance remains important
and worthy of deeper
exploration, other governance targets may
offer more direct governance
over frontier AI development in the near
term. This
is why in the main text, we focused
primarily
on compute governance, which provides more
concrete control points
through its physical and concentrated
nature.