Section 4.4 – Systemic Challenges Section
– Race Dynamics
In the words of John Schulman, talking
about times
near the creation of the first AGI, you
have
the race dynamics where everyone's trying
to stay ahead,
and that might require compromising on
safety. So I
think you would probably need some
coordination among the
larger entities that are doing this kind
of training.
pause either further training or pause
deployment or avoiding
certain types of training that we think
might be
riskier. We already talked about race
dynamics in the
chapter on AI risks as amplifying factors
for all
risks. We mention them here again because
governance initiatives
might have special leverage to be able to
mitigate
race dynamics. Competition drives AI
development at every level.
From start-ups racing to demonstrate new
capabilities to nation-states
viewing AI leadership as essential for
future power, competitive
pressures shape how AI systems are built
and deployed.
This dynamic creates a prisoner's dilemma
like tension, where
even though everyone would benefit from
careful safety-focused development,
those who move fastest gain competitive
advantage. At this
point, the textbook shows figure 4.14. It
depicts how
to extort your opponent and what you stand
to
gain by extortion. The AI race creates a
collective
action problem. Even when developers
recognise risks, unilateral caution
means ceding ground to less scrupulous
competitors. Open AI's
evolution illustrates this tension.
Founded as a safety-focused small
non-profit, competitive pressures led to
creating a for-profit subsidiary
and accelerating deployment timelines.
When your competitors are raising
billions and shipping products monthly,
taking six extra months
for safety testing feels like falling
irreversibly behind. This
dynamic makes it exceedingly difficult for
any single entity,
be it a company or a country, to
prioritize
safety over speed. Competitive pressure
leads to safety washing,
cutting corners on testing, skipping
external red teaming, and
rationalizing away warning signs. Move
fast and break things
becomes the implicit motto, even when the
things being
broken might include fundamental safety
guarantees. We've already seen
this with models released despite known
vulnerabilities justified by
the need to maintain market position.
Public companies face
constant pressure to demonstrate progress
to investors. Each competitor's
breakthrough becomes an existential threat
requiring immediate response. When
Anthropic releases Claude III, OpenAI must
respond with GPT
4.5. When Google demonstrates new
capabilities, everyone scrambles to
match them. This quarter-by-quarter racing
leaves little room for
careful safety work that might take years
to pay
off. At this point, there is interactive
figure 4.3
in the textbook, available in the online
version. It
shows annual patent applications related
to artificial intelligence, 2019.
Patents submitted in the selected
country's patent office. National
security concerns intensify race dynamics.
When Vladimir Putin declared
whoever becomes the leader in AI will
become the
ruler of the world, he articulated what
many policymakers
privately believe. This transforms AI
development from a commercial
competition into a perceived struggle for
geopolitical dominance. Over
50 countries have launched national AI
strategies, often explicitly
framing AI leadership as critical for
economic and military
superiority. Unlike corporate races
measured in product cycles, international
AI competition involves long-term
strategic positioning. Yet paradoxically,
this
makes racing feel even more urgent.
Falling behind today
might mean permanent disadvantage
tomorrow. The textbook has interactive
figure 4.4 here, which you can explore in
the
online version. It shows cumulative number
of large-scale AI
systems by country since 2017. refers to
the location
of the primary organization with which the
authors of
large-scale AI systems are affiliated.
Race dynamics make collective
action and coordination feel impossible.
Countries hesitate to implement
strong safety regulations that might
handicap their domestic AI
industries. Companies resist voluntary
safety commitments unless competitors make
identical pledges. Everyone waits for
others to move first,
creating gridlock even when all parties
privately acknowledge the
risks. The result is a lowest common
denominator approach
to safety that satisfies no one. AI
governance needs
innovative approaches to break out of race
dynamics. Traditional
arms control offers limited lessons, since
AI development happens
in private companies, not government labs.
We need new
approaches, several ideas have been
proposed, some examples are
Reciprocal snapback limits states publish
caps on model scale,
autonomous weapon deployment and data
center compute that activate
only when peers file matching commitments.
The symmetry removes
the fear of unilateral restraint and keeps
incentives focused
on shared security rather than zero-sum
dominance. safety as
a competitive asset. Labs earn market
trust by subjecting
frontier models to independent red team
audits, embedding provenance
watermarks and disclosing incident
reports. Regulation can turn these
practices into a de facto license to
operate so
that secure by design becomes the shortest
route to
sales. Tamerasa EDAL 2024 Containment
Export controls on advanced
chips API only access with real-time
misuse monitoring Digital
forensics And know your customer checks
slow the spread
of dangerous capabilities even as
beneficial services stay widely
available These measures address open
publication, model theft, talent
mobility and hardware diffusion, factors
that let a single
leak replicate worldwide within days.
Chevron et al. 2023,
Sega 2023, Nevo et al. 2024, agile
multilateral oversight
with a coordinated halt option. A lean UN-
mandated body,
think about it like a CERN or an IAEA
for AI, needs the authority to impose
emergency pauses
when red lines are crossed, backed by chip
export
restrictions and cloud provider throttles
that make a global
off-switch technically credible. secret
safe verification, secure enclaves, tamper
evident compute logs, and zero knowledge
proofs let inspectors
confirm that firms observe model and data
controls without
exposing weights or proprietary code,
closing the principal oversight
gap identified in current treaty
proposals. Chevlan, et al.
2023, Waseel et al. 2024, and El-Yung et
al.
2024. Section, proliferation. AI
capabilities propagate globally through
digital
networks at speeds that render traditional
control mechanisms largely
ineffective. Unlike nuclear weapons that
require specialized materials and
facilities, AI models are patterns of
numbers that can
be copied and transmitted instantly. Let's
think about this
scenario. A cutting-edge AI model capable
of generating hyper-realistic
deepfakes or designing novel bioweapons is
developed by a
well-intentioned research lab. The lab,
adhering to principles of
open science, publishes their findings and
releases the model's
code as open source. Within hours, the
model is
downloaded thousands of times across the
globe. Within days,
modified versions start appearing on code
sharing platforms. Within
weeks, the capabilities that were once
confined to a
single lab have proliferated across the
Internet, accessible to
anyone with a decent computer and an
Internet connection.
This scenario, while hypothetical, isn't
far from reality. This
fundamental difference makes traditional
non-proliferation approaches nearly
useless for
AI governance. The textbook has a
supplementary note titled
Balancing Proliferation Mitigations and
Power Concentration, which we'll skip
over here. Multiple channels enable rapid
proliferation. Open publication
accelerates capability diffusion. The AI
research community's commitment to
openness means breakthrough techniques
often appear on ARXIV within
days of discovery. What took one lab years
to
develop can be replicated by others in
months. Meta's
release of Llama II led to thousands of
fine-tuned
variants within weeks, including versions
with safety features removed
and new dangerous capabilities added. Sega
2023. Model Theft
presents growing risks. As AI models
become more valuable,
they become attractive targets for
malicious hackers and criminal
groups. A single successful breach could
transfer capabilities worth
billions in development costs. Even
without direct theft, techniques
like model distillation can extract
capabilities from API access
alone. Nevo et al. 2024. Talent mobility
spreads tacit
knowledge. When researchers move between
organizations, they carry irreplaceable
expertise. The deep learning diaspora from
Google Brain and
DeepMind seeded AI capabilities worldwide.
Unlike written knowledge, this
experiential understanding of how to build
and train models
can't be controlled through traditional
means. Basiroglue 2024 hardware
proliferation enables distributed
development. As AI chips become cheaper
and more available, the barrier to entry
keeps dropping.
What required a supercomputer in 2018 now
runs on
hardware costing under $100,000. This
democratization means dangerous
capabilities
become accessible to ever smaller actors.
Massey, 2024. AI
proliferation poses unique challenges.
Digital goods follow different rules
than physical objects. Traditional
proliferation controls assume scarcity.
There's
only so much enriched uranium or only so
many
advanced missiles. But copying a model
file costs essentially
nothing. Once capabilities exist anywhere,
preventing their spread becomes
a battle against the fundamental nature of
information. It's
far easier to share a model than to
prevent
its spread. Even sophisticated
watermarking or encryption schemes can
be defeated by determined actors,
verifying that someone if
not developing harmful AI capabilities is
extremely hard. Unlike
nuclear technology, where detection
capabilities roughly match proliferation
methods,
AI governance lacks comparable defensive
tools. Nuclear inspectors can
use satellites and radiation detectors to
monitor compliance. But
verifying that an organisation isn't
developing dangerous AI capabilities
would require invasive access to code,
data and development,
practices likely revealing valuable
intellectual property. Many organizations
thus
refuse intrusive monitoring. This would
require a combination of
many different technical and national
measures. The textbook includes
figure 4.1 seen here. It depicts table of
evasion
techniques to avoid verification methods
under current national technical
means. Dual use nature complicates
controls. The same transformer
architecture that powers beneficial
applications can also enable harmful
uses. Unlike specialized military
technology, we can't simply ban
dangerous AI capabilities without
eliminating beneficial ones. This dual
use problem means governance must be far
more nuanced
than traditional non-proliferation
regimes. A motivated individual with
modest
resources can now fine-tune powerful
models for harmful purposes.
This democratization of capabilities means
threats can emerge from
anywhere, not just nation-states or major
corporations. Traditional governance
frameworks aren't designed for this level
of distributed risk.
How can governance help slow AI
proliferation? Several potential
solutions have been proposed to find the
right balance
between openness and control. targeted
openness, publish fundamental research
but withhold model weights and fine-tuning
recipes for high-risk
capabilities, keeping collaboration alive
while denying turnkey misuse, SEGA
2023. Staged releases. Roll out
progressively stronger versions only
after each tier passes red team audits and
external
review. Giving society time to surface
failure modes and
tighten safeguards before the next step.
Soliman 2023. Enhanced
information security. Treat frontier
checkpoints like key crown jewel
secrets. Hardened build pipelines. Model
weight encryption in use
and at rest. and continuous insider threat
monitoring. Nevo
et al. 2024. Export controls and compute
access restrictions.
Block shipment of the most advanced AI
accelerators to
unvetted end users and require cloud
providers to gate
high-end training clusters behind know-
your-customer checks. O'Brien et al.
2024. Responsible disclosure. Adopt
cybersecurity-style norms for reporting
newly
discovered dangerous capability routes, so
labs alert peers and
regulators without publishing full exploit
paths. O'Brien et al.
2024. Built-in technical breaks. Embed
jailbreak resistant tuning, capability
throttles and provenance watermarks that
survive model distillation, adding
friction even after weight's leak. Dong et
al. 2024.
Section Uncertainty In the words of Greg
Brockman, the
exact way the post-AGI world will look is
hard
to predict. That world will likely be more
different
from today's world than today's is from
the 1500s.
We do not yet know how hard it will
be to make sure AGI's act according to the
values of their operators. Some people
believe it will
be easy, some people believe it'll be
unimaginably difficult,
but no one knows for sure. Expert
predictions consistently
fail to capture AI's actual trajectory. If
you read
media coverage of chat GPT, which called
it breathtaking,
dazzling, astounding, you'd get the sense
that large language
models, LLMs, took the world completely by
surprise. Is
that impression accurate? Actually yes,
GPT-3's capabilities exceeded what
many thought possible with simple scaling.
Each major breakthrough
seems to come from unexpected directions,
making long-term planning
nearly impossible. The scaling hypothesis,
larger models with more
compute reliably produce more capable
systems, has held surprisingly
well. But we don't know if this continues
to
AGI or hits fundamental technical or
economic limits. This
uncertainty has massive governance
implications. If scaling continues,
compute
controls remain effective. If algorithmic
breakthroughs matter more, entirely
different governance approaches are
needed. Risk assessments vary by
orders of magnitude. Some researchers
assign negligible probability to
existential risks from AI, while others
consider them near
certain without intervention, reflecting
fundamental uncertainty about AI's
trajectory
and controllability. When experts disagree
this dramatically, how can
policymakers make informed decisions?
Capability emergence surprises even
developers.
Models demonstrate abilities their
creators didn't anticipate and can't
fully explain. If the people building
these systems can't
predict their capabilities, how can
governance frameworks anticipate what
needs regulating? This unpredictability
compounds with each generation of
more powerful models. Traditional
policymaking assumes predictable outcomes.
Environmental
regulations model pollution impacts. Drug
approval evaluates specific health
effects. But AI governance must prepare
for scenarios ranging
from gradual capability improvements to
sudden recursive self-improvement. Waiting
for certainty means waiting too long. By
the time
we know exactly what AI capabilities will
emerge, it
may be too late to govern them
effectively. Yet
acting under uncertainty risks
implementing wrong-headed policies that
stifle
beneficial development or fail to prevent
actual risks. This
creates a debilitating dilemma for
conscientious policymakers. How can
governance operate under uncertainty?
Adaptive governance models that could
keep pace with rapidly changing technology
could offer a
path forward. Rather than fixed
regulations based on current
understanding, we need frameworks that can
evolve with our
knowledge. This might include regulatory
triggers based on capability
milestones rather than timelines, sunset
clauses that force regular
reconsideration of rules, safe harbours
for experimentation within controlled
environments, rapid response institutions
capable of updating policies as
understanding improves, building consensus
despite uncertainty requires new
approaches.
Traditional policy consensus emerges from
shared understanding of problems
and solutions. With AI, we lack both. Yet
somehow
we must build sufficient agreement to
implement governance before
capabilities outrace our ability to
control them. This may
require focusing on process legitimacy
rather than outcome certainty
agreeing on how to make decisions even
when we
disagree on what to decide. Section
Accountability to quote
Jan Leiker, After resigning from open AI,
these problems
are quite hard to get right, and I am
concerned we aren't on a trajectory to get
there.
Open AI is shouldering an enormous
responsibility on behalf
of all of humanity. But over the past
years,
safety culture and processes have taken a
backseat to
shiny products. We are long overdue in
getting incredibly
serious about the implications of AGI. A
small number
of actors make decisions that affect all
of humanity.
The CEOs of perhaps five companies and key
officials
in three governments largely determine how
Frontier AI develops.
Their choices about what to build, when to
deploy,
and how to ensure safety have consequences
for billions
who have no voice in these decisions. Open
AI's
board has fewer than 10 members.
Anthropics' long-term benefit
trust controls the company with just five
trustees. These
tiny groups make decisions about
technologies that could fundamentally
alter human society. No pharmaceutical
company could release a
new drug with such limited oversight. Yet
AI systems
with far broader impacts face minimal
external scrutiny. Nearly
all Frontier AI development happens in
just two regions,
the San Francisco Bay Area and London. The
values,
assumptions and blind spots of these tech
hubs shape
AI systems used worldwide. Yet we know
more about
how sausages are made than how Frontier AI
systems
are trained. What seems obvious in Palo
Alto might
be alien in Lagos or Jakarta, yet the
global
majority have essentially no input into AI
development. At
this point, the textbook shows figure
4.17. It depicts,
in 2023, most of the notable AI models
originated
from US institutions. Traditional
accountability mechanisms don't apply.
Corporate
boards nominally provide oversight, but
most lack the incentives
to evaluate systemic AI risks. Government
regulators struggle to
keep pace with rapid development. Academic
researchers who might
provide scientific evidence and
independent assessment often depend on
corporate funding or compute access. The
result is a
governance vacuum where no one has both
the capability
and authority needed for proper
governance. The consequences of
this lack of governance are already
becoming apparent. We've
seen AI-generated deepfakes used to spread
political misinformation. Language
models have been used to create convincing
phishing emails
and other scams. When models demonstrate
concerning behaviors, we
can't trace whether they result from
training data, reward
functions, or architectural choices. This
black box nature of
development is a big bottleneck in
accountability. There is
figure 4.1teen in the textbook here. It
depicts diagram
showing the path from auditability to
auditability, ex ante,
to accountability, post hoc, section,
power and wealth concentration.
AI concentrates power in unprecedented
ways. AI systems, especially
those developed by dominant corporations,
are reshaping societal power
structures. These systems determine access
to information and resources,
effectively exercising automated authority
over individuals. As these systems
become more capable, this concentration
intensifies. The organisation that
first develops AGI could gain decisive
advantages across every
domain of human activity. A winner take
all dynamic
with no historical precedent. Wealth
effects compound existing inequalities.
AI automation primarily benefits capital
owners while displacing workers,
deepening existing disparities. Recent
empirical evidence suggests that AI
adoption significantly increases wealth
inequality by disproportionately
benefiting those
who own models, data and computational
resources at the
expense of labour. Without targeted
governance interventions, AI risks
creating never-before-seen levels of
economic inequality, potentially resulting
in
the most unequal society in human history.
The textbook
includes figure 4.9-tine here. It depicts
Swiss cheese model
model, representing one recommended
defense-in-depth strategy against the risk
of undetected and unconstrained power
accumulation. Threat vectors are
in red. Democratic governance faces
existential challenges. When information
itself is controlled by private entities,
traditional democratic institutions
struggle to remain effective. Some
empirical evidence indicates that
higher levels of AI integration correlate
with declining democratic
participation and accountability, as
elected officials find themselves unable
to regulate complex technologies that
evolve faster than legislative
processes. This emerging technocratic
reality fundamentally undermines
democratic principles
regarding public control and oversight.
International disparities threaten global
stability. Countries without domestic AI
capabilities face permanent subordination
to AI leaders. AI adoption significantly
exacerbates international inequalities,
disproportionately favouring
technologically advanced nations. This
disparity threatens not
only economic competitiveness but also
basic sovereignty when critical
decisions are effectively outsourced to
foreign-controlled AI systems. We
have no agreed frameworks for distributing
AI's benefits or
managing its disruptions. Should AI
developers owe obligations to
displaced workers? How should AI-generated
wealth be taxed and
redistributed? What claims do non-
developers have on AI capabilities?
These questions need answers before AI's
impacts become irreversible,
yet governance current discussions barely
acknowledge them. At this
point, the textbook shows figure 4.20. It
depicts, in
the US, the number of graduates with
bachelor's degrees
in computing has increased 22% over the
last 10
years. Yet access remains limited in many
African countries
due to basic infrastructure gaps like
electricity.