Section 4.6 Implementation Section AI
Safety Standards What approaches
exist for developing AI safety standards
at the national
level? Various approaches to developing
safety standards exist within
national contexts. From government-led
standardization bodies to public-private
collaborative
processes. National standards bodies play
a critical role in
developing and implementing AI safety
standards that align with
each country's policy priorities and
technological capabilities. The EU
AI Act demonstrates this through its
requirement for a
code of practice that specifies high-level
obligations for general-purpose
AI models. In the United States, the
National Institute
of Standards and Technology, NIST, has
developed an AI
risk management framework that serves as a
voluntary standard
within American jurisdiction. In 2021, the
Standardization Administration of
China, SAC, released a roadmap for AI
standards development
that includes over 100 technical and
ethical specifications from
algorithmic transparency to biometric
recognition safety. coordinated by
government
agencies such as the Ministry of Industry
and Information
Technology, MIIT, and the China Electronic
Standardization Institute, CESE.
Unlike in the US or EU, where standards
are
often multi-stakeholder-developed or
market-driven, China's process is highly
centralized
and closely linked to its broader
geopolitical ambitions. How
do national standards bodies develop
effective AI safety standards?
National standards have experience in
governing various socio-technical issues
within their countries. For example,
national cybersecurity standards have
spread across industries. Environmental
sustainability standards have prompted
significant
corporate investments. and safety
standards have been implemented across
sectors, from automotive to energy.
Expertise from other high-stakes
industries can be leveraged to develop
effective AI safety
standards tailored to a country's specific
needs and regulatory
environment. National standards can be
used to spread a
culture of safety and responsibility in AI
research and
development in four ways. The criteria
within standards establish
rules and expectations for safety
practices within the country's
AI ecosystem. Standards embed individual
researchers and organisations within
a larger network of domestic
accountability. Regular implementation of
standards helps researchers internalise
safety routines as part of
standard practice. When standards are
embedded in products and
software packages, they reinforce safety
considerations regardless of which
domestic organisations use the system.
These mechanisms help create
what some researchers have called a safety
mindset, among
AI practitioners within the national AI
ecosystem. National standards
serve as effective tools for fostering a
culture of
responsibility and safety in AI
development, which is essential
for long-term societal benefit. Section
Regulatory Visibility Regulatory
visibility
requires active, independent scrutiny of
AI systems before, during
and after deployment. As frontier AI
systems become increasingly
integrated into society, external
scrutiny, involving outside actors in
the evaluation of AI systems, offers a
powerful tool
for enhancing safety and accountability.
Effective external scrutiny should
adhere to the ASPIRE framework, which
proposes six criteria
for effective external evaluation. Access.
External scrutineers need appropriate
access to AI systems and relevant
information. Searching attitude.
Scrutineers should actively seek out
potential issues and vulnerabilities.
Proportionality to the risks. The level of
scrutiny should
match the potential risks posed by the
system. Independence.
Scrutineers should be free from undue
influence from AI
developers. Resources Adequate resources
must support thorough scrutiny. Expertise.
Scrutineers must possess the necessary
technical and domain-specific expertise.
Some countries are exploring model
registries, which are centralized
databases that include architectural
details, training procedures, performance
metrics,
and societal impact assessments. These
registries support structured oversight
and can act as early warning systems for
emerging
capabilities. helping regulators detect
dangerous trends before they materialize
as harms. Different jurisdictions take
different approaches, but model
documentation typically encompasses basic
documentation, model identification,
intended use
cases. technical specification,
architecture, parameters, computational
requirements, performance documentation,
benchmark results, capability evaluations,
impact assessment, societal effects,
safety
implications, ethical considerations.
deployment documentation, implementation
strategies, monitoring plans.
Another method of regulatory visibility
for AI is the
Know Your Customer KYC system. KYC systems
are already
an established part of financial
regulation used to detect
and prevent money laundering and terrorist
financing. They have
proven effective in their ability to
identify high-risk actors
before a transaction takes place. the same
principle can
be applied to compute access. As discussed
in the
compute governance section, frontier
models require massive computational
resources,
often concentrated in a small number of
hyperscale providers
who serve as natural regulatory choke
points. A KYC
system for AI would enable governments to
detect the
development of potentially hazardous
systems early, prevent covert model
training and implement export controls or
licensing requirements with
greater precision. Since this approach
targets capability thresholds, rather
than use cases, it could serve as a
preventative
tool for risk management, rather than a
reactive one
to deployment failures. However,
implementing a KYC regime for
compute involves several open questions.
Providers would need clear
legal mandates, technical criteria for
client verification, and processes
for escalating high-risk cases to
authorities. Jurisdictional fragmentation
is
a challenge. Many developers rely on
globally distributed compute
services, and without international
cooperation, KYC regimes risk being
undercut by regulatory arbitrage. To be
effective, a compute-based
KYC system would need to align with other
transparency
mechanisms, such as model registries and
incident reporting systems.
How can national policies support
responsible information sharing?
Responsible
reporting of information is important for
both self-regulation and
government oversight. As we discussed in
the Corporate Governance
section, companies developing and
deploying frontier AI systems have
primary access to information about their
system's capabilities and
potential risks. And sharing this
information responsibly can significantly
improve the state's ability to manage AI
risks. National
policies must address the tension between
transparency and proprietary
control. One approach is tiered disclosure
in which technical
documentation is provided to regulators
under confidentiality agreements while
public communication remains high-level
and risk-focused. Another approach is
through anonymized or aggregated sharing
of data, which enables
statistical insight without revealing
sensitive implementation details. Although
incident
reporting systems from other industries,
such as the Confidential
and Non-Punitive Aviation Safety Reporting
System, ASRS, in the
United States, offer useful precedents, no
equivalent system yet
exists for AI. In aviation, it is clear
what
constitutes an incident or near miss. But
with AI,
the lines can be blurry. Adapting this
model would
require clear definitions of what
constitutes an incident, with
structured categories ranging from model
misbehavior to societal harms.
Current national efforts on this are
fragmented. In the
EU, the AI Act mandates reporting of
serious incidents
by high-risk and general-purpose AI
developers. In China, the
cyberspace administration is building a
centralized infrastructure for real-time
reporting of critical failures under
cybersecurity law. In the
United States, incident reporting remains
sector-specific, with preliminary efforts
underway in health and national security.
Section, ensuring compliance.
What regulatory tools can ensure
compliance with AI safety
standards? For high-risk AI systems,
oversight mechanisms must go
beyond voluntary standards or one-time
evaluations. Many researchers have
proposed licensing regimes that would
mirror regulatory practices in
sectors such as pharmaceuticals or nuclear
energy. In these
domains, operators must obtain and
maintain licenses by demonstrating
continuous compliance with strict safety
and documentation requirements. Applied
to Frontier AI, this approach would
involve formal approval
processes before model deployment,
periodic audits and the ability
for authorities to revoke licenses in
cases of non-compliance.
A credible licensing framework would
require developers to submit
a structured safety case, which is a
formal argument
supported by evidence showing that a
system meets safety
thresholds for deployment. This could
include threat modelling, red
teaming results, interpretability
evaluations and post-deployment monitoring
plans. Safety
cases provide a mechanism for both ex-
anti-approval and for
tracking whether safety claims continue to
hold as systems
evolve in deployment. Embedding these
requirements into the licensing
process can help governments establish a
continuous cycle of
review, feedback and technical
verification. How would enforcement work
in practice? Licensing frameworks must be
supported by agencies
with the power to investigate violations,
impose sanctions and
suspend development. National enforcement
practices vary between horizontal
governance,
applying general rules across sectors, and
vertical regimes, targeting
specific domains like healthcare or
finance. For example, the
European Union's AI Act establishes
enforcement authority through horizontal
governance framework with the European AI
Office, which can
investigate, issue fines up to 3% of
global annual
turnover, and mandate corrective action
combined with mandatory incident
reporting. systemic risk mitigation
requirements and are supporting codes
of practice for GPAI models. In contrast,
China's cyberspace
administration, CAC, exercises centralized
enforcement powers under a vertical
regulatory framework. While its approach
prioritizes rapid intervention and
censorship compliance, the CAC lacks
transparent procedural checks and
often relies on vague criteria for
enforcement. In the
United States, enforcement is fragmented.
While export controls are
strictly applied through agencies like the
Department of Commerce,
broader AI safety compliance has been
delegated to individual
agencies with no national licensing
authority. As a result,
enforcement actions are often reactive and
domain-specific and rely
on discretionary executive powers.
Striking the right balance between
these approaches will depend on
institutional capacity, developer
incentives,
and the pace of AI advancement. In some
cases,
using existing sectoral authorities may
suffice. In others, new
institutions will be required to handle
general-purpose capabilities that
fall outside traditional regulatory
categories. The textbook includes Figure
4.34 here. It depicts the flow from safety
cases
to enforcement, section, limitations and
trade-offs. Every governance approach
faces fundamental constraints that no
amount of institutional design
can fully overcome. Understanding these
limitations helps set realistic
expectations and identifies where
innovation is most needed. Some
risks resist technical solutions. Despite
advances in interpretability and
evaluation, we still cannot fully
understand or predict AI
behavior. Black box models make
verification difficult. Emergent
capabilities
appear unexpectedly. The gap between our
governance ambitions and
technical capabilities are substantial.
Current safety techniques like RLHF
and Constitutional AI show promise for
today's models, but
may fail catastrophically with more
capable systems. We're building
governance frameworks around safety
approaches that might become obsolete.
This fundamental uncertainty requires
adaptive frameworks that can evolve
with understanding. Measurement challenges
undermine accountability. We lack robust
metrics for many safety-relevant
properties. How do you measure
a model's tendency toward deception? Its
potential for autonomous
improvement. Its resistance to misuse.
Without reliable measurements, compliance
becomes a matter of interpretation rather
than verification. The
EU AI Act, for example, requires systemic
risk assessments
but provides limited guidance on how to
measure such
risks quantitatively. Expertise shortages
create critical bottlenecks. The number
of individuals who deeply understand both
advanced AI systems
and governance remains extremely limited,
and this gap exists
at every level from company safety teams
and regulators
to international bodies. A lack of
interdisciplinary talent undermines
efforts to anticipate and manage emerging
risks. Institutional capacity
for technical evaluation and oversight is
similarly weak in
many jurisdictions. Governments struggle
to attract and retain the
expertise as needed to regulate powerful
AI models. AMN's
technically literate, governance-aware
professionals may be the most serious
constraint on effective AI governance.
Much of the existing
talent is concentrated in a few dominant
firms, limiting
public sector oversight and reinforcing
asymmetries in governance capacity.
Coordination costs escalate faster than
capabilities. Each additional stakeholder,
requirement and review process adds
friction to AI development.
While some friction helps ensure safety,
excessive bureaucracy can
drive development to less responsible
actors or underground entirely.
Speed mismatches create fundamental
governance gaps. AI capabilities advance
in months, while international agreements
take years to negotiate.
GPT-4's capabilities surprised experts in
March 2023. By the
time regulatory responses emerged in 2024,
the technology had
moved on to multimodal systems and AI
agents. Safety
researchers emphasised precaution and
worst-case scenarios. Companies
prioritised competitive
position and time to market. Governments
balance multiple constituencies
with conflicting demands and users want
beneficial capabilities without
understanding risks. Regulatory arbitrage
undermines safety standards across
borders.
If Europe implements strict safety
requirements while other regions
remain permissive, development may simply
shift locations. As we
previously discussed in the proliferation
section, the digital nature
of AI makes it so that a model can
be trained in Singapore, deployed from
Ireland and used
globally. Companies may bifurcate
offerings, providing safer systems to
regulated markets while deploying riskier
versions elsewhere. True global
coverage requires more than powerful
individual jurisdictions.