Section 4.9 Appendix National Governance A
comprehensive domestic governance
regime for AI safety requires three
interconnected mechanisms. Development
of safety standards, regulatory visibility
and compliance enforcement. And
Elyung et al. 2023. Safety standards form
the foundation
of AI governance by establishing clear,
measurable criteria for
the development, testing and deployment of
AI systems within
national jurisdictions. These standards
must be technically precise while
remaining flexible enough to accommodate
rapid technological advancement. Effective
standards serve as institutional tools for
coordination and provide
the infrastructure needed to develop new
AI technologies in
a controlled manner within a country's
regulatory boundaries. What
lessons can national AI governance draw
from nuclear safety
regulation? The regulatory approach used
for nuclear safety provides
an instructive model for national AI
safety standardization. The
five-level hierarchy used in nuclear
safety standards, ranging from
fundamental principles to specific
implementation guides, offers a blueprint
for developing comprehensive AI safety
standards. This multi-level framework
allows principals established at higher
levels to be incorporated
into more specific guidelines at lower
levels, creating a
coherent and thorough regulatory system
that can be implemented
within national jurisdictions. Key lessons
from nuclear regulation applicable
to national AI governance include
standardized safety frameworks. Just
as nuclear regulation established
standardized frameworks for safety,
national
AI governance can standardize the
behavior, learning, and decision-making
criteria of AI systems to enhance
technology safety within
the country's borders. Independent
supervision mechanisms. Nuclear regulatory
authorities
established independent supervisory
systems for monitoring and evaluating
safety.
Similarly, national AI governance can
establish neutral bodies to
continuously monitor and evaluate the
operation and performance of
AI systems. Regular protocols and
exercises. Nuclear safety regulators
conduct regular protocols and exercises
for responding to incidents.
Similar approaches can be developed at the
national level
for promptly responding to AI-related
accidents or abnormal behaviors.
information sharing mechanisms, nuclear
regulatory systems, established platforms
for
sharing safety standards, research, and
incident information across sectors.
Similar platforms can be developed for AI
at the
national level to share research,
technology, and incident information
across industries. CHEAAR 2024 Section
European Union. What legislative
foundation has the EU established for AI
governance? The
European Union broke new ground with the
EU-AI Act,
the world's first comprehensive legal
framework for artificial intelligence.
Initially proposed in 2001 and formally
adopted in March
2024, this horizontally integrated
legislation regulates AI systems based
on their potential risks and safeguards
the rights of
EU citizens. At its core is a risk-based
approach
that classifies AI systems into four
distinct categories. unacceptable
risk, high risk, limited risk and minimal
risk. Unacceptable
risk AI systems, such as those that
manipulate human
behaviour or exploit vulnerabilities, are
banned outright. High risk
AI systems, including those used in
critical infrastructure, education
and employment, face strict requirements
and oversight. Limited risk
AI systems require transparency measures,
while minimal risk AI
systems are largely unregulated. How is
the EU AI
Act being implemented? The Act entered
into force in
August 2024 and is being implemented in
phases. From
February 2, 2025, the ban on prohibited AI
practices,
social scoring, certain biometric
identification systems, and requirements
for
staff AI literacy took effect. From August
2, 2025,
obligations for general-purpose AI, GP AI
model providers will
apply, including documentation, copyright
compliance, and data transparency. The
legislation establishes the European AI
Office to oversee implementation
and enforcement, coordinating compliance,
providing guidance to businesses and
enforcing the rules. This dedicated body
serves as the
leading agency enforcing binding AI rules
on a multinational
coalition, positioned to shape global AI
governance similar to
how GDPR restructured international
privacy standards. what additional
requirements
exist for high-risk and systemic-risk AI
systems. For GP
AI models, presenting systemic risks
identified either by surpassing
a computational threshold, 10 to the 25th
flops, or
based on potential impact criteria such as
scalability and
risk of large-scale harm. Additional
obligations apply. Providers must
conduct adversarial testing, track and
report serious incidents, implement
strong cybersecurity measures, and
proactively mitigate systemic risks. The
European AI Office facilitated the
drafting of a General
Purpose AI Code of Practice, completed in
April 2025,
providing a central tool for GP AI model
providers
to comply with the Act's requirements.
While compliance through
this code is voluntary, it offers
providers a clear
practical pathway to demonstrate
adherence. How does the EU
approach enforcement and penalties? The EU
AI Office serves
as the enforcement authority, empowered to
request information, conduct
evaluations, mandate corrective measures,
and impose fines of up
to 3% of a provider's global annual
turnover or
$15 million. whichever is higher. This
represents a substantial
enforcement mechanism, though slightly
lower than the 7% maximum
mentioned in earlier drafts of the
legislation. The fines
for non-compliance are quite high,
demonstrating the EU's strong
commitment to ensuring adherence to its
regulatory framework. What
values and priorities drive the EU's
approach? The EU
has demonstrated a clear prioritization
for the protection of
citizens' rights. The EU-AI Act's core
approach to categorising
risk levels is designed primarily around
measuring the ability
of AI systems to infringe on the rights of
EU citizens. This can be observed in the
list
of use cases deemed to be high risk, such
as educational or vocational training,
employment, migration and asylum,
and administration of justice or
democratic processes. Most of
the requirements are designed with the
common citizen in
mind, including transparency and reporting
requirements, the ability of
any citizen to lodge a complaint with a
market
surveillance authority, prohibitions on
social scoring systems, and anti-
discrimination
requirements. This rights-based approach
contrasts markedly with China's focus
on social control and the US emphasis on
geopolitical
competition. At this point, the textbook
shows Figure 4.35.
It depicts the EU-AI Act. Classification
of general-purpose AI
models with systemic risks. Observatorio
de riesgos catastróficos globales.
Section, United States. How has US policy
on AI
governance changed? AI governance in the
United States has
shifted significantly since the 2024
election. President Donald Trump
overturned the previous administration's
executive order on safe, secure
and trustworthy AI from October 2023.
which had introduced
requirements for developers of advanced AI
systems to share
safety test results with the federal
government. In January
2025, Executive Order on 4179 explicitly
revoked the previous
AI Safety Executive Order and directed
federal agencies to
review policies to remove barriers to
innovation and ensure
AI systems are free from ideological bias
or engineered
social agendas. A separate executive order
on AI infrastructure
prioritized national security, economic
competitiveness, domestic data center
development,
and workforce development standards. What
characterized the US approach
before this shift? Prior to these changes,
the US
had taken an approach centered around
executive orders and
non-binding declarations due to
legislative gridlock in Congress. Three
key executive actions shaped this
approach. The US-China semiconductor
export controls launched in October 2022,
the blueprint for
an AI Bill of Rights released in October
2022,
and the executive order on artificial
intelligence issued in
October 2023. The semiconductor export
controls marked a significant
escalation in US efforts to restrict
China's access to
advanced computing and AI technologies by
banning the export
of advanced chips, chip-making equipment
and semiconductor expertise to
China. What distinctive features define
the US regulatory philosophy?
The US has taken a distinctive approach to
AI
governance by controlling the hardware and
computational power required
to train and develop AI models. It is
uniquely
positioned to leverage this compute-based
approach to regulation as
home to all leading vendors of high-end AI
chips,
NVIDIA, AMD, Intel, giving it direct
legislative control over
these chips. Beyond export controls, the
US has pursued
a decentralized, largely non-binding
approach relying on executive action.
Due to structural challenges in passing
binding legislation through
a divided Congress, the U.S. has relied
primarily on
executive orders and agency actions that
don't require congressional
approval, distributing research and
regulatory processes among selected
agencies.
What is the current state of U.S. AI
governance?
In February 2025, the Office of Management
and Budget
released Memorandum M2521, directing
federal agencies to accelerate AI
adoption, minimize bureaucratic hurdles,
empower agency-level AI leadership, and
implement minimum risk management
practices for high-impact AI systems.
At the state level, California's SB 1047,
which attempted
to address risks associated with frontier
models, was vetoed
in September 2024. A new bill, SB 53,
focusing
on whistleblower protections for employees
reporting critical AI risks,
has been introduced. The USAI Safety
Institute remains active
despite the federal policy shift,
continuing to develop testing
methodologies and conduct model
evaluations. How does geopolitics
influence
USAI policy? USAI policy strongly
prioritizes its geopolitical competition
with China. The US-AI governance strategy
is heavily influenced
by the perceived threat of China's rapid
advancements in
AI and the potential implications for
national security and
the global balance of power. The binding
actions taken
by the US in forcing semiconductor export
controls are
explicitly designed to counter China's AI
ambitions and maintain
US technological and military superiority.
This geopolitical focus sets
the US apart from the EU, which has
prioritized
the protection of individual rights, and
China, which has
prioritized internal social control. The
US strategy appears more
concerned with the strategic implications
of AI and ensuring
that the technology aligns with US
interests in the
global arena. There is figure 4.36 in the
textbook
here. It depicts number of AI-related
regulations in the
United States, 2016 and 2023. Section,
China. How has
China's approach to AI governance evolved?
China has developed
a distinctive vertical iterative
regulatory approach to AI governance,
passing targeted regulations for specific
domains of AI applications
one at a time. This approach contrasts
sharply with
the EU's comprehensive horizontal
framework. China's regulatory evolution
began
with the algorithmic recommendation
provisions in August 2021, which
established the world's first mandatory
algorithm registry and required
all qualifying algorithms used by Chinese
organizations to be
registered within 10 days of public
launch. This was
followed by the deep synthesis provisions
in November 2022,
which regulated algorithms that
synthetically generate content to combat
deep fakes by requiring labelling, user
identification and prevention
of misuse as defined by the government.
What are
the current regulatory measures in place?
China strengthened its
AI governance framework with the
implementation of the interim
measures for the management of generative
artificial intelligence services
in August 2023. These measures were a
direct response
to chat GPT and expanded policies to
better encompass
multi-use LLMs, imposing risk-based
oversight with higher scrutiny for
systems capable of influencing public
opinion. Under these regulations,
providers must ensure lawful data use,
protect intellectual property,
respect user privacy, and uphold socialist
core values. In
2024, China officially elevated AI safety
to the level
of national security and public safety,
requiring AI providers
to actively moderate illegal or harmful
content and report
violations to the cyberspace
administration of China, CAC, the
primary regulatory body overseeing China's
AI industry, what regulatory
developments are on the horizon. In March
2025, China
released the final measures for labelling
artificial intelligence-generated content,
taking effect on September 1, 2025. These
measures mandate
explicit labels for AI-generated content
that could mislead the
public, alongside metadata identifying the
provider. China is also
preparing to implement the Regulation on
Network Data Security
Management in 2025. These iterative
regulations appear to be
building toward a comprehensive artificial
intelligence law proposed in
a legislative plan released in June 233.
This pattern
mirrors China's approach to Internet
regulation in the 2000s,
which culminated in the all-encompassing
cybersecurity law of 2017.
What distinctive features characterised
China's regulatory philosophy? The CAC
has focused primarily on regulating
algorithms with the potential
for social influence rather than
prioritizing domains like healthcare,
employment, or judicial systems that
receive more attention in
Western regulatory frameworks. The
language used in these regulations
is typically broad and nonspecific,
extending greater control to
the CAC for interpretation and
enforcement. For example, Article
5 of the Interim Generative AI Measures
states that
providers should encourage the innovative
application of generative AI
technology in each industry and field and
generate exceptional
content that is positive, healthy and
uplifting. This demonstrates
China's strong prioritization of social
control and alignment with
government values in its AI regulations.
How is China
implementing its regulatory vision at
different levels? At the
municipal level, Shanghai and Beijing
launched AI safety labs
in mid-2024, and over 40 AI safety
evaluations have
reportedly been conducted by government-
backed research centres. China has
demonstrated an inward focus, primarily
regulating Chinese organisations and
citizens. Major international AI labs,
such as OpenAI, Anthropic
and Google, do not actively serve Chinese
consumers, partly
due to unwillingness to comply with
China's censorship policies.
This has resulted in Chinese AI governance
operating largely
on a parallel and disjoint basis to
Western AI
governance approaches. The textbook
includes Figure 4.37 here. It
depicts in 2024 Chinese institutions
significantly increased publication of
Frontier AI safety papers compared to 2023
from approximately
7 papers per month in 2023 to 18 per
month in 2024.