Section 4.5 – Governance Architectures The
governance of Frontier
AI cannot be entrusted to any single
institution or
level of authority. Companies lack
incentives to fully account
for societal impacts. Nations compete for
technological advantage and
international bodies struggle with
capacity for enforcement. Each level
of governance, corporate, national and
international, brings unique strengths
and faces distinct limitations.
Understanding how these levels interact
and reinforce each other is important for
building effective
AI governance systems. There is figure
4.21 in the
textbook here. It depicts the three levels
of AI
governance. Corporate governance provides
speed and technical expertise. Companies
developing frontier AI have unmatched
visibility into emerging capabilities
and can implement safety measures faster
than any external
regulator. They control critical decision
points, architecture design, training
protocols, capability evaluations, and
deployment criteria. When OpenAI
discovered
that GPT-4 could engage in deceptive
behavior, they could
immediately modify training procedures,
something that would take months
or years through regulatory channels.
National governance establishes democratic
legitimacy and enforcement power. While
companies can act quickly,
they lack the authority to make decisions
affecting entire
populations. National governments provide
the democratic mandate and enforcement
mechanisms necessary for binding
regulations. The EU-AI Act demonstrates
this by establishing legal requirements
backed by fines up
to 3% of global revenue, creating real
consequences for
non-compliance that voluntary corporate
measures cannot match. International
governance
addresses global externalities and
coordination failures. AI risks don't
respect borders. A dangerous model
developed in one country
can affect the entire world through
digital proliferation. International
mechanisms help align incentives between
nations, preventing races to
the bottom and ensuring consistent safety
standards. The International
Network of AI Safety Institutes, launched
in 2024, exemplifies
how countries can share best practices and
coordinate standards
despite competitive pressures. The
textbook includes Figure 4.222 here.
It depicts how the levels interact and
reinforce. Governance
levels create reinforcing feedback loops.
Corporate safety frameworks inform
national regulations, which shape
international standards, which in turn
influence corporate practices globally.
When Anthropic introduced its responsible
scaling policy in 2023, it provided a
template that
influenced both the US Executive Order's
compute thresholds and
discussions at international AI summits.
This cross-pollination accelerates the
development of effective governance
approaches. Gaps at one level
create pressure at others. When corporate
self-governance proves insufficient,
pressure builds for national regulation.
When national approaches diverge
too sharply, creating regulatory
arbitrage, demand grows for international
coordination. This dynamic tension drives
governance evolution, though it
can also create dangerous gaps during
transition periods. Different
levels handle different timescales and
uncertainties. Corporate governance excels
at rapid response to technical
developments but struggles with
long-term planning under competitive
pressure. National governance can
establish
stable frameworks but move slowly.
International governance provides long-
term
coordination but faces the greatest
implementation challenges. Together, they
create a temporal portfolio addressing
both immediate and systemic
risks. Section Corporate Governance To
quote Elon Musk, AI
is a rare case where I think we need
to be proactive in regulation than be
reactive. I
think that digital superintelligence is
the single biggest existential
crisis that we face and the most pressing
one.
It needs to be a public body that has
insight and then oversight to confirm that
everyone is
developing AI safely. And mark my words,
AI is
far more dangerous than nukes, far. So why
do
we have no regulatory oversight? This is
insane. Dario
Amade once wrote, Almost every decision I
make feels
like it's balanced on the edge of a knife.
If we don't build fast enough,
authoritarian countries could
win. If we build too fast, the kinds of
risks we've written about could prevail.
In this section,
we'll look at how AI companies approach
governance in
practice. We'll look at what works, what
doesn't, and
where gaps remain. This will help us
understand why
corporate governance alone isn't enough
and set the scene
for later discussions of national and
international governance. By
the end of this section, we'll establish
both the
essential role of company-level governance
and why it needs
to be complemented by broader regulatory
frameworks. Corporate governance
refers to the internal structures,
practices and processes that
determine how AI companies make safety
relevant decisions. Companies
developing Frontier AI have unique
visibility into emerging capabilities
and can implement safety measures faster
than external regulators.
Sastri et al. 2024. They have the
technical knowledge
and direct control needed to implement
effective safeguards. But
they also face immense market pressures
that can push
against taking time for safety measures.
It includes policies,
oversight structures, technical protocols,
and organizational norms that companies
use to ensure safety throughout the AI
development process.
These mechanisms translate high-level
principles into operational decisions
within
labs and development teams. Internal
corporate governance mechanisms matter
because frontier AI companies currently
have significant freedom in
governing their own systems. Their
proximity to development allows
them to identify and address risks earlier
and more
effectively than external oversight alone
could achieve. However, internal
governance alone cannot address systemic
risks. These require public
oversight, which we explore later in this
chapter. At
this point, there is Interactive Figure
4.5 in the
textbook, available in the online version.
It shows affiliation
of research teams building notable AI
systems by year
of publication, describes the sector where
the authors of
a notable AI system have their primary
affiliations. AI
companies control the most sensitive
stages of model development.
Architecture design, training runs,
capability evaluations, deployment
criteria and
safety protocols. Well-designed internal
governance can reduce risks by
aligning safety priorities with day-to-day
decision-making, embedding escalation
procedures
and enforcing constraints before
deployment. It includes proactive measures
like pausing training runs, restricting
access to high-risk capabilities
and auditing internal model use. Because
external actors often
lack access to proprietary information,
internal governance is the
first line of defence. especially for
models that have
not yet been released. In the words of
International
AI Safety Report, deployment can take
several forms. Internal
deployment for use by the system's
developer, or external
deployment either publicly or to private
customers. Very little
is publicly known about internal
deployments. However, companies are
known to adopt different types of
strategies for external
deployment. Internally deployed systems
also need governance of safeguards.
Just because a model is not deployed
publicly should
not mean the corporate governance
safeguards do not apply.
We have seen in previous chapters that
automating AI,
R&D, is one of the core goals of several
AI companies. This combined with
proliferation safeguards and public
release mitigations means that we can see
many models
that are heavily used internally but not
available to
the public. These internal deployments
often lack the scrutiny
applied to external launches and may
operate with elevated
privileges, bypass formal evaluations, and
evolve capabilities through iterative
use before external stakeholders are even
aware of their
existence. Without policies that
explicitly cover internal use, such
as access controls, internal deployment
approvals, or safeguards against
recursive model use, high-risk systems may
advance unchecked. Yet
public knowledge of these deployments are
limited. and most
governance efforts still focus on public-
facing releases. Strengthening internal
governance around internal deployment is
critical to ensure that
early and potentially hazardous use cases
are properly supervised.
At this point, the textbook shows Figure
4.23. It
depicts the figure illustrates a self-
reinforcing loop in which
AI systems progressively automate AI
research, leading to increasingly
capable AI that further accelerates its
own development. Organizational
structures establish who makes decisions
and who is responsible
for safety in AI companies. Later sections
cover specific
safety mechanisms. Here we focus on the
governance question.
who has the authority within companies to
prioritize safety
over other goals. For example, an
effective governance structure
determines whether a safety team can delay
a model
release if they identify concerns, whether
executives can override
safety decisions, and whether the board
has final authority
over high-risk deployments. These
authority relationships directly affect
how
safety considerations factor into
development decisions. Corporate AI
governance
needs a combination of roles, board-level
oversight, AI risk
executives, and technical safety teams.
Effective AI governance requires
three interconnected levels of internal
oversight, board-level oversight
structures
allocating resources and enforcing safety
policies such as algorithm
review boards, ARBs, and ethics boards for
technical and
societal risk assessments, guiding go-
slash-no-go decisions on deployments and
establishing oversight with clear lines of
accountability. executives allocating
resources and enforcing safety policies,
roles like the Chief
Artificial Intelligence Officer, CARIO,
GO, Chief Risk Officer, CRO,
and related positions to coordinate risk
management efforts across
the organization and help translate
ethical principles into practice,
Schaefer et al. 2022, Janssen et al. less
2025,
technical safety teams conducting
evaluations and recommending mitigations,
teams
comprising internal auditors, risk
officers and specialized audit committees
for ensuring rigorous risk identification,
maintaining audit integrity and
providing operational assurance with
direct reporting lines to the
Board for Independence. Chouette 2023,
Raji et al. 2020.
The textbook has a supplementary note
titled Open AI's
Corporate Restructuring, which will skip
over here. There is
figure 4.4 in the textbook here. It
depicts Swiss
cheese model representing our recommended
defense-in-depth strategy against the
risk of loss of control via internally
deployed misaligned
AI. Threat vectors are in red. Subsection
Frontier Safety
Framework Frontier Safety Framework's FSFs
are one example of
corporate AI governance. FSFs are policies
that AI companies
create to guide their development process
and ensure they're
taking appropriate precautions as their
systems become more capable.
They're the equivalent of the safety
protocols used in
nuclear power plants or high-security
laboratories, and help bridge
internal corporate governance mechanisms
and external regulatory oversight in
AI safety. The concept of a FSF was first
introduced in 2023. They gained momentum
during the Seoul
AI Summit in May 2024, where 16 companies
committed
to implementing such policies. As of March
2025, 12
companies have published comprehensive
Frontier AI safety policies. Anthropic,
OpenAI, Google DeepMind, Magic, Naver,
Meta, G42, Cohere, Microsoft,
Amazon, XAI, and Nvidia, with additional
companies following suit.
They go under different names. For
example, OpenAI calls
their FSF the preparedness framework, and
Anthropic calls them
responsible scaling policies, RSPs. They
are very similar in
principle. What essential elements define
a comprehensive FSF? Despite
variations in implementation, most FSFs
share several fundamental elements.
Capability thresholds, FSFs, establish
specific thresholds at which AI
capabilities would pose severe risks
requiring enhanced safeguards. NEVO
et al. 2024 Common capability concerns
include biological weapons
assistance, such as enabling the creation
of dangerous pathogens,
cyber-offensive capabilities, such as
automating zero-day exploit discovery,
automated
AI research and development, such as
accelerating AI progress
beyond human oversight, autonomous
replication and adaptation. Model weight
security. As models approach dangerous
capability thresholds, companies implement
increasingly sophisticated security
measures to prevent unauthorized access to
model weights. These range from standard
information security protocols
to advanced measures like restricted
access environments, encryption and
specialized hardware security. NEVO et al.
2024. Conditions for
halting development deployment. Most
frameworks contain explicit commitments to
pause model development or deployment if
capability thresholds are
crossed before adequate safeguards can be
implemented. Full capability
elicitation Through FSFs, companies commit
to evaluating models in
ways that reveal their full capabilities
rather than underestimating
them. Fuang et al. 2024 Evaluation
frequency and timing
FSFs establish specific timelines for when
evaluations must occur.
typically before deployment, during
training and after deployment, with
triggers for additional assessments when
models show significant capability
increases. Davidson et al. 2023.
Accountability mechanisms. These include
internal governance roles, for example,
Anthropics responsible scaling officer,
external advisory boards and third-party
audits, transparency commitments about
model capabilities and safety measures.
whistleblower protections for staff
reporting safety concerns. Policy Updates
All FSFs acknowledge the
evolving nature of AI risks and commit to
regular
policy reviews and updates as
understanding of risks and
best practices improve. METR 2025 A multi-
layered internal auditing
and governance approach helps
operationalize safety frameworks in
practice.
When actually implementing the safety
frameworks, organizations should ensure
risks are identified and managed at
multiple levels, reducing
the chances of dangerous oversights. For
example, when researchers
develop a model with unexpectedly advanced
capabilities, safety teams
can conduct thorough evaluations and
implement additional safeguards, while
audit teams review broader processes for
managing emergent capabilities.
One approach is the three lines of
defence, three
LOD model, adapted from other safety
critical industries, first
line of defence. Frontline researchers and
developers implement safety
measures in day-to-day work, conduct
initial risk assessments, and
adhere to ethical guidelines and safety
protocols. Second line
of defence, specialised risk management
and compliance functions, including
AI ethics committees, dedicated safety
teams and compliance units
provide oversight and guidance. Third line
of defence. Independent
internal audit functions provide assurance
to board and senior
management through regular audits of
safety practices, independent model
evaluations and assessments of overall
preparedness. The textbook includes
Figure 4.25 here. It depicts the 3LOD
model as
described above. At this point, the
textbook shows Figure
4.26. It depicts sample org chart of an AI
company with equivalent responsibilities
for each of the three
lines. FSFs need to account for
capabilities that don't
yet exist. AI capabilities are fast
growing and changing.
FSFs incorporate techniques from other
safety critical industries adapted
to AI development. scenario analysis,
exploring potential future scenarios
like an AI system developing deceptive
behaviors or unexpected
emergent capabilities, fishbone analysis,
identifying potential causes of alignment
failures such as insufficient safety
research, deployment pressure or
inadequate testing, causal mapping,
visualizing how research decisions, safety
measures and deployment strategies
interact to influence overall risk,
Delphi technique, gathering expert
opinions through structured rounds of
questionnaires to synthesize diverse
perspectives on potential risks. BOTI
analysis, mapping pathways between causes,
hazardous events and consequences,
along with prevention and mitigation
measures. There is figure
4.27 in the textbook here. It depicts
example of
BOTI analysis technique. Even with
rigorous pre-deployment safeguards,
dangerous
capabilities may emerge after deployment.
FSFs increasingly incorporate deployment
corrections, which are comprehensive
contingency plans for scenarios where
pre-deployment risk management falls
short. Technical controls for maintaining
continuous control over deployed models
through monitoring and modification
capabilities supported by pre-built
rollback mechanisms. Organizational
preparedness for
establishing dedicated incident response
teams trained in rapid risk
assessment and mitigation. legal framework
for creating clear user
agreements that establish the operational
framework for emergency interventions,
model shutdown such as full market removal
or the
destruction of the model and associated
components, subsection limitation.
Here is a quote by Demis Hassabis. These
kinds
of decisions are too big for any one
person.
We need to build more robust governing
structures that
don't put this in the hands of just a
few people. FSFs represent a corporate
self-regulation mechanism, which
represents progress, but it might be
insufficient. FSFs give
companies a way to demonstrate their
commitment to proactive
risk management. Their public nature
enables external scrutiny, while
their risk categorization frameworks show
engagement with potential failure
modes. The framework's deliberately
flexible structure allows adaptation as
understanding of AI risks evolves. While
FSFs represent progress
in AI governance, their effectiveness
ultimately depends on implementation.
Companies like Anthropic and OpenAI have
established notable governance
mechanisms. No matter how well designed,
internal policies remain
subject to companies' strategic interests.
When safety competes with
speed, profitability or market dominance,
even strong internal governance
may be compromised. Voluntary measures
lack enforceability and insiders
often face misaligned incentives when
raising concerns. As AI
capabilities continue to advance,
governance frameworks must evolve
accordingly.
there is still significant room for
improvement. Some suggest
that companies should define more precise,
verifiable risk thresholds,
potentially drawing on societal risk
tolerances from other industries.
For instance, industries dealing with
catastrophic risks typically set
maximum tolerable risk levels ranging from
1 in 10,000
to 1 in 10 billion per year. quantitative
thresholds
that AI companies might adopt with
appropriate adjustments. Systemic
risks and collective action problems
cannot be mitigated by
corporate self-regulation of a single
company. no one corporation
can be trusted to serve the public
interest alone.
Corporate governance frameworks like FSFs
show how companies can
coordinate around shared safety standards.
However, voluntary corporate coordination
faces systematic pressures from market
competition and regulatory arbitrage.
When safety competes with speed or market
share, even
well-intentioned companies may defect from
coordination agreements. This is
why corporate governance requires the
democratic legitimacy and enforcement
power that only national governance can
provide. Section National
Governance Jiang Jun once wrote, the
potential impact of
AI might exceed human cognitive
boundaries. To ensure that
this technology always benefits humanity,
we must regulate the
development of AI and prevent this
technology from turning
into a runaway wild horse. We need to
strengthen
the detection and evaluation of the entire
lifecycle of
AI. ensuring that mankind has the ability
to press
the pause button at critical moments. We
established in
the previous section that companies can
often lack incentives
to fully account for the broader societal
impact, face
competitive pressures that may compromise
safety and lack the
legitimacy to make decisions affecting
entire populations. National governance
frameworks therefore serve as an essential
complement to self-regulatory
initiatives, setting regional standards
that companies can incorporate into
their internal practices. Unlike
traditional technological governance
challenges, frontier
AI systems generate externalities that
span multiple domains, from
national security to economic stability,
from social equity to
democratic functioning. AI systems
threaten national security by
democratizing
capabilities usable by malicious actors,
facilitate unequal economic outcomes
by concentrating market power in specific
companies and countries
while displacing jobs elsewhere, and
produce harmful societal conditions
through extractive data practices and
biased algorithmic outputs. Traditional
regulatory bodies designed for narrower
technological domains typically lack
the necessary spatial remit, technical
competence, or institutional authority
to effectively govern these systems.
Consider the contrast with
self-driving vehicles, where the primary
externalities are relatively well-defined,
safety of road users, and fall within
existing regulatory
frameworks, traffic safety agencies.
Frontier AI systems, by contrast,
generate externalities that cross
traditional regulatory boundaries and
jurisdictions,
requiring new institutional approaches
that can address the expertise
gap, coordination gap and temporal gap in
current regulatory
frameworks. AI systems can cause harm in
ways that
are not always transparent or predictable.
Beyond software bugs
or input-output mismatches, risks emerge
from how AI systems
internally represent goals, make trade-
offs and generalize from data.
When these systems are deployed at scale,
even subtle
misalignments between system behavior and
human intent can have
widespread consequences. Automated sub-
goal pursuit, for example, can generate
outcomes that are technically correct but
socially catastrophic if
not carefully constrained. because many of
these failure modes
are embedded in opaque model architectures
and training dynamics.
They resist detection through conventional
auditing or certification processes.
National regulation provides an anchor for
accountability by requiring
developers to build, test and deploy
systems in ways
that are externally verifiable, legally
enforceable and publicly legitimate.
As we will see in this section, major
regions
have developed distinctly different
regulatory philosophies that reflect their
unique institutional contexts and
political priorities. Understanding these
national
frameworks will provide context for our
subsequent analysis of
international governance mechanisms, which
must navigate and harmonize these
regional differences to create effective
global standards for AI
systems whose impacts transcend national
borders. Across the last
decade, over 30 countries have released
national AI strategies
outlining their approach to development,
regulation, and adoption. These
strategies differ widely in emphasis, but
when systematically analyzed,
they fall into three recurring governance
patterns. Development, control
and promotion. In development-led models,
such as those in
China, South Korea and Hungary, the state
acts as
a strategic coordinator, directing public
resources toward AI infrastructure,
research programs and national missions.
control-oriented approaches prominent in
the European Union and countries like
Norway and Mexico,
emphasise legal standards, ethics
oversight and risk monitoring frameworks.
Promotion-focused models, including the
United States, United Kingdom and
Singapore, adopt a more decentralised
approach. The state acts
primarily as an enabler of private sector
innovation with
relatively few regulatory constraints.
These differences matter. Any attempt
to build international governance
frameworks will need to account
for the structural asymmetries between
these national regimes, particularly
around enforcement authority,
accountability mechanisms, and
institutional capacity. The
textbook includes Figure 4.28 here. It
depicts the state's
role in governing artificial intelligence,
development, control, and promotion
through national strategies. At this
point, the textbook shows
Figure 4.29. National governance provides
the enforcement mechanisms and
democratic legitimacy necessary to make
corporate coordination stable and
binding. However, AI risks transcend
national borders and regulatory
arbitrage allows development to shift to
jurisdictions with weaker
standards. No single nation can
effectively govern global AI
systems alone. This fundamental limitation
drives the need for
international coordination mechanisms.
Section International Governance. As
Antonio Guterres
said, AI poses a long-term global risk.
Even its
own designers have no idea where their
breakthrough may
lead. I urge the UN Security Council to
approach
this technology with a sense of urgency.
its creators
themselves have warned that much bigger,
potentially catastrophic and
existential risks lie ahead. To quote
Kamala Harris, just
as AI has the potential to do profound
good,
it also has the potential to cause
profound harm.
From AI-enabled cyberattacks at a scale
beyond anything we
have seen before to AI-formulated
bioweapons that could endanger
the lives of millions, these threats are
often referred
to as the existential threats of AI
because, of
course, they could endanger the very
existence of humanity.
These threats, without question, are
profound and they demand
global action. Can't individual countries
just regulate AI within
their own borders? The short answer is no,
not
effectively. Effective management of
advanced AI systems requires coordination
that transcends national borders. This
stems from three fundamental
problems. No single country has exclusive
control over AI
development. Even if one nation implements
stringent regulations, developers
in countries with looser standards could
still create and
deploy potentially dangerous AI systems
affecting the entire world.
The regulation of those risks requires
international cooperation. Talberg
et al. 2023 When asked about China's
participation in
the Bletchley AI Safety Summit, James
Cleverly, former UK
Foreign Secretary, correctly noted, we
cannot keep the UK
public safe from the risks of AI if we
exclude one of the leading nations in AI
tech.
Race to the bottom dynamics, countries
fear competitive disadvantage
in the AI race, which creates incentives
for regulatory
arbitrage and undermines safety standards
globally. Lancieri et al.
2024. International governance can help
align incentives between nations,
encouraging responsible AI development
without forcing any one country
to sacrifice its competitive edge. Lee
2025 The textbook
has interactive figure 4.6 here, which you
can explore
in the online version. It shows cumulative
number of
large-scale AI systems by country since
2017, refers to
the location of the primary organization
with which the
authors of a large-scale AI systems are
affiliated. How
do national policies affect global AI
development? Even seemingly
domestic regulations, such as immigration
policies see below, can
reshape the global AI landscape through
various spillover mechanisms.
There is figure 430 in the textbook here.
It
depicts what are the career paths of top-
tier AI
researchers. Macropolo. Companies
worldwide, eager to maintain access to
the lucrative European market, often find
it more cost-effective
to adopt EU standards across their entire
operations rather
than maintaining separate standards for
different regions. For example,
a US tech company developing a new AI-
powered facial
recognition system for use in public
spaces may see
this system being classified as high risk
under the
EU AI Act. This would subject it to strict
requirements around data quality,
documentation, human oversight, and more.
Companies then have a choice to either
develop two
separate versions of your product, one for
the EU
market and one for everywhere else, or
simply apply
the EU standards globally. Many will be
tempted to
choose the second option to minimize their
cost of
compliance. This is what's known as the
Brussels Effect.
EU regulations can end up shaping global
markets, even
in countries where those regulations don't
formally apply. The
Brussels effect can manifest in two ways.
De facto
adoption, companies often voluntarily
adopt EU standards globally to
avoid the complexity and cost of
maintaining different standards
for different markets. De Jure influence.
Other countries frequently
adopt regulations similar to the EU's,
either to maintain
regulatory alignment or because they view
the EU's approach
as a model worth emulating. The EU's
regulations might
offer the first widely adopted and
mandated operationalization of
concepts like risk management or systemic
risk in the
context of frontier AI. As other countries
grapple with
how to regulate advanced AI systems, they
may look
to the EU's framework as a starting point.
Siegman
and Ander Leung, 2022. Ursula von der
Leyen once
wrote, we should not underestimate the
real threats coming
from AI. It is moving faster than even its
developers anticipated. We have a
narrowing window of opportunity
to guide this technology responsibly. In
2023, the US
and UK governments both announced new
institutes for AI
safety. As of 2025, there are at least 12
National AI Safety Institutes, AISIs,
established worldwide. These include
institutes from the United States, United
Kingdom, Canada, France,
Germany, Italy, Japan, South Korea,
Singapore, Australia, Kenya and
India. The European Union has established
the European AI
Office, which functions similarly to
national AISIs. These institutes
collaborate through the International
Network of AI Safety Institutes,
launched in November 2024 to coordinate
research, share best
practices, and develop interoperable
safety standards for advanced AI
systems. The textbook includes Figure 4.31
here. It depicts
these countries as part of the
international network for
AI safety, with their respective national
bodies dedicated to
AI safety. Global governance efforts also
face major obstacles.
Strategic competition between leading
powers who view AI as
both a national security asset and an
economic engine
often undermines cooperation. Power
asymmetries further complicate
negotiations. Countries
with advanced AI capabilities, like the
United States and
China, may resist international
constraints, while others may demand
technology transfer and capacity-building
support in exchange for participation.
Divergent political systems and values
also pose barriers, with
disagreements over issues such as privacy,
free expression and
state authority. For example, China's
Global AI Governance Initiative
centres sovereignty and non-interference,
contrasting with Western frameworks rooted
in individual rights and democratic
accountability. Perhaps most
significantly,
deep trust deficits between major powers,
fuelled by tensions
over trade, intellectual property and
human rights. make it
difficult to reach credible, enforceable
agreements, adding to the
complex geopolitical landscape shaping the
future of international AI
governance. At this point, the textbook
shows Figure 4.32.
It depicts cartoon highlighting a
discrepancy between countries' statements
and their true intentions in the context
of the
UK's November 2023 AI Safety Summit, The
Economist. The
textbook has a supplementary note titled,
Existing International Mechanisms
2025, which we'll skip over here. How does
international
technology governance typically evolve?
Understanding the progression of
international
policymaking helps contextualize current
AI governance efforts and identify
potential paths forward. International
policymaking typically progresses through
several
stages. agenda setting, identifying the
issue and placing it
on the international agenda, policy
formulation, developing potential
solutions
and approaches, decision-making, choosing
specific courses of action,
implementation,
putting chosen policies into practice,
evaluation, assessing effectiveness and
making adjustments. For AI governance,
we're still largely in
the early stages of this process. The
series of
AI summits, the network of AI safety
institutes, and
other international frameworks all
represent progress in agenda setting
and initial policy formulation. But the
real work of
crafting binding international agreements
and implementing them still lies
ahead. Previous international governance
efforts provide valuable lessons for
AI. So, what can we learn from decades of
nuclear arms control efforts? Let's
consider three important lessons.
the power of norms and institutions.
Despite early fears
of rapid proliferation, only nine
countries possess nuclear weapons
nearly 80 years after their development,
which resulted from
concerted efforts to build global norms
against nuclear proliferation
and use. The Nuclear Non-Proliferation
Treaty, NPT, signed in
1968, created a framework for preventing
the spread of
nuclear weapons and helped promote
peaceful uses of nuclear
technology. the role of epistemic
communities. The development of
nuclear arms control agreements wasn't
solely the work of
diplomats and politicians. It relied
heavily on input from
scientists, engineers, and other technical
experts who understood the
technology and its implications. These
experts formed a network
of professionals with recognized expertise
in a particular domain,
or as what political scientists call an
epistemic community.
They played important roles in shaping
policy debates, providing
technical advice and even serving as back-
channel diplomats during
tense periods of the Cold War. Unlike
nuclear physicists
who were often employed directly by
governments, many AI
experts work in the private sector, so a
challenge
to forming such networks for global AI
governance will
be ensuring that epistemic communities can
effectively inform policy
decisions. the persistent challenge of
normal accidents. Despite decades
of careful management, the nuclear age has
seen several
incidents where human error, technical
malfunctions, or misunderstandings nearly
led to catastrophe. Sociologist Charles
Perrow termed these normal
accidents, arguing that in complex,
tightly coupled systems, such
incidents are inevitable. 1985. Applying
the concept to AI,
we could see unexpected interactions and
cascading failures increase
as AI systems become more complex and
interconnected. The
speed at which AI systems operate could
mean that
a normal accident in AI might unfold too
quickly
for human intervention. challenging the
notion of meaningful human
control, often proposed as a safeguard for
AI systems,
Mars 2019. Subsection, Policy Options.
Here is a quote
by Damis Hassabis. We must take the risks
of
AI as seriously as other major global
challenges, like
climate change. It took the international
community too long
to coordinate an effective global response
to this, and
we're living with the consequences of that
now. We
can't afford the same delay with AI. Then
maybe
there's some kind of equivalent one day of
the
IAEA, which actually audits these things.
Several institutional arrangements
could support international AI governance.
Scientific Consensus Building, similar
to the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate
Change, IPCC, a
dedicated body could provide regular
reports on AI capabilities
and risks to inform policymakers and the
public. Given
the rapid pace of AI development, this
body would
need to be nimbler than traditional
scientific consensus building
organizations. political consensus
building and norm setting. Building on
scientific consensus, a forum for
political leaders could develop
shared norms and principles, perhaps
structured like the UN
Framework Convention on Climate Change,
UNFCCC. Such a body
could facilitate ongoing dialogue,
negotiate agreements, and adapt governance
approaches as the technology evolves.
coordination of policy and
regulation. An international body focused
on policy coordination could
help harmonize AI regulations across
countries, reducing fragmentation and
preventing regulatory arbitrage
opportunities. Enforcement of standards
and restrictions,
mechanisms for monitoring compliance and
enforcing agreed-upon standards would
be necessary for effective governance.
Stabilization and emergency response
A global network of companies, experts and
regulators ready
to assist with major AI system failures
could help
mitigate risks. This group could work
proactively to identify
potential vulnerabilities in global AI
infrastructure and develop contingency
plans, similar to the International Atomic
Energy Agency's Incident
and Emergency Centre, but operating on
much faster timescales.
International joint research,
collaborative research could help ensure
that
Frontier AI development prioritizes safety
and beneficial outcomes, similar
to how CERN facilitates international
scientific cooperation. Distribution of
benefits and access. An institution
focused on ensuring equitable
access to AI benefits could prevent
harmful concentration of
capabilities and ensure the technology's
benefits are widely distributed
through mechanisms like a global fund for
AI development
assistance or technology transfers. There
is figure 4.33 in
the textbook here. It depicts an overview
table of
governance functions and their purpose.
What does this mean
for designing effective institutions?
There is no one-size-fits-all solution.
Institutions for global AI governance must
be tailored to
the unique characteristics of the
technology. Rapid iteration cycles,
broad deployment contexts and uncertain
future trajectories. We will
likely need a network of complementary
institutions, each fulfilling
specific governance functions listed
above. The key is not
just which institutions we build, but why
and how.
What specific risks and benefits require
international coordination, what
functions are essential to manage them,
and which designs
best match those functions under real-
world constraints. Without clear
answers, institutional design risks
becoming a mirror of past
regimes rather than a response to the
challenges of
advanced AI.