Section 4.3 – Compute Governance At this
point, the
textbook shows Figure 4.6. It depicts
example of an
NVIDIA Blackwell B100 Accelerator 2025.
Each B100 carries 192
GB of HBM3e memory and delivers nearly 20
pflops
of FP4 throughput. roughly doubling the
performance of the
H100 from 2024. Compute is a powerful
governance target
because it meets all three criteria for
effective governance
targets. Measurability Unlike data or
algorithms, Compute leaves clear
physical footprints. Training frontier
models requires massive data centers
housing thousands of specialized chips,
Pilsenheim 2023, We can
track computational capacity through well-
defined metrics like floating-point
operations,
FLOPs, allowing us to identify potentially
risky training runs
before they begin. Heim and Kösler 2024.
Controlability, the
supply chain for advanced AI chips, has
clear checkpoints.
Only three companies dominate the current
market. NVIDIA designs
most AI training chips, TSMC manufactures
the most advanced
processors, and ASML produces the only
machines capable of
making cutting-edge chips. This
concentration enables governance through
export
controls, licensing requirements, and
supply chain monitoring. Grunewald, 2023,
Sastry et al. 2024. Meaningfulness. As we
discussed in
the Risks chapter, the most dangerous
capabilities are likely
to emerge from highly capable models which
require massive
amounts of specialized computing
infrastructure to train and run.
Compute requirements directly constrain
what AI systems can be
built. Even with cutting-edge algorithms
and vast data sets,
organisations cannot train frontier models
without sufficient computing power.
This makes compute a particularly
meaningful point of intervention,
as it allows us to shape AI development
before
potentially dangerous systems emerge
rather than trying to control
them after the fact heim et al. in 2024.
At this point, there is interactive figure
4.1 in
the textbook, available in the online
version. It shows
performance on knowledge tests versus
training computation. Performance on
knowledge tests is measured with the MMLU
benchmark, here
with five shot learning, which gauges a
model's accuracy
after receiving only five examples for
each task. Training
computation is measured in total petaflop,
which is one
E15 floating-point operations. The
discussion in the next few
subsections will focus on the elements of
actually implementing
compute governance. We explain how
concentrated supply chains enable
tracking and monitoring of compute. We
also give a
brief discussion of hardware-based on-chip
compute governance mechanisms and
finally discuss some limitations based
around limitations to governance
based on compute thresholds and how
distributed training and
open source might challenge compute
governance. There is figure
4.7 in the textbook here. It depicts
sketch of
research domains for AI and compute.
Section, Tracking. AI-specialized
chips emerge from a complex global
process. It starts
with mining and refining raw materials
like silicon and
rare earth elements. These materials
become silicon wafers, which
are transformed into chips through
hundreds of precise manufacturing
steps. The process requires specialized
equipment, particularly photolithography
machines
from ASML, along with various chemicals,
gases and tools
from other suppliers. The textbook
includes figure 4.8 here.
It depicts the compute supply chain,
Bellfield and Huar
2022. There are several choke points in
semiconductor design
and manufacturing. The supply chain is
dominated by a
handful of companies at critical steps.
NVIDIA designs most
AI specialized chips, TSMC manufactures
the most advanced chips,
and ASML produces the machines needed by
TSMC to
manufacture the chips. It is estimated
that NVIDIA controls
around 80% of the market for AI training
GPUs.
Similarly, both TSMC and ASML maintain
strong leads in
their respective domains. Besides building
the chips, the purchase
and operation of them at the scale needed
for
Frontier AI models requires massive
upfront investment. In 2019,
academia and governments were leading in
AI supercomputers. Today,
companies control over 80% of global AI
computing capacity,
while governments and academia have fallen
below 20%. Just
three providers, Amazon, Microsoft, and
Google, control about 65%
of cloud computing services. A small
number of AI
companies like OpenAI, Anthropic and
DeepMind operate their own
massive GPU clusters, but even these
require specialized hardware
subject to supply chain controls. The
textbook has interactive
figure 4.2 here, which you can explore in
the
online version. It shows market share for
logic chip
production by manufacturing stage. At this
point, the textbook
shows figure 4.9. It depicts concentration
of the AI
chip supply chain expressed as percentage
of total market
share. Supply chain concentration creates
natural intervention points. Authorities
only need to work with a small number of
key players to implement controls, as
demonstrated by US
export restrictions on advanced chips. It
is worth keeping
in mind though that this heavy
concentration is also
concerning. We're seeing a growing compute
divide. While major
tech companies can spend hundreds of
millions on AI
training, academic researchers struggle to
access even basic resources.
This impacts who can participate in AI
development and
reduces independent oversight of frontier
models. It also raises
concerns around potential power
concentration. The textbook includes
Figure
4.10 here. It depicts the spectrum of chip
architectures
with trade-offs in regards to efficiency
and flexibility. Rather
than trying to control all computing
infrastructure, governance should
focus specifically on specialized AI
chips. These are distinct
from general-purpose hardware in both
capabilities and supply chains.
By targeting only the most advanced AI-
specific chips, we
can address catastrophic risks while
leaving the broader computing
ecosystem largely untouched. For example,
US export controls specifically
target high-end data center GPUs while
excluding consumer hardware.
Section Monitoring Training Frontier AI
models leaves multiple observable
footprints which might allow us to detect
concerning AI
training runs. The most reliable is energy
consumption. Training
runs that might produce dangerous systems
require massive power
usage, often hundreds of megawatts,
creating distinctive patterns. Besides
energy, other technical indicators include
network traffic patterns, characteristic
of model training, hardware procurement
and shipping records, cooling
system requirements and thermal
signatures, infrastructure buildout like
power
substation construction. These signals
become particularly powerful when
combined.
Sudden spikes in both energy usage and
network traffic
at a facility containing known AI hardware
strongly suggest
active model training. Regulations have
already begun using compute
thresholds to trigger oversight
mechanisms. The US executive order
on AI requires companies to notify the
government about
training runs exceeding 10 to the 26th
operations. a
threshold designed to capture the
development of the most
capable systems. The EU AI Act sets an
even
lower threshold of 10 to the 25th
operations, requiring
not just notification, but also risk
assessments and safety
measures. These thresholds help identify
potentially risky development activities
before they complete, enabling preventive
rather than reactive governance.
At this point, the textbook shows figure
4.11. It
depicts compute thresholds as specified in
the US Executive
Order 14110. Cloud compute providers can
play an important
role in compute governance. Most frontier
AI development happens
through cloud computing platforms rather
than self-owned hardware. This
creates natural control points for
oversight, since most organizations
developing advanced AI must work through
these providers. Cloud
provider's position between hardware and
developers allows them to
implement controls that would be difficult
to enforce through
hardware regulation alone. They maintain
the physical infrastructure, track
compute usage patterns and maintain
development records. They can
also monitor compliance with safety
requirements, can implement access
controls and respond to violations. One
suggested approach is
Know Your Customer, KYC requirements
similar to financial services.
Providers would verify the identity and
intentions of clients
requesting large-scale compute resources,
maintain records of significant compute
usage, and report suspicious patterns.
This can be done
while protecting privacy. Basic workload
characteristics can be monitored
without accessing sensitive details like
model architecture or training
data. Similar KYC laws can be applied to
the
supply chain on purchases of state-of-the-
art AI compute hardware.
Section On Chip Controls. There is Figure
4.12 in
the textbook here. It depicts current AI
chips already
have some components of this architecture,
but not all.
These gaps likely could be closed with
moderate development
effort as extensions of functionality
already in place. Beyond
monitoring and detection, compute
infrastructure can include active control
mechanisms built directly into the
processor hardware. Similar to
how modern smartphones and computers
include secure elements for
privacy and security, AI chips can
incorporate features that
verify and control how they're used. These
features could
prevent unauthorized training runs or
ensure chips are only
used in approved facilities. The
verification happens at the
hardware level, making it much harder to
bypass than
software controls. It is worth noting that
on-chip controls
are highly speculative. On-chip controls
could enable methods like
usage limits, logging, and location
verification. Several approaches show
promise. usage limits could cap the amount
of compute
used for certain types of AI workloads
without special
authorization. Secure logging systems
could create tamper-resistant records of
how chips are used. Location verification
could ensure chips
are only used in approved facilities.
Hardware could even
include safety interlocks that
automatically pause training if certain
conditions aren't met. Ideas like this are
also called
on-chip governance. We already see similar
concepts in cybersecurity
with features like Intel's software guard
extensions or trusted
platform modules, TPM, providing hardware-
level security guarantees. While we're
still far from equivalent safeguards for
AI compute, early
research shows promising directions. Some
chips already include basic
monitoring capabilities that could be
expanded for governance purposes.
Section Limitation The trend over the last
decade has
involved more compute, but this will not
last forever.
We spoke at length about scaling laws in
previous
chapters. Research suggests scaling-based
returns to AI capabilities are
still possible through 2030. Algorithmic
improvements also enhance efficiency,
meaning the same compute achieves more
capability over time.
Smaller models could begin to show
comparable capabilities and
risks. For example, Falcon 180b is
outperformed by far
smaller models like Lama 3 8b. This makes
static
compute thresholds less reliable as
capability indicators without regular
updates. Moreover, reasoning models, LRMs,
and inference time scaling,
e.g. OpenAI03, Claude4, DeepSeq R1, and
methods like model
distillation can dramatically improve
model capabilities without changing the
amount of compute used to train a model.
Current
governance frameworks do not account for
these post-training enhancements.
The textbook includes figure 4.13 here. It
depicts estimates
of the scale constraints imposed by the
most important
bottlenecks to scale. Each estimate is
based on historical
projections. The dark shaded box
corresponds to an interquartile
range and light shaded region to an 80%
confidence
interval. The four boxes showcase four
constraints that might
slow down growth in the future. power,
chips, compute,
data and latency. Smaller, more
specialized models can still
cause risks. Different domains have very
different compute requirements.
Highly specialized models trained on
specific datasets might develop
dangerous capabilities while using
relatively modest compute. For example,
models focused on biological or
cybersecurity domains could pose
serious risks even with compute usage
below typical regulatory
thresholds. Compute governance can help
manage AI risks, but
overly restrictive controls can accelerate
power concentration. Only a
handful of organizations can afford the
compute needed for
frontier AI development. adding more
barriers could worsen this
disparity, concentrating power in a few
large tech companies
and reducing independent oversight.
Academic researchers already struggle to
access the compute they need for
meaningful AI research.
As models get larger and more compute-
intensive, this gap
between industry and academia grows wider.
Large compute clusters
have many legitimate uses beyond AI
development, from scientific
research to business applications. Overly
broad restrictions could hinder
beneficial innovation. Additionally, once
models are trained, they can
often be run for inference using much less
compute
than training required. This makes it
challenging to control
how existing models are used without
imposing overly restrictive
controls on general computing
infrastructure. Distributed training and
inference
approaches could bypass compute governance
controls. Currently, training frontier
models requires concentrating massive
compute resources in single locations
due to communication requirements between
chips. Decentralized training methods
are being researched, but have not really
caught up
to centralized methods. However, if we see
fundamental advances
in distributed training algorithms, this
could eventually allow training
to be split across multiple smaller
facilities. While this
remains technically challenging and
inefficient, it could make detection
and control of dangerous training runs
more difficult. Compute
monitoring and compute thresholds should
primarily operate as an
initial screening mechanism. These
approaches should be used mainly
to identify models warranting further
scrutiny, rather than as
the sole determinant of specific
regulatory requirements. They are
most effective when used to trigger
oversight mechanisms, such
as notification requirements and risk
assessments, whose results can
then inform appropriate mitigation
measures. Technical governance measures
need
to coordinate with corporate, national and
international initiatives. We
focused on compute governance as our
primary technical example,
though coordination challenges apply
equally to data governance, model
governance, and other technical measures.
Each approach faces the
same fundamental limitation. Technical
measures alone cannot address systemic
risks that emerge from competitive
dynamics and global deployment.
This is why technical measures must be
embedded within
corporate, national and international
governance frameworks that align
incentives
with coordinated safety standards. Before
we talk about those,
however, we need to explore broader
concepts like decision-making
under uncertainty, game-theoretic
collective action problems and other
systemic
forces that shape the governance
landscape. We will talk
about this in the next section.