Section 4.2 – Governance Problems AI
governance is not
the same as traditional technology
governance. Traditional technology
governance
relies on several key assumptions that
break down when
applied to AI. We typically assume we can
predict
how a technology will be used and its
likely
impacts. that we can effectively control
its development pathway
and that we can regulate specific
applications or end
uses. For example, pharmaceutical
governance uses clinical trials and
approval processes based on intended
medical applications. while nuclear
technology is controlled through
international treaties, safeguards and
monitoring
of specific facilities and materials.
These approaches work when
technologies follow relatively predictable
development paths and have clear
applications. To understand what makes AI
governance uniquely challenging,
we can examine AI through three different
lenses that
each require different governance
approaches. AI as general-purpose
technology.
AI transforms many sectors simultaneously,
making sector-specific regulation
insufficient.
Like electricity or computers before it,
AI can reshape
healthcare, finance, transportation and
education all at once. Traditional
technology governance typically focuses on
specific applications. We regulate
medical devices differently from
automobiles. But when a single
AI system can diagnose diseases, trade
stocks and drive
cars, our regulatory silos break down. The
impacts span
across society in ways that make targeted
regulation insufficient.
AI as information technology. AI processes
and generates information
in unprecedented ways. Unlike traditional
information systems that store
and retrieve data, AI can create entirely
new content,
from photorealistic images to convincing
text to synthetic voices.
This creates unprecedented challenges
around security, privacy and information
integrity. Traditional governance
frameworks weren't designed to handle
technologies
that can rapidly generate and manipulate
information at massive
scale. The speed and scope of potential
information impacts
outstrip traditional control mechanisms.
AI as intelligence technology. AI
introduces unique control challenges as
systems become more capable.
As AI systems approach and potentially
exceed human cognitive
abilities in various domains, they may
develop sophisticated ways
to evade controls or pursue unintended
objectives. We're already
seeing glimpses of this with language
models that can
engage in deception or manipulation when
pursuing goals. There
are several dangerous capabilities, refer
back to chapters 1
and 2, which become even more acute when
considering
that AI systems might develop these
capabilities without being
explicitly programmed for them. The
intelligence aspect of AI
creates a dynamic where the technology
being governed might
actively resist or circumvent governance
measures, a challenge without
precedent in technology regulation. The
combination of AI as
a general purpose, information,
intelligence technology creates unique
governance
challenges. The mixed nature of AI as a
general
purpose, information processing, and
potentially intelligent technology gives
rise
to three fundamental problems that make
traditional governance approaches
inadequate. The textbook includes Figure
4.2 here. It depicts
summary of the three regulatory challenges
posed by Frontier
AI. Section, unexpected capabilities. AI
systems develop surprising abilities
that weren't part of their intended
design. Through several
of our chapters now, we have shown that
Foundation
models can show emergent capabilities that
appear suddenly as
models scale up with more data, parameters
and compute.
GPT-3 unexpectedly demonstrated the
ability to perform basic arithmetic,
while later models showed emergent
reasoning capabilities that surprised
even their creators. Evaluations have
found that frontier models
can autonomously conduct basic scientific
research, hack into computer
systems, and manipulate humans through
persuasion, none of which
were explicitly trained for. At this
point, the textbook
shows Figure 4.3. It depicts example of
unexpected capabilities,
graphs showing several metrics that
improve suddenly and unpredictably
as models increase in size, AI evaluations
are still
in their early stages in 2025, testing
frameworks lack
established best practices, and the field
has yet to
mature into a reliable science. While
evaluations can reveal
some capabilities, they cannot guarantee
absence of unknown threats,
forecast new emergent abilities, or assess
risks from autonomous
systems. Predictability itself is a
nascent research area, with
major gaps in our ability to anticipate
how present
models behave, let alone future ones. Even
the most
comprehensive test and evaluation
frameworks struggle with complex,
unpredictable
AI behavior. Section Deployment Safety
Once deployed, AI systems
can be repurposed for harmful applications
beyond their intended
use. The same language model trained for
helpful dialogue
can generate misinformation, assist with
cyber attacks, or help
design biological weapons. Users regularly
discover new capabilities through
clever prompting that bypasses safety
measures called jail breaks
that unlock dangerous functionalities.
There is figure 4.4 in
the textbook here. It depicts a schematic
of using
autonomous LLM agents to hack websites.
Once a dual-purpose
technology is public, it can be used for
both
beneficial and harmful purposes. AI agents
amplify deployment risks.
We're now seeing autonomous AI agents that
can chain
together model capabilities in novel ways,
using tools and
taking actions in the real world. These
agents can
pursue complex goals over extended
periods, making their behavior
even harder to predict and control post-
deployment. Section –
proliferation. AI capabilities spread
rapidly through multiple channels, making
containment nearly impossible. Models can
be stolen through cyber
attacks, leaked by insiders, or reproduced
by competitors within
months. The rapid open-source replication
of chat GPT-like capabilities
led to models with safety features removed
and new
dangerous capabilities discovered through
community experimentation. With API-based
models,
techniques like model distillation can
even extract capabilities without
direct access to model weights. Physical
containment doesn't work
for digital goods. Unlike nuclear
materials or dangerous pathogens,
AI models are just patterns of numbers
that can
be copied instantly and transmitted
globally. Once capabilities exist,
controlling their spread becomes a losing
battle against the
fundamental nature of digital information.
The textbook includes Figure
4.5 here. It depicts examples of
proliferation, OSCAN 2024.
Section, Governance Targets. The unique
challenges associated with AI
governance mean we need to carefully
choose where and
how to intervene in AI development. This
requires identifying
both what to govern, targets, and how to
govern
it mechanisms. Governance must intervene
at points that address
core challenges before they manifest. We
can't wait for
dangerous capabilities to emerge or
proliferate before acting. Instead,
we need to identify intervention points in
the AI
development pipeline that will help us
shape AI development
proactively. Effective governance targets
share three essential properties.
Measurability.
We must be able to track and verify what's
happening. The amount of computing power
used for training
can be measured in precise units,
floating-point operations, making
it possible to set clear thresholds and
monitor compliance.
Sastri et al. 2024. controllability, there
must be concrete
mechanisms to influence the target. It's
not enough to
identify what matters, we need practical
ways to shape
it. The semiconductor supply chain, for
instance, has clear
choke points where export controls can
effectively limit access
to advanced chips. Heim et al. 2024.
Meaningfulness. Targets
should address fundamental aspects of AI
development that actually
shape capabilities and risks. Regulating
superficial aspects like user
interfaces might be easy but won't prevent
the emergence
of dangerous capabilities. Core inputs
like compute and data,
however, directly determine what kinds of
AI systems can
be built. And Elyung et al. 2023. In the
AI development pipeline, several
intervention points meet these criteria.
Early in development, we can target the
compute infrastructure
required for training and the data that
shapes model
capabilities. During and after
development, we can implement safety
frameworks, monitoring systems and
deployment controls. Each target offers
different opportunities and faces
different challenges, which we'll explore
in the following sections.