Section 1.11 Appendix Discussion on LLMs
Current LLMs, although
trained on abundant data, are still far
from perfect.
Will these problems persist in future
iterations or will
they disappear? This section examines the
main criticisms of
those models and tries to determine if
they are
valid, even for future LLMs. This kind of
qualitative
assessment is important to know whether
LLMs represent the
most likely route to AGI or not.
Imperically insufficiency?
Can LLMs be creative? The creativity of
LLMs is
often debated, but there are clear
indications that AI,
in principle, is capable of creative
processes in various
ways. Autonomous scientific research,
recent advancements have shown that
LLMs can indeed make novel discoveries.
For example, a
study by DeepMind demonstrated that an LLM
discovered new
solutions for the cap-set problem, a long-
standing open problem
in mathematics, which was a favorite open
problem of
Terence Tao. This indicates that AI can
not only
understand existing knowledge, but also
contribute new insights in
complex fields like mathematics.
Autonomous discovery. AI, I think,
capability to rediscover human strategies
and openings independently. AlphaGo,
for example, rediscovered human-go
strategies and openings through self-play,
McGrath at AL 2021, without any human data
input.
This demonstrates an AI's ability to
independently learn and
innovate within established domains.
Creative optimization. AI can optimize
in surprisingly creative ways. The
phenomena of specification gaming,
where AI finds unintended solutions to
problems, illustrate this.
Although this unpredictability poses its
challenges, it also shows
that AI systems can come up with novel
creative
solutions that might not be immediately
obvious or intuitive
to human problem solvers. DeepMind's blog
post on specification
gaming illustrates this point vividly.
Krakowna at AL 2020.
Aren't LLMs just too slow at learning
things? Arguments
against transformer-based language models
often state that they are
too sample inefficient, and that LLMs are
extremely slow
to learn new concepts when compared to
humans. To
increase performance in new tasks or
situations, it's often
argued that LLMs require training on vast
amounts of
data, millions of times more than a human
would
need. However, there's a growing trend
towards data efficiency
and an increasing belief that this can be
significantly
improved in future models. Efficient Zero
is a reinforcement
learning agent that surpasses median human
performance on a
set of 26 Atari games after just two hours
of real-time experience per game. This is
a considerable
improvement over previous algorithms
showcasing the potential leaps in
data efficiency. The promise here is not
just more
efficient learning, but also the potential
for rapid adaptation
and proficiency in new tasks akin to a
child's
learning speed. Efficient zero is not an
LLM, but
it shows that deep learning can sometimes
be made
efficient. Scaling laws indicate that
larger AIs tend to
be more data efficient, requiring less
data to reach
the same level of performance as their
smaller counterparts.
Papers such as language models are few-
shot learners, and
the evidence that larger models seem to
take less
data to reach the same level of
performance suggests
that as model scale, they become more
proficient with
fewer examples. This trend points towards
a future where
AI might be able to rapidly adapt and
learn
from limited data, challenging the notion
that AI's are
inherently slow learners compared to
humans. Are LLMs robust
to distributional shifts? While it is true
that AI
has not yet achieved maximal robustness,
for example, being
able to perform perfectly after a change
in distribution,
there has been considerable progress.
Robustness correlates with capabilities.
Robustness is closely linked to the
capabilities of AI
models, when AI's are trained on difficult
tasks. For
instance, there is a significant
improvement in robustness and
transfer learning from GPT-2 to GPT-4. In
computer vision,
recent models like segment anything,
Carolov at L 2023,
are far more robust and capable of
transfer learning
than their less capable predecessors. This
progression isn't due
to any mysterious factors, but rather a
result of
scaling and improving upon existing
architectures. Robustness is a
continuum, and perfect robustness may be
not necessary. Robustness
in AI should not be viewed as a binary
concept, but rather as existing on a
continuum. This
continuum is evident in the way AI models,
like
those in image classification, often
surpass human performance in
both capability and robustness, Corsica
2022. However, it's important
to recognize that no system is completely
immune to
challenges, such as adversarial attacks.
This is exemplified by
advanced AI's like Catago and Grow, which,
despite being
vulnerable to such attacks, weighing at
L-2022, still achieves
a superhuman level of play. However, the
quest for
perfect robustness may not be essential to
create capable
transformative AI, as even systems with
certain vulnerabilities can
achieve superhuman levels of competence.
However, while robustness may
not be necessary to create capable AI, the
creation
of safe, aligned AI will have to solve the
problem of misgeneralizing goals. Shallow
understanding? Stochastic parrots. Do
AI's only memorize information without
truly compressing it? There
are two archetypal ways to represent
information in an
LLM, either memorize point-by-point, like
a lookup table, or
compress the information by only
memorizing higher-level features, which
we can then call the world model. This is
explained in the very important paper,
superposition, memorization, and
double descent. It turns out that to store
points,
initially, the model learns the position
of all the
points, pure memorization. Then, if we
increase the number
of points, the model starts to compress
this knowledge,
and the model is now capable of
generally... Here
is a quote by Francois Cholet.
Unfortunately, too few
people understand the distinction between
memorization and understanding. It's
not some lofty question like, does the
system have
an internal world model? At this point,
the textbook
shows figure 1.68. There is figure 1.69 in
the
textbook here. It depicts from
superposition, memorization, and double
descent. AI is capable of compressing
information, often in
a relevant manner. For example, when
examining the representations
of words representing colors in LLMs, like
red and
blue, the structure formed by all the
embeddings of
those colors creates the correct color
circle. This uses
a non-linear projection, such as a
T-distributed stochastic neighbor
embedding, T-sni, to project from high-
dimensional space to the
2D plane. Other examples of world models
are presented
in a paper called Eight Things to Know
about
large language models. Of course, there
are other domains
where AI resembles more of a lookup table,
but
it is a spectrum, and each case should be
examined individually. For example, for
factual association, the paper
locating and editing factual associations
in GPT shows that
the underlying data structure for GPT2 is
more of
a lookup table. But the paper emergent
linear representations
in world models of self-supervised
sequence models demonstrates that
a small GPT is capable of learning a
compressed
world model of a fellow GPT. There are
more
examples in the section dedicated to world
models in
the paper, eight things to know about
large language
models. It's clear that LLMs are
compressing their representations
at least a bit. Many examples of
impressive capabilities
are presented in the work the stochastic
parent hypothesis
is debatable for the last generation of
LLMs, which
shows that it cannot be purely a
memorization. Well,
LLMs inevitably hallucinate? LLMs are
prone to hallucinate, a
term used to describe the generation of
content that
is nonsensical or factually incorrect in
response to certain
prompts. This issue highlighted in studies
such as on
faithfulness and factuality and abstract
of summarization by Maynaz
at L and truthful QA, measuring how models
mimic
human falsehoods by Lynn at L poses a
significant
challenge. However, it's important to see
that these challenges
are anticipated due to the training setup
and can
be mitigated. Inherent bias and source
texts One of
the fundamental reasons LLMs may produce
untrue content is
training data, which may not always be
entirely factual
or unbiased. In essence, LLMs are
reflecting the diverse
and sometimes contradictory nature of
their training data. In
this context, LLMs are constantly
hallucinating, but occasionally these
hallucinations align with our perception
of reality. Strategies to
enhance factual accuracy. The tendency of
LLMs to generate
hallucinations can be significantly
diminished using various techniques. See
the box below for a breakdown of those.
Larger
models can be more truthful than smaller
ones. This
is the case with truthful QA. OpenAI
reports that
GPT-4 is 40% more accurate and factually
consistent than
its predecessor. The textbook has a
supplementary note titled,
many techniques can be used to increase
the truthfulness
of LLMs, which we'll skip over here.
Section, structural
inadequacy. Are LLMs missing System 2?
System 1 and
System 2 are terms popularized by
economist Daniel Kahneman
in his book, Thinking Fast and Slow,
describing the
two different ways our brains form
thoughts and make
decisions. System 1 is fast, automatic,
and intuitive. It's
the part of our thinking that handles
everyday decisions
and judgments without much effort or
conscious deliberation. For
example, when you recognize a face or
understand simple
sentences, you're typically using System
1. On the other
hand, System 2 is slower, more
deliberative, and more
logical. It takes over when you're solving
a complex
problem, making a conscious choice, or
focusing on a
difficult task. It requires more energy
and is more
controlled, handling tasks such as
planning for the future,
checking the validity of a complex
argument, or any
activity that requires deep focus.
Together, these systems interact
and influence how we think, make
judgments, and decide,
highlighting the complexity of human
thought and behavior. A
key concern is whether LLMs are able to
emulate
system 2 processes, which involve slower,
more deliberate, and
logical thinking. Some theoretical
arguments about the depth limit
in transformers show that they are
provably incapable of
internally dividing large integers.
However, this is not what
we observe in practice. GPT-4 is capable
of detailing
some calculations step by step and
obtaining the expected
result through a chain of thought, or via
the
usage of tools like a code interpreter.
Emerging Metacognition
Emerging functions in LLMs, like the
Reflection technique, allow
these models to retrospectively analyze
and improve their answers.
It is possible to ask the LLM to take
a step back, question the correctness of
its previous
actions, and consider ways to improve the
previous answer.
This greatly enhances the capabilities of
GPT-4, enhancing its
capabilities, and aligning them more
closely with human system-2
operations. Note that this technique is
emergent and is
not work well with previous models. These
results suggest
a blurring of the lines between these two
systems.
System-2 processes may be essentially an
assembly of multiple
system-1 processes, appearing slower due
to involving more steps
and interactions with slower forms of
memory. This perspective
is paralleled in how language models
operate, with each
step in a system one process akin to a
constant time execution step in models
like GPT. Although
these models struggle with intentionally
orchestrating these steps to
solve complex problems, breaking down
tasks into smaller steps,
least to most prompting, or prompting them
for incremental
reasoning, chain of thought prompting
significantly improves their performance.
Are LLMs missing an internal world model?
The notion
of a world model in AI need not be
confined to explicit encoding within an
architecture. Contrary to
approaches like HJEPA, which advocate for
an explicit world
model to enhance AI training, there's
growing evidence that
a world model can be effectively implicit.
This concept
is particularly evident in reinforcement
learning or RL, where
the distinction between model-based and
model-free RL can be
somewhat misleading. Even in model-free
RL, algorithms often implicitly
encode a form of a world model that is
crucial for optimal performance. Time and
geographical coordinates. Research
on Lama 2 models reveals how these models
can
represent spatial and temporal
information, Gurney and Tegmark 2024.
LLMs like Lama 2 models encode approximate
real-world coordinates
and historical timelines of cities. Key
findings include the
gradual emergence of geographical
representations across model layers, the
linearity of these representations, and
the model's robustness to
different prompts. Significantly, the
study shows that the models
are not just passively processing this
information, but actively
learning the global geometry of space and
time. board
representation. In the paper, emergent
linear representations in world
models of self-supervised sequence models,
Nanda at all, 2023,
the author presents significant findings
on the nature of
representations in AI models. The paper
delves into how
the Othello GPT model, trained to predict
legal moves
in the game of Othello, develops an
emergent world
representation of the game board. Contrary
to previous beliefs
that this representation was non-linear,
he demonstrates that it
is in fact linear. He discovers that the
model
represents board states, not in terms of
black or
white pieces, but as my color or their
color,
aligning with the model's perspective of
playing both sides.
This works shed light on the potential of
AI
models to develop complex, yet linear,
world representations through
simple objectives like next token
prediction. Other examples are
presented in the paper eight things to
know about
LLMs, Bowman 2023. Can LLMs learn
continuously and have
long-term memory? Continual learning and
the effective management of
long-term memory represent significant
challenges in the field of
AI in general. Catastrophic forgetting. A
crucial obstacle in
this area is catastrophic forgetting. A
phenomenon where a
neural network, upon learning new
information, tends to entirely
forget previously learned information.
This issue is an important
focus of ongoing research, aiming to
develop AI systems
that can retain and build upon their
knowledge over
time. For example, suppose we train an AI
on
an Atari game. At the end of the second
training, the AI has most likely forgotten
how to
play the first aim. This is an example of
catastrophic forgetting. But now suppose
we train a large
AI on many Atari games simultaneously, and
even add
some internet text and some robotic tasks.
This can
just work. For example, the AI Goddo
illustrates this
training process and exemplifies what we
call the blessing
of scale, which is that what is impossible
in
small regimes can become possible in large
regimes. Other
techniques are being developed to solve
long-term memory. For
example, scaffolding-based approaches have
also been employed for achieving
long-term memory and continual learning in
AI. Scaffolding in
AI refers to the use of hard-coded
wrappers, explicitly
programmed structures by humans, that
involve a for loop
to query continuously the model. Langchain
addresses these challenges
by creating extensive memory banks.
Langchain is a Python
library that allows LLMs to retrieve and
utilize information
from large datafets, essentially providing
a way for AI
to access a vast repository of knowledge
and use
this information to construct more
informed responses. However, this
approach may not be the most elegant due
to
its reliance on external data sources and
complex retrieval
mechanisms. A potentially more seamless
and integrated solution could
involve utilizing the neural network's
weights as dynamic memory,
constantly evolving and updating based on
the tasks performed
by the network. Voyager. A remarkable
example of a
scaffolding-based long-term memory is the
AI Voyager, an AI
system developed under the AutoGPT
paradigm. This system is
notable for its ability to engage in
continuous learning
within a 3D game environment like
Minecraft. In a
single game session, AI Voyager
demonstrates the capacity to
learn basic controls Achieve initial goals
such as resource
acquisition, and eventually advance to
more complex behaviors, including
combat with enemies, and crafting tools
for gathering sophisticated
resources. This demonstrates a significant
stride in ALLM's ability
to learn continually and manage long-term
memory within dynamic
environments. It should be noted that
scaffold-based long-term memory
is not considered an elegant solution, and
purists would
prefer to use the system's own weights as
long-term
memory. Planning is an area that AI's
currently struggle
with, but there is significant progress.
Some paradigms, such
as those based on scaffolding, enable task
decomposition and
breaking down objectives into smaller,
more achievable sub-objectives.
Furthermore,
the paper Voyager, an open-ended embodied
agent with large
language models, demonstrates that it is
possible to use
GPT-4 for planning in natural language in
Minecraft. Section,
differences with the brain. It appears
that there are
several points of convergence between the
LLMs and the
linguistic cortex. Behavioral
similarities. LLM show a close comparison
to human linguistic abilities and the
linguistic cortex Canal
2022. These models have excelled in
mastering syntax and
a significant portion of semantics in
human language. Of
course, today, they still lag in aspects
such as
long-term memory, coherence, and general
reasoning. Faculties that in
humans depend on various brain regions,
like the hippocampus
and prefrontal cortex, but we explained in
the last
sections that those problems may be
solvable. Convergence in
Internal Representations. LLMs have a
representation that converges with
scale toward the brain representation.
This is supported by
the study, brains and algorithms partially
converge in natural
language processing, Couch Attacks, and
King 2022. Additional insights
can be found in the works, The Brain as
a Universal Learning Machine, Canal 2015,
and Brain Efficiency,
much more than you wanted to know, Canal
2022.
At comparable learning stages, LLMs and
the linguistic cortex
develop similar or equivalent feature
representations. In some evaluations,
advanced LLMs have been able to predict
100% of
the explainable neural variants, as
detailed by Shrimp, Martin
et al, in the neural architecture of
language, integrative
modeling converges on predictive
processing, Shrimp et al 2021.
Scale is also important in primates. The
principal architectural
difference between human and other primate
brains seems to
be the number of neurons rather than
anything else,
as demonstrated in various studies, Housel
2012, Pearson at
Al 2023, Charvette 2021. Section further
reasons to continue
scaling LLMs. Following are some reasons
to believe that
labs will continue to scale LLMs. Scaling
laws on
LLM implies further qualitative
improvements. The scaling laws might
not initially appear impressive. However,
linking these quantitative measures
can translate to a qualitative improvement
in algorithm quality.
An algorithm that achieves near-perfect
loss, though, is one
that necessarily comprehends all
subtleties and displays enormous
adaptability.
The fact that the scaling laws are not
bending
is very significant and means that we can
make
the model a qualitatively better reasoner.
From simple correlations
to understanding. During a training run,
GPTs go from
basic correlations to deeper and deeper
understanding. Initially, the
model merely establishes connections
between successive words. Gradually, it
develops an understanding of grammar and
semantics, creating links
between sentences and subsequently between
paragraphs. Eventually, GPT masters
the nuances of writing style. The textbook
has a
supplementary note titled Exercise Scaling
Laws on LLM implies
further qualitative improvements, which
we'll skip over here. Text
completion is probably an AI complete
test. Current LLMs
have only as many parameters as small
mammals have
synapses. No wonder they are still
imperfect. Models like
GPT-4, though very big compared to other
models, should
be noted for their relatively modest scale
compared to
the size of a human brain. To illustrate,
the
largest GPT-3 model has a similar number
of parameters
to the synapses of a hedgehog. We don't
really
know how many parameters GPT-4 has, but if
it
is the same size as Palm, which has 512
B parameters, then GPT-4 has only as many
parameters
as a chinchilla has synapses. In contrast,
the human
neocortex contains about 140 trillion
synapses, which is over
200 times more synapses than a chinchilla.
For a
more in-depth discussion on this
comparison, see the related
discussion here. For a discussion of the
number of
parameters necessary to emulate a synapse,
see the discussion
on biological anchors. GPT-4 is still
orders of magnitude
cheaper than other big science projects.
Despite the high
costs associated with training large
models, the significant leaps
and AI capabilities provided by scaling
justify these costs.
For example, GPT-4 is expensive compared
to other ML
models. It is said to cost 50 million in
training, but the Manhattan Project costs
25 billion, which
is 500 times more without accounting for
inflation, and
achieving human level intelligence may be
more economically important
than achieving the nuclear bomb.
Collectively, these points support
the idea that AGI can be achieved by only
scaling current algorithms.