Section 1.5, leveraging scale. In the
previous section, we
looked at different notions of how to
define AGI
and measure the relevant capabilities. Now
we'll examine one
of the most important drivers behind
improvements in these
capabilities. Scale. bitter a lesson.
Human-engineered domain knowledge
consistently
loses to general methods that leverage
massive computation. We
assume that most of you probably went to
university
in an era where machine learning and AI
roughly
mean the same thing, or even that deep
learning
and AI mean the same thing. This hasn't
always
been true. Early in AI's history,
researchers believed the
key to artificial intelligence was
carefully encoding human knowledge
and expertise into computer programs. This
led to expert
systems filled with handcrafted rules and
chess engines programmed
with sophisticated strategic principles.
Time and again, these approaches
hit walls, while simple learning
algorithms combined with massive
computation kept improving. However, time
and time again, researchers
learned what we now call the bitter
lesson. The
biggest lesson that can be read from 70
years
of AI research is that general methods
that leverage
computation are ultimately the most
effective and by a
large margin. The bitter lesson is based
on the
historical observations that one, AI
researchers have often tried
to build knowledge into their agents. 2.
This always
helps in the short term and is personally
satisfying
to the researcher. But 3. In the long run,
it plateaus and even inhibits further
progress. And 4.
Breakthrough progress eventually arrives
by an opposing approach based
on scaling computation by search and
learning. The bitterness
comes from discovering that decades of
human expertise mattered
less than computation. Researchers who
spent years encoding grandmaster
chess knowledge watched brute force search
defeat world champion
Gary Kasparov. Handcrafted feature
detectors in computer vision got
outperformed by neural networks that
learned their own features
from data. phonetics-based speech
recognition lost to statistical
approaches.
The pattern repeated, domain expertise
helped initially, then hit
a wall. Simple learning algorithms plus
massive compute kept
improving. The better lesson doesn't
reject human ingenuity or
algorithmic innovation. There's a
difference between building better general
learning systems and encoding task-
specific human knowledge. This isn't
a difference just between good old-
fashioned AI, GoFi, and
modern deep learning. Even within deep
learning, the bitter
lesson still applies. The winning
algorithms are those that
leverage scale most effectively.
Transformers didn't beat LSTMs by
encoding linguistic knowledge. They
outperformed because attention mechanisms
parallelize
better and can actually use massive
compute productively. Algorithmic
innovation still matters, finding
architectures and training methods that
extract more from the same data and
hardware. The
algorithms that succeed are the ones that
unlock scales
potential. The bitter lesson shapes
expectations about AI progress.
If the bitter lesson continues to be true,
improvements
should come from either finding algorithms
that better leverage
scale or simply scaling existing
algorithms with more compute,
data, and parameters. In the last few
years, the
majority of gains seen in AI capabilities
have emerged
from scaling up the same transformer-based
language models. Training
frontier AI models costs hundreds of
millions of dollars,
making it critical to predict returns on
investment. AI
Labs face resource allocation decisions
with massive stakes. Should
they spend more on GPUs or training data?
Train
a larger model briefly or a smaller model
longer.
With a fixed compute budget, they might
choose between
a 20 billion parameter model, trained on
40% of
their data, or a 200 billion parameter
model, trained
on 4% of it. Getting this wrong, waste
hundreds
of millions. Scaling laws help turn these
gambles into
engineering decisions by establishing
empirically observed relations. Scaling
laws
describe how model accuracy changes as you
vary four
key variables. Compute, total floating
point operations, FLOPs, during
training, accounts for GPU power, number
of chips, and
training duration, how many steps you
train for. Parameters,
the numbers the model adjusts during
training, roughly analogous
to model size. Data, training examples
seen, measured in
tokens for LLMs. Accuracy. How well the
model performs
on benchmarks, the inverse of loss, lower
loss, higher
accuracy. There is figure 1.33 in the
textbook here.
It depicts example of capabilities
increasing with an increase
with one of variables in the scaling laws,
parameter
count. The same model architecture, party,
was used to
generate an image using an identical
prompt with the
only difference between the models being
the parameter size.
There are noticeable leaps in quality, and
somewhere between
3 billion and 20 billion parameters, the
model acquires
the ability to spell words correctly.
Scaling laws are
empirically observed relationships, not
laws of nature. OpenAI first
documented these relationships in 2020 by
running hundreds of
experiments, varying inputs while
measuring accuracy. They found that
when you increase compute by 10X, accuracy
improves predictably.
Double the parameters, accuracy jumps
predictably. These patterns proved
surprisingly consistent across model
architectures and tasks, suggesting they
capture something fundamental about how
neural networks learn. Later
research revealed optimal training
requires roughly 20 tokens of
data per parameter, about 10 times more
data than
early laws suggested. This meant previous
large models were
under-trained relative to their size. The
relationships continue evolving
as researchers gather more evidence, but
the core insight
remains. Scale drives predictable
capability gains. The following graphs
clearly show massive increases in scale
for data, compute,
and parameter count by all major AI labs.
At
this point, there is interactive figure
1.4 in the
textbook, available in the online version.
It shows exponential
growth of parameters in notable AI
systems. Parameters are
variables in an AI system whose values are
adjusted
during training to establish how input
data gets transformed
into the desired output. For example, the
connection weights
in an artificial neural network. The
textbook has interactive
figure 1.5 here, which you can explore in
the
online version. It shows exponential
growth of data points
used to train notable AI systems. Each
domain has
a specific data point unit. For example,
for vision,
it is images. For language, it is words.
And
for games, it is time steps. This means
systems
can only be compared directly within the
same domain.
At this point, there is interactive figure
1.6 in
the textbook. available in the online
version. It shows
exponential growth of computation in the
training of notable
AI systems. Computation is measured in
total petaflop, which
is 10 to the 15th floating point
operations. The
textbook has a supplementary note titled,
The Broken Neural
Scaling Laws, BNSL, Update in 2023, which
will skip
over here. Scaling Hypothesis Scaling
might continue driving capability
gains. Look back at the examples from
previous sections,
the programming abilities, emergent
reasoning, scientific research assistance,
the
jump from GPT 3.5 to GPT 4 across
professional
exams. These capabilities appeared as
models got bigger and
trained on more data without requiring new
architectural breakthroughs
or encoded domain knowledge. If current
approaches scaled up
could produce systems capable of
automating AI research within
years, safety work becomes far more
urgent. The existing
evidence supports multiple interpretations
because we're watching a technology
develop in real time, whose limits we
don't fully
understand. So different people hold
different hypotheses about how
the future could unfold. The strong
scaling hypothesis. This
proposes that simply scaling up existing
architectures with more
compute and data will be sufficient to
reach transformative
AI capabilities. According to this view,
we already have
all the fundamental components needed.
It's just a matter
of making them bigger, following
established scaling laws. At
this point, the textbook shows Figure
1.35. It depicts
augmentation slash scaffolding stays
constant. But if the scaling
hypothesis, weak or strong, is true, then
capabilities will
keep improving just by scaling. The weak
scaling hypothesis.
This view states that even though scale
will continue
to be the primary driver of progress, we
will
also need targeted architectural and
algorithmic improvements to overcome
specific bottlenecks. These improvements
wouldn't require fundamental
breakthroughs, but
rather incremental enhancements to better
leverage scale. Researchers have
been developing algorithms that leverage
scale and compute for
more than a decade. We have seen many
gains
come from improvement in compute
efficiency, from innovations like
better attention mechanisms, mixture of
experts routing, and efficient
training methods. But even when
researchers have developed sophisticated
algorithms following the bitter lessons
principles, data suggests that
between 60 to 95% of performance gains
came from
scaling compute and data, while
algorithmic improvements contributed 5
to 40%, though there is substantial
methodological uncertainty in
disentangling these contributions. The
emergence of unexpected capabilities might
provide another argument for strong
scaling. We've seen previous
generations of foundation models
demonstrate remarkable abilities that
weren't
explicitly trained for, like programming.
This emergent behavior hints
that it is not impossible for higher order
cognitive
abilities to similarly emerge simply as a
function of
further scale. There is Figure 1.36 in the
textbook
here. It depicts, even if we see no
improvements
in model scale, other elicitation
techniques and scaffolding can
keep improving. So overall capabilities
keep growing. Realistically, the
future is probably going to see both
improvement due
to scaffolding and scale. So for now,
there does
not seem to be an upper limit on improving
capabilities, as long as either one of the
two
holds. Scale combined with techniques and
tools hypothesis. Essentially,
both the scaling laws, which only predict
foundation model
capabilities, and most debates around
scale as all you
need, often miss other aspects of AI
development that
happen outside the scope of what scaling
laws can
predict. They don't account for
improvements in AI scaffolding,
like chain of thought prompting, tool use,
or retrieval,
or combinations of multiple models working
together in novel
ways. Any LLM with internet access, code
execution, and
the ability to call upon the help of other
specialized submodels has substantially
more capability than the same
LLM alone. We gave several examples of
this being
the dominant trend in our first section,
tool use,
thinking for longer, inference time
scaling, MCP servers, and
so on. Debates around the scaling laws
only tell
us about the capabilities of a single
foundation model
trained in a standard way. For example, by
the
strong scaling hypothesis, we can reach
TAI by simply
scaling up the same foundation model until
it completely
automates MLR&D. But even if scaling
stops, halting capabilities
progress on the core foundation model in
either a
week or a strong way, the external
techniques that
leverage the existing model can still
continue advancing. Many
researchers think that this is a core
element where
future capabilities will come from. It is
also referred
to as unhobbling, schlep, and various
other terms, but
all of them point to the same underlying
principle.
Raw scaling of single model performance is
only one
part of overall AI capability advancement.
The textbook includes
Figure 1.37 here. It depicts an example of
how
much the performance on a benchmark can
change just
by using post-training techniques, like
doing reasoning-specific training and
allowing the model to think for longer.
The base
model scores around 4.5% on the humanity's
last exam
benchmark, HLE. Whereas with each
subsequent unhobbling step, we
see jumps and performance leading up to a
25%
score on the benchmark. Even the tool-
based scaling hypothesis
is debated. Some argue that tools or scale
poured
into LLMs is unlikely to lead to AGI as
they define it. They advocate for
completely different architectures
from transformer-based LLMs, focusing
instead on things like neurosymbolic
approaches, ensemble methods, or a
completely new undiscovered architecture.
Despite disagreements about whether scale
will lead to true
AGI, major AI labs are betting heavily on
scaling.
Sam Altman from OpenAI has stated his
belief that
scaling is going to be a big component
leading
to capability gains. Anthropics CEO Dario
Amadeh has expressed
similar views, and DeepMind safety teams
similarly wrote that
not many more fundamental innovations are
needed for AGI.
This consensus suggests that regardless of
whether strong, weak,
or tools-based scaling dominates, scale
itself will likely remain
central to near-term progress.