Section 1.6, Forecasting Timelines If TAI
is able to
automate cognitive labor and thereby
automate MLR&D by 2030,
we need safety solutions working soon.
There's no time
for slow theoretical research. We need
approaches that work
with current systems and scale quickly. If
it arrives
around 2050, we have breathing room for
fundamental alignment
research, for building robust governance
frameworks, and for developing
evaluation methods we can trust. This
section presents empirical
trends and forecasts of AI progress using
data-driven analysis.
Our goal is to build on the scaling laws
discussion and present the strongest
available evidence so you
can form informed views on where AI might
be
headed. We focus primarily on compute-
based trends, with heavier
quantitative forecasts presented alongside
graphs. An appendix covers judgment-based
surveys and expert opinions. Remember the
old saying, all
models are wrong, but some are useful.
Forecasting helps
us form internally consistent beliefs
about different possible futures.
The way that you should think about
forecasting methods
is not as concrete predictions of
timelines, but instead
as scenarios that help you reason about
different potential
futures. They let you check if your
beliefs are
internally coherent. If you think
investment grows 5x per
year, and software efficiency improves 3x
per year, and
hardware scales 15% per year, and each
order of
magnitude automates at least 10% of tasks,
then what
does that imply? Is the outcome of this
combination
consistent with the future you expect? If
you're surprised,
maybe one of your input beliefs needs
updating. Current
evidence suggests scaling can continue
through at least 2030.
Training compute has grown 5x per year
since 2020.
Data set sizes have grown by 3.7x per year
and training costs by 3.5x per year. As a
concrete example, this means that in mid
2025, the
cost of training a single AI model, GROC4,
including
hardware and electricity, is estimated at
$480 million USD.
By 2030, this trajectory points to a
single training
run requiring hundreds of billions of
dollars and gigawatts
of power, which is comparable to running a
small
city. These are unprecedented scales, but
analysis suggests that
they aren't impossible. The question is
whether the economic
incentives justify it and whether the
infrastructure constraints, chips,
power, data can be overcome in time. AI
systems
that leverage more compute during training
and inference are
capable of automating progressively more
tasks. Initially, only a
small fraction of tasks are automated, so
running AI
systems creates relatively little economic
value. Once effective compute
budgets grow large enough, the range of
automated tasks
expands until eventually all cognitive
labor becomes automated. This
feedback loop, Compute Enabling
Automation, which increases productivity,
which
funds more compute, continues until full
labor automation. At
this point, the textbook shows Figure
1.38. It depicts
the feedback loop of compute leading to
more automation,
which increases productivity, which
increases both the amount of
produced compute, as well as compute
efficiency, completing the
loop until all labor is automated. The
path to
full labor automation runs through three
resources. Compute, data,
and the economic returns that fund both.
In the
subsections below, we examine each
constraint. For compute, we
look at effective flop growth, the
combination of more
chips, better algorithms, and more
efficient hardware. For data,
we track when we exhaust the internet's
text and
what happens after. Each section answers,
does this constraint
stop scaling before 2030? The appendix
provides detailed breakdowns
of the other relevant factors, like
investment trends, semiconductor
production, and power infrastructure for
readers who want the
full picture. All forecasts come with wide
error margins
that compound over time. Even if we assume
compute-based
scaling laws hold, we still don't know how
much
compute TAI will actually require. One
framework for estimating
the compute required for general
intelligence uses biological anchors,
treating the human brain as a proof of
concept.
These estimates vary dramatically
depending on the biological process
used as a reference. A lower bound
considers the
compute performed in learning skills
during a human lifetime,
about 10 to the 28th flop, while a
theoretical
upper bound accounts for the total compute
performed in
shaping humans over evolutionary history,
about 10 to the
power of 41 flop, 12 orders of magnitude
of
uncertainty, It's like not knowing if
something costs one
dollar or a trillion dollars. When someone
says AGI
in 2045, they mean somewhere in the 2030s,
2050s
range, with 2045 as a rough center, not a
precise state. The same principle applies
to all trends
and forecasts presented through this
section. For example, projections
of available chips range by a factor of 20
times, and some compute estimates span 50
times. Section.
Effective compute. Effective compute
combines three independent factors that
each multiply your AI capabilities.
Scaling laws track performance
against compute, but compute means more
than just counting
GPUs. When researchers say GPT-4 used more
compute than
GPT-3, they're not just talking about
running more hardware
for longer. They're talking about the
growth in effective
compute, measured in effective floating
point operations, e-flops, As
an analogy, think of it like measuring how
far
a fleet of cars can travel. You need three
things. How many cars you have, chip
production, how
fast each car goes, hardware efficiency,
and how efficiently
you're driving, software efficiency. The
relationship looks like this.
Effective compute equals software
efficiency times hardware efficiency times
number of chips. As an illustrative
example, think about
wanting to train a model that gets 90%
accuracy
on some benchmark. In 2020, that might
have required
1 billion flop using the algorithms
available then. But
by 2025, better training methods, hardware
utilization and other
algorithmic improvements mean you only
need 100 million flop
to hit that same 90% accuracy. Your
software got
10x more efficient. better algorithms
multiply your effective compute
without building a single new chip.
Meanwhile, the physical
efficiency of your chips got better too. A
GPU does more flop per dollar than a 2020
GPU. That's hardware efficiency. And
you're also just making
more chips overall as more investment
keeps flowing in.
So the total effective flops changes as a
function
of all three of these variables. Each
factor can
improve independently, which is why
effective compute grows faster
than any single input. You can build more
chips
without improving their speed. You can
develop better software
to make use of existing hardware. You can
design
faster processors without changing either
your software or building
more chips. When all three improve
simultaneously, as they
have been, the total compute available,
effective compute, compounds
much faster than hardware trends alone
would suggest. Here's
are the trends for each in 2025, with more
details in the appendix. Hardware
efficiency. GPU performance grows
at 1.35x per year. Each new chip
generation does
more flops for the same cost. Algorithmic
efficiency. Software
improvements cut the compute needed for a
given result
by roughly three times per year. Better
trading methods
mean you need less hardware to hit the
same
benchmark. Chip production. The number of
AI chips produced
has grown 2.3 times per year since 2019,
driven
by semiconductor fab expansions and
massive capital investment. There
is figure 1.39 in the textbook here. It
depicts
growth in effective compute breaks down
into three parts.
Growth in computing hardware, improvements
in hardware efficiency, and
software efficiency gains. The textbook
includes Figure 1.40 here.
It depicts the gate model by Epic AI,
translates
a given stock of effective compute into a
degree
of AI automation. This occurs by expanding
the fraction
of tasks that can be automated, and by
increasing
the effective runtime compute on tasks
that are already
automated. Wide-spread automation often
happens within two decades from
the start of the simulation. Note that
gate uses
the abstract notion of a fraction of
economically useful
tasks, as a simplification, and does not
specify the
tasks and the order in which they are
automated.
The red line showcases aggressive
parameter settings. Green is
conservative parameter settings. The red
zone highlights the difference
in timelines to full automation between
aggressive and conservative
models. At this point, the textbook shows
Figure 1.41.
It depicts simulation of labor share of
income over
the next decades, using the gate model.
The red
line showcases aggressive parameter
settings. Green is conservative parameter
settings. The red zone highlights the
difference in timelines
to full automation between aggressive and
conservative models. The
fraction of gross world product, GWP, paid
out to
human workers rapidly decreases as AI
becomes the primary
source of labor. We talk about wages
falling below
subsistence levels in the next chapter
under Automation Systemic
Risks. Section training data. Besides just
effective compute, the
second overarching factor that we have to
take into
consideration is the amount of available
data to train
on. The training data set size for
language models
has grown by 3.7x per year since 2010. The
internet has maybe 30 years worth of text
data
at current consumption rates, but will hit
that wall
around 2028. The indexed web contains
roughly 500 trillion
tokens of text after removing duplicates.
The largest models
in 2024 train on about 15 trillion tokens.
If
we keep scaling at 4x per year,
projections say
that we will exhaust high-quality public
text data between
2026 and 2032. Three escape routes exist.
Whether data
actually constrain scaling through 2030
depends on how well
these alternatives work. Multi-modal data.
The internet has 10
trillion images and 10 trillion seconds of
video. If
encoded efficiently, this could 3 to 10 x
the
effective data supply. Synthetic data. AI
generating its own
training data removes the constraint
entirely, if the outputs
are high enough quality. Post-training
methods like reinforcement learning
on reasoning tasks already demonstrate
this works for some
domains. Task-based learning. Self-play
reinforcement learning can generate
training
data through environment interaction. This
means AI's can learn
without human-generated pre-training
examples, as long as tasks can
be formalized as games with explicit rules
and success
metrics, like Go or Chess. For example,
Alpha Zero
learned superhuman strategies without any
human gameplay examples, using
only the game rules and billions of self-
played matches.
In principle, this approach could be
extended to teaching
any arbitrary task, allowing for data-free
learning through self-play
on specified tasks. This is still very
speculative. It
requires simulation environments encoding
task dynamics, explicit reward functions,
and tractable state spaces. There is
figure 1.42 in
the textbook here. It depicts projections
of future data
set sizes, according to three different
scaling policies. Depending
on the degree of overtraining, the stock
is fully
used between 2025 and 2030.