Section 1.2 Current Capabilities AI models
can write, reason,
code, generate media, and control robots,
often matching or
surpassing expert human performance on
specific tasks. In this
first section, we'll try to give you a
sense
of what AI is actually capable of doing as
of late 2025. Numbers and graphs don't
really make
these capabilities tangible, so we will
try to include
as many videos, images, and examples to
really help
you get a sense of where AI currently
stands.
But in case you are interested, we also
mention
benchmark scores that measure progress
quantitatively. The trajectory matters
more than a snapshot. This section can
serve both
as a quick history and as a snapshot of
current capabilities. As you read through
it, try to
keep in mind how quickly we got here.
Language
generation went from coherent paragraphs
to research assistants in
a few years. Image generation went from
laughable to
professional grade in a decade. Video
generation seems to
be following a similar path, compressed
into three years.
If you're already familiar with AI or
machine learning,
some of these stories might be review for
you,
but hopefully everyone who reads will be
able to
take away at least one new thing from this
section. Section Games Game Playing AI is
already at
the superhuman level for many games.
Comparing AI and
humans at games has been a common theme
through
the last few decades, with AI making
continuous progress.
IBM's Deep Blue defeated chess grandmaster
in 1997. IBM's
Watson won overwhelmingly at Jeopardy in
2011, and AlphaGo
managed to beat the Go World Champion,
Lisa Doll,
in 2016. AlphaGo was a landmark moment,
because this
is a game with more possible positions
than atoms
in the observable universe. During Game 2,
AlphaGo played
Move 37, a move that had a 1 in
10,000 chance of being used. Commentators
initially thought it
was a mistake. Instead, it was the move
that
several rounds later led to winning the
game. The
move demonstrated what many consider to be
sparks of
genuine creativity that diverged from
centuries of human play
that the model was trained on. The
textbook includes
Figure 1.2 here. It depicts Kasparov, a
chess grandmaster,
defeated the chess system Deep Blue in
1996. One
year later, in 1997, he resigned in the
last
game of the six-game match after 19 moves,
granting
the win to Deep Blue. For the first time
in the history of mankind, I saw something
similar
to an artificial intellect. AI's
superhuman game-playing capability extends
to video games. Machine learning
techniques on simple Atari
games in 2013 progressed to Open AI 5
defeating
world champions at Dota 2 in 2019. That
same
year, DeepMind's Alpha Star beat
professional esports players at
Starcraft 2. These are games with open-
ended real-time environments
requiring thousands of rapid decisions and
long-term planning. By
2020, the MuZero system played Atari
games, Go, Chess,
and Shogi without even being told the
rules. These
are AI's that all play and learn
autonomously without
human intervention. In 2025, game-playing
AI's have evolved to
open-ended environments across a huge
variety of games. They
carry the abilities learned from one game
onto the
next, improving their performance over
time. At this point,
the textbook shows Figure 1.3. It depicts
the history
of going from AlphaGo, which was already
superhuman in
2016, to Mu0, which was not only
superhuman, but
was trained without any human data, domain
knowledge, or
knowledge of the game's rules. Gameplaying
AI is relatively
narrow in what it can do. Despite this, it
is extremely impressive because of the
strategic planning, pattern
recognition, and adversarial thinking at
displays. These same reasoning
abilities, planning ahead, building
strategies, adapting to feedback that
started with Gameplaying now also apply to
scientific research,
mathematical proofs, and complex real-
world problem solving. There is
Figure 1.4 in the textbook here. It
depicts video
showcasing example of the state of game
playing AI
assistance using the SEMA 2 model in 2025.
The
textbook includes Figure 1.5 here. It
depicts video showcasing
example of the state of game playing AI
using
the SEMA 2 model in 2025. The textbook has
a supplementary note titled, Planning and
Continuous Learning in
Minecraft with GPT-4, which will skip over
here. Section.
Text Generation. Generating text can take
language models far
beyond simple conversations. You're
probably familiar with chat GPT.
These types of language generation AIs are
what we
call large language models, or LLMs. In
2018, early
versions of these LLMs could only write a
few
coherent paragraphs, but over a few short
years, they
have gotten a lot better. By 2025, GPT-5
gets
92.5% of questions right, in domains
ranging from highly
complex STEM fields, international law, to
nutrition and religion,
as measured by the MMLU benchmark. Models
like Clawed
by Anthropic, GROC by X, GLM 4.7 by ZPU
AI, and deep-seek V3.2 showcased similar
levels of performance
across various domains. There is Figure
1.7 in the
textbook here. It depicts, in a few short
years,
LLMs have gone from being barely useful to
being
regularly used coding assistance. The
textbook includes Figure 1.8
here. It depicts performance on common
exams as a
percentile compared to human test takers.
Notice the large
jump from GPT 3.5 to GPT 4 on these
tests, often from well below the median
human to
the very top of the human range. The jump
from GPT 3 to GPT 4 was in a
single year. The textbook has interactive
figure 1.1 here,
which you can explore in the online
version. It
shows we are seeing an explosion in
language models
due to their generality and applicability
to a wide
range of tasks. At this point, the
textbook shows
figure 1.9. It depicts a list of nowhere
near-solved
problems in AI, from a brief history of
AI,
published in January 2021. They also say,
at present,
we have no idea how to get computers to
do the tasks at the bottom of the list.
But everything in the category nowhere
near-solved has been
solved by GPT-4, except human-level
general intelligence. Language models
have provided a core around which we have
seen
many impressive capabilities emerge, like
scientific research, reasoning, and
software development. All of these
capabilities stem from the
same principle of generating language and
gradually refining it.
Section, tool use. LLMs can intelligently
use external tools,
dramatically boosting performance.
Language models in 2020 exhibited
remarkable
abilities to solve new tasks from
instructions, but they
used to struggle with basic functions like
arithmetic. Instead
of trying to get a single model to do
everything, increasingly LLMs use external
tools to achieve both
capabilities. They recognize when they
need a calculator, code
interpreter, or up-to-date information
from a search engine, and
call these tools appropriately. Tool use
significantly improves model
performance. For example, the OpenAI-03
model with external tools
outperforms O3 alone by almost 5% on
benchmarks like
humanity's last exam, HLE. In December
2025, at least
10,000 tool servers are operational,
including meta tools like
a tool to search for tools to help LLMs
find the exact one they need for the
specific
situation. This leads to a significant
enough boost that
companies now report benchmark performance
separately. with and without
tools. The textbook includes Figure 1.10
here. It depicts
a simple example from Toolformer. The
model autonomously decides
to call different APIs, from top to
bottom, a
question answering system, a calculator, a
machine translation system,
and a Wikipedia search engine, to obtain
information that
is useful for completing a piece of text.
Section,
Reasoning, and Research. Models now
demonstrate multi-step reasoning by
working through problems step by step. In
addition to
using tools, LLMs now show their
reasoning, catch their
own errors, and backtrack when needed. In
late 2024,
OpenAI introduced 01, the first reasoning
model. These AIs
allocate more effort per problem, trading
thinking time for
accuracy. The longer they think, the
better their responses
tend to get. Using these reasoning
techniques, both OpenAI
and Google DeepMind achieved gold medal
performance at the
2025 International Mathematical Olympiad.
On Frontier Math, a test
of research level mathematics, GPT 5.2
solved 41% of
Tier 1 to 3 problems. In ML terms,
thinking
time is called inference. It is the act of
generating new tokens, words, so
increasing thinking time is
more formally called inference time
scaling. Similar to tool
use, this also led to such a boost in
performance that companies report high
thinking time, high compute
results of benchmark separately than no
thinking time, low
compute results. At this point, the
textbook shows Figure
1.11. It depicts a sample of an easy Tier
1 problem from frontier math, an extremely
difficult mathematics
test created by mathematicians. GPT 5.2
can solve 41%
of Tier 1.3 problems, and 29% of the even
harder Tier 4 problems. LLMs can help
generate and
evaluate scientific hypotheses. Combining
techniques like letting AI think
for longer and tools like web search or
specialized
AI models, we are starting to see research
assistants.
As one example, Google introduced AI co-
scientist in 2025.
The team used it to generate and evaluate
proposals
for repurposing drugs, identifying drug
targets, and explaining antimicrobial
resistance in real-world laboratories.
Others have attempted to build
a fully autonomous AI scientist, which
generates novel research
ideas, writes code, executes experiments,
visualizes results, describes its
findings by writing a full scientific
paper, and then
runs a simulated review process for
evaluation. There is
figure 1.12 in the textbook here. It
depicts an
example of the Google co-scientist. You
can see the
thinking time labeled as test time compute
increasing on
the left. AI is transitioning to an active
research
collaborator across scientific domains.
Instead of only using language
models, companies are also using
approaches similar to Alpha0
to create a whole range of specialized
models for
scientific domains. For example, Demis
Hassabis and John Jumper
were awarded the Nobel Prize in Chemistry
for their
work on building Alpha Fold. This is a
model
that helped solve the long outstanding
protein folding problem,
and its successors Alpha Fold 2 and 3
continue
to aid thousands of researchers in
biology. Similarly, Alpha
Genome is helping us better understand
human DNA. Alpha
Evolve is helping generate faster
algorithms for machine learning,
and Alpha Chip helps design the
semiconductors that run
algorithms. The textbook includes Figure
1.13 here. It depicts
animation, showing alpha genome, taking 1
million DNA letters
as input, and predicting diverse molecular
properties across different
tissues and cell types. Beyond just
mathematics and scientific
research, AI models are also developing
more abstract intellectual
skills. LLMs have some level of
metacognition. They can
evaluate the validity of their own claims
and predict
which questions they will be able to
answer correctly.
They have some knowledge about their own
selves and
their limitations. Similarly, they display
the ability to attribute
mental states to themselves and others,
theory of mind.
This helps in predicting human behaviors
and responses. We
are going to talk more about how we
concretely
define and measure things like
intelligence, metacognition, and so
on in later sections. At this point, the
textbook
shows Figure 1.14. It depicts an example
puzzle from
the abstraction and reasoning corpus for
AI, or ARC-AGI-V1.
These are designed to be easy for humans,
but
very hard for AI's. Models are able to
solve
increasing numbers of such abstract
reasoning puzzles, especially with
the advent of large reasoning models, or
LRMs, in
2025. Section Software Development. Coding
is evolving from autocomplete
to collaborative software development.
LLMs can generate text in
any form, and one particular type of text
that
they are proving to be especially good at
is
generating code. When paired with
reasoning capabilities and tools,
LLMs read documentation, edit code bases
spanning thousands of
files, run tests, debug failures, and
iterate until tests
pass, with increasingly minimal human
guidance. In 2025, systems
like Claude Opus 4.5, Gemini 3 Pro, and
GPT
5.2 implement features and entire
applications increasingly independently.
When
tested against real GitHub issues from
open source projects,
in 2024, AI systems Claude 3 Opus could
solve
just 15% problems. But by 2025, this had
jumped
to being able to solve 74% of issues,
tools
plus Claude 4 Opus. There is Figure 1.15
in
the textbook here. It depicts AI systems
now develop
themselves. Boris Churney, creator of
Claude Code and Thropics
AI-powered software development tool,
stated in December 2025 that
100% of his contributions to Claude Code
over the
previous 30 days were written by Claude
Code itself.
Churney, 2025, Twitter. Section, Vision,
Images, and Video Image
generation progressed from unrecognizable
noise to photo-realistic scenes in
under a decade. In 2014, Generative
Adversarial Networks GANs
produced grainy low-resolution faces. By
2023, models generated detailed
images from complex text prompts. Models
like mid-journey V7
create photorealistic scenes nearly
indistinguishable from professional
photography. Video
generation is following a similar
trajectory. AI-generated videos and
deepfakes are getting increasingly
indistinguishable from real videos. The
textbook includes Figure 1.16 here. It
depicts an example
of the evolution of image generation. At
the top
left, starting from GANs, Generative
Adversarial Networks, to the
bottom right, an image from mid-journey
V5. At this
point, the textbook shows Figure 1.17. It
depicts improvements
between the V1 of the mid-journey image
generation model
in early 2022 to the V6 in December 2023.
Prompt, high-quality photography of a
young Japanese woman smiling,
backlighting, natural pale light, film
camera by Rinku Kawawuchi,
HDR. There is Figure 1.18 in the textbook
here.
It depicts sample of an AI-generated video
by OpenAI
Sora 2, prompt, a gymnast flips on a
balance
beam, cinematic. Multimodal models combine
language and image understanding
capabilities. In 2025, Multimodal models
answer questions about spatial
relationships and images, read embedded
text in complex scenes,
and extract information from charts and
diagrams. Image models
released in 2025, handle generation, and
sophisticated editing across
modalities. Systems like Gemini 3 Pro
Image work text-to-image,
image-to-image, and handle complex
editing, changing lighting, style, or
composition while maintaining coherence.
The textbook includes Figure 1.19
here. It depicts an infographic containing
both images and
educational text generated by Google's
nano-banana pro model. Prompt.
Create an infographic that shows how to
make a
lychee chai. At this point, the textbook
shows Figure
1.20. It depicts example of extending
video and image
generation to an interactive world. This
was generated by
DeepMind Genie 3. The bottom left arrows
indicate the
user interacting with the generated
environment. Section Robotics. Both
AI and robotics are evolving with robots
giving AI
physical embodiment in the real world.
Robotics is combining
LLMs and visual models to create robot
control models
EG, RT1, or RT2. These robots can use
techniques
borrowed from language models, like
breaking complex actions into
step-by-step plans to control robot
manipulators. They manage to
learn behaviors like opening cabinets,
operating elevators, and cooking
tasks through observing human
demonstrations. Robots have demonstrated
the
ability to perform intricate manipulation,
sauteing shrimp, storing heavy
pots and cabinets, and rinsing pans. There
is Figure
1.21 in the textbook here. It depicts
Sarah RT2
model for manipulation tasks. The robot's
actions are conditioned
on images and text commands. Autonomous
robots are moving
from research labs into real-world
industrial deployment at significant
scale. In 2023, China installed 276,300
industrial robots. These
systems handle welding, parts assembly,
materials handling, and quality
inspection. Tasks requiring precision, but
not necessarily advanced reasoning.
In addition to industrial robots,
warehouse robotics represents one
of the most mature deployments. Amazon
operates over 1
million robots across its fulfillment
network, handling everything from
inventory storage to package sorting.
Robots in warehouses and
industry are able to handle packages,
speed up inventory
identification using machine vision, and
autonomously unload shipping containers.
At this point, there is video 1.1 in the
textbook. It covers video showcasing one
example of the
state of humanoid robots in 2024. The
textbook includes
Figure 1.22 here. It depicts Boston
Dynamics stretch robot
that can autonomously unload shipping
containers, lift up to
50 pounds, and clear away mist boxes along
the
way. At this point, the textbook shows
Figure 1.23.
It depicts Amazon has a huge fleet of
robots
that automate its warehouses. This is an
example of
the Hercules robot that retrieves shelves
of products and
delivers them to employees who then pick
the items
customers ordered for shipping.