Section 1.7. Takeoff. This final section
synthesizes a lot
of the discussion that has happened
through this chapter.
We started from where we are currently and
went
all the way to forecasting specific trends
in the
inputs to AI capabilities. So this section
lays out
different sides of the debate on what the
combination
of all of this implies. Here is a quote
by Jan Lekun. There is no question that
machines
will become smarter than humans, in all
domains in
which humans are smart, in the future.
It's a
question of when and how, not a question
of
if. Takeoff speed refers to how quickly AI
systems
become dramatically more powerful than
they are today, and
cause major societal changes. This is
related to but
distinct from AI timelines, how long until
we develop
advanced AI. While timelines tell us when
transformative AI
might arrive, takeoff speeds tell us what
happens after
it arrives. Does AI capability and impact
increase gradually
over years or explosively over days or
weeks? When
analyzing different takeoff scenarios, we
can look at several
key factors. Speed. How quickly do AI
capabilities improve?
Continuity. Do capabilities improve
smoothly or in sudden jumps?
Homogeneity. How similar are different AI
systems to each
other? Polarity. How concentrated is power
among different AI
systems? In the next section, we discuss
just one
of these factors that tends to be the most
debated. Takeoff speed. The rest,
continuity, homogeneity, and polarity
are explained in an appendix. section,
speed. In a
slow takeoff scenario, AI capabilities
improve gradually over months
or years. We can see this pattern in
recent
history. The transition from GPT-3 to
GPT-4 brought significant
improvements in reasoning, coding, and
general knowledge, but these
advances happened over several years
through incremental progress. Paul
Cristiano describes slow takeoff as
similar to the industrial
revolution, but 10x100x faster. Terms like
slow takeoff and
soft takeoff are often used
interchangeably. In mathematical terms,
slow takeoff scenarios typically show
linear or exponential growth
patterns. With linear growth, capabilities
increase by the same
absolute amount each year. Imagine an AI
system that
gains a fixed number of new skills
annually. More
commonly, we might see exponential growth,
where capabilities increase
by a constant percentage. Similar to how
we discussed
scaling laws in earlier sections. Just as
model performance
improves predictably with compute and
data, slow take-off suggests
capabilities would grow at a study, but
manageable rate.
This might manifest as GDP growing at 10
to
30%. Slow take-off provides us time to
adapt and
respond. If we discover problems with our
current safety
approaches, we can adjust them before AI
becomes significantly
more powerful. This connects directly to
what we'll discuss
in later chapters about governance and
oversight. Slow Take
Off allows for iterative refinement of
safety measures and
gives time for coordination between
different actors and institutions.
The textbook includes Figure 1.43 here. It
depicts an
illustration of slow, continuous takeoff.
Fast takeoff describes scenarios
where AI capabilities increased
dramatically over very short periods,
perhaps days or even hours. Instead of the
gradual
improvement we saw from GPT-3 to GPT-4,
imagine an
AI system making that much progress every
day. This
could happen through recursive self-
improvement, where an AI system
becomes better at improving itself,
creating an accelerating feedback
loop. Mathematically, fast takeoff
involves super exponential or hyperbolic
growth, where the growth rate itself
increases over time.
Rather than capabilities doubling every
year as an exponential
growth, they might double every month,
then every week,
then every day. This relates to what we
discussed
in the scaling section about potential
feedback loops in
AI development. If AI systems can improve
the efficiency
of AI research itself, we might see this
kind
of accelerating progress. The dramatic
speed of fast takeoff
creates unique challenges for safety. As
we'll explore in
the chapter on strategies, many current
safety approaches rely
on testing systems, finding problems, and
making improvements. But
in a fast takeoff scenario, we might only
get
one chance to get things right. If an AI
system starts rapidly self-improving, we
need safety measures that
work robustly from the start, because we
won't have
time to fix problems once they emerge.
Terms like
fast take-off, hard take-off, and fume are
often used
interchangeably. At this point, the
textbook shows figure 1.44.
It depicts an illustration of fast
continuous take-off, which
is usually taken to mean super-exponential
or hyperbolic growth.
The growth rate itself increases. The
speed of AI
take-off fundamentally shapes the
challenge of making AI safe.
If progress follows predictable patterns
as our current understanding
suggests, we might have more warning and
time to
prepare. But if new mechanisms, like
recursive self-improvement, create
faster feedback loops, we need different
strategies. Today, when
we discover that language models can be
jailbroken, companies
can patch these vulnerabilities in the
next release. In
a slow takeoff, this pattern could
continue. We'd have
time to discover and fix safety issues as
they
arise. But in a fast takeoff, we might
need
to solve all potential jail-breaking
vulnerabilities before deploying the
AI, because a system could become too
powerful to
safely modify before we can implement any
further safety
fixes. The majority of experts,
researchers and engineers, agree
that AI will pose risks, and it should be
developed responsibly. The differences are
in small nuances of
how to respond. These can often be boiled
down
to whether they expect problems to be
noticeable and
fixable in time, or too fast for us to
respond. Unfortunately, these sometimes
get misreported as AI experts
disagree on AI risks. To quote Andrew
Aing, this
is how we build airplanes. We build
airplanes, sometimes
they crash tragically, and then we fix it.
I
think AI sometimes gives bad outputs, and
then we
fix it. And that's how we actually make
these
things reliable. There is figure 1.45 in
the textbook
here. It depicts comparison of slow versus
fast takeoff,
showcasing that while described as
linguistically slow. Understanding fast
versus slow helps you get the overview of
the
takeoff debate. But there can be a bunch
of
other factors like, are there sudden
jumps? Takeoff continuity.
How many systems are taking off at the
same
time? Takeoff polarity. How
architecturally similar are these systems?
Takeoff similarity. If you want to learn
more, feel
free to read the section, takeoff
arguments. The overhang
argument, there might be situations where
there are substantial
advancements or availability in one aspect
of the AI
system, such as hardware or data, but the
corresponding
software or algorithms to fully utilize
these resources haven't
been developed yet. The term overhang is
used because
these situations imply a kind of stored or
latent
potential. Once the software or algorithms
catch up to
the hardware or data, there could be a
sudden
unleashing of this potential, leading to a
rapid leap
in AI capabilities. Overhangs provide one
possible argument for
why we might favor discontinuous or fast
takeoffs. There
are two types of overhangs commonly
discussed. Hardware Overhang.
This refers to a situation where there is
enough
computing hardware to run many powerful AI
systems, but
the software to run such systems hasn't
been developed
yet. If such hardware could be repurposed
for AI,
this would mean that as soon as one
powerful
AI system exists, probably a large number
of them
would exist, which might amplify the
impact of the
arrival of human level AI. Data Overhang.
This would
be a situation where there is an abundance
of
data available that could be used for
training AI
systems, but the AI algorithms capable of
utilizing all
that data effectively haven't been
developed or deployed yet.
Overhangs are also used as a counter-
argument to why
AI pauses do not meaningfully affect
takeoff speeds. One
counter argument to the overhang argument
is that it
relies on the assumption that during the
time that
we are pausing AI development, the rate of
production
of chips will remain constant. It could be
argued
that the company's manufacturing these
chips will not make
as many chips if data centers aren't
buying them.
However, this argument only works if the
pauses for
any appreciable length of time. Otherwise,
the data centers
might just stockpile the chips. It is also
possible
to make progress on improved chip design
without having
to manufacture as many during the pause
period. However,
during the same pause period, we could
also make
progress on AI safety techniques. The
Economic Growth Argument
Historical patterns of economic growth,
driven by human population
increases, suggests a potential for slow
and continuous AI
takeoff. This argument says that as AI's
augment the
effective economic population, we might
witness a gradual increase
in economic growth, mirroring past
expansions, but at a
potentially accelerated rate due to AI-
enabled automation. Limitations and
AI's ability to automate certain tasks
alongside societal and
regulatory constraints, e.g. that medical
or legal services can
only be rendered by humans, could lead to
a
slower expansion of AI capabilities.
Alternatively, growth might far
exceed historical rates. Using a similar
argument for a
fast takeoff hinges on AI's potential to
quickly automate
human labor on a massive scale, leading to
unprecedented
economic acceleration. The textbook
includes Figure 1.46 here. It
depicts a visualization of the ranking of
arguments for
explosive economic growth, both in favor
and against, by
epoch AI. Compute centric takeoff
argument. This argument, similar
to the Bioanker's report, assumes that
compute will be
sufficient for transformative AI. Based on
this assumption, Tom
Davidson's 2023 report on compute-centric
AI takeoff discusses feedback
loops that may contribute to takeoff
dynamics. Investment feedback
loop. There might be increasing investment
in AI, as
AI's play a larger and larger role in the
economy. This increases the amount of
compute available to
train models, as well as potentially
leading to the
discovery of novel algorithms, all of this
increases capabilities,
which drives economic progress, and
further incentivizes investment.
Automation
Feedback Loop As AI's get more capable,
they will
be able to automate larger parts of the
work
of coming up with better AI algorithms, or
helping
in the design of better GPUs. Both of
these
will increase the capability of the AI's,
which in
turn allow them to automate more labor.
Depending on
the strength and interplay of these
feedback loops, they
can create a self-fulfilling prophecy,
leading to either an
accelerating fast take-off, if regulations
don't curtail various aspects
of such loops, or a slow take-off, if the
loops are weaker or counterbalanced by
other factors. The
entire model is shown in the diagram
below. At
this point, the textbook shows figure
1.47. It depicts
a summary of what a compute-centric
framework says about
take-off speeds. At this point, there is
video 1.3
in the textbook. It covers optional video
explaining the
argument behind automating research and
development. Automating research argument.
Researchers could potentially design the
next generation of ML
models more quickly by delegating some
work to existing
models, creating a feedback loop of ever
accelerating progress.
The following argument is put forth by
Ajaya Kotra.
Currently, human researchers collectively
are responsible for almost all
of the progress in AI research, but are
starting
to delegate a small fraction of the work
to
large language models. This makes it
somewhat easier to
design and train the next generation of
models. There
is figure 1.48 in the textbook here. It
depicts
a. This figure shows a representation of a
self-reinforcing
loop in red. It demonstrates how
internally deployed AI
systems are used to help automate AI R&D,
initially
alongside human researchers. These AIR&D
efforts culminate in a
more capable AI system, which can be
deployed as
a new, improved, automated researcher.
This cycle keeps repeating,
resulting in a self-free-enforcing loop.
The next generation is
able to handle harder tasks and more
different types
of tasks, so human researchers delegate
more of their
work to them. This makes it significantly
easier to
train the generation after that. Using
models gives a
much bigger boost than it did the last
time
around. Each round of this process makes
the whole
field move faster and faster. In each
round, human
researchers delegate everything they can
productively delegate to the
current generation of models. And the more
powerful those
models are, the more they contribute to
research. And
thus, the faster AI capabilities can
improve. So before
we see a recursive explosion of
intelligence, we see
a steadily increasing amount of the full
R&D process
being delegated to AI's. At some point,
instead of
a significant majority of the research and
design being
done by AI assistants at superhuman
speeds, it will
become that all of the research and design
for
AI is done by AI assistants at superhuman
speeds.
At this point, there is a possibility that
this
might eventually lead to a full automated
recursive intelligence
explosion. the intelligence explosion
argument. This concept of the
intelligence explosion is also central to
the conversation around
discontinuous takeoff. It originates from
IJ Good's thesis, which
posits that sufficiently advanced machine
intelligence could build a
smarter version of itself. This smarter
version could in
turn build an even smarter version of
itself, and
so on, creating a cycle that could lead to
intelligence vastly exceeding human
capability. In their 2012 report
on the evidence for intelligence
explosions, Mule, Hauser, and
Salomon delve into the numerous advantages
that machine intelligence
holds over human intelligence, which
facilitate rapid intelligence
augmentation.
These include computational resources.
Human computational ability remains
somewhat
stationary, whereas machine computation
possesses scalability. Speed, humans
communicate
at a rate of two words per second. while
GPT-4 can process 32k words in an instant.
Once
LLMs can write better than humans, their
speed will
most probably surpass us entirely.
Duplicability. Machines exhibit effortless
duplicability. Unlike humans, they do not
need birth, education,
or training. While humans predominantly
improve individually, machines have
the potential to grow collectively. Humans
take 20 years
to become competent from birth, whereas
once we have
one capable AI, we can duplicate it
immediately. Once
AI's reached the level of the best
programmer, we
can just duplicate this AI. The same goes
for
other jobs. Editability. Machines
potentially allow more regulated
variations.
They exemplify the equivalent of direct
brain enhancements via
neurosurgery in opposition to laborious
education or training requirements.
Humans can also improve and learn new
skills, but
they don't have root access to their
hardware. We
are just starting to be able to understand
the
genome's spaghetti code, while AI could
use code-versioning tools
to improve itself, being able to attempt
risky experiments
with backup options in case of failure.
This allows
for much more controlled variation. Goal
coordination. Copy AI's
possess the capability to share goals
effortlessly, a feat
challenging for humans.