Section 1.3 Foundation Models Foundation
Models represent a fundamental
shift in how we develop AI. Rather than
building
specialized models for many small specific
tasks, we can
now train large-scale models that serve as
a foundation
for many different applications. These
models are then specialized
later by a process called fine tuning to
perform
specific tasks. Think of this as similar
to how
we can build many different types of
buildings using
the same base structure. We can build
banks, restaurants,
or housing, but the underlying foundation
remains largely the
same. This is just a very quick intuitive
definition.
We will get more into the details in the
next few subsections on training,
properties, and risks. The
textbook includes video 1.2 here, which
you may want
to watch separately. It covers optional
video to understand
foundation models. The traditional
approach of training specialized AI
models for every task often proved
inefficient in limiting.
Progress was bottlenecked by the need for
human label
data and the inability to transfer
knowledge between tasks
effectively. Foundation models overcame
these limitations through a process
called self-supervised learning on massive
unlabeled data sets. This
breakthrough happened because of many
different reasons. Advances and
specialized hardware like GPUs, new
machine learning architectures like
Transformers, and increased access to huge
amounts of online
data are some of the more prominent
reasons for
this shift. In language processing, models
like GPT-4 and
Claude are examples of foundation models.
Both of these
have demonstrated the ability to generate
human language, have
complex conversations, and perform simple
reasoning tasks. Examples in
computer vision include models like Dolly3
and stable diffusion.
These are domain-specific examples, but we
are also seeing
a trend toward multimodal foundation
models, LLMMs. This includes
things like GPT4V and Gemini that can work
across
different types of data, processing and
generating text, images,
code, audio, and probably more in the
future. Even
in reinforcement learning, where models
were traditionally trained for
specific tasks, we're seeing foundation
models like Goddo demonstrate
the ability to learn general purpose
behaviors that can
be adapted to various different downstream
tasks. At this
point, there is interactive figure 1.2 in
the textbook,
available in the online version. It shows
number of
large-scale AI systems released per year.
describes the specific
area, application, or field in which a
large-scale AI
model is designed to operate. The 2025
data is
incomplete and was last updated 01 June
2025. Foundation
models mark a paradigm shift towards
general-purpose systems. This
paradigm introduces many new risks, which
didn't exist previously.
These include misuse risks from power
centralization, homogenization, and
dual use capabilities, just to name a few.
The
ability of foundation models to learn
broad transferable capabilities
has led to increasingly sophisticated
behaviors emerging from relatively
simple training objectives. Complex
capabilities, combined with generality and
stale, means we need to seriously consider
safety risks
beyond just misuse that previously seemed
theoretical or distant.
Beyond just misuse risk, things like
misalignment are becoming
an increasing concern with each new
capability that these
foundation models exhibit. We dedicate an
entire chapter to
the discussion of these risks, but we will
also
give you a small taste on the kinds of
possible risks in the next few subsections
as it
warrants some repetition. The textbook has
interactive figure 1.3
here, which you can explore in the online
version.
It shows cumulative number of large-scale
AI models by
domain since 2017. Describes the specific
area, application, or
field in which a large-scale AI model is
designed
to operate. What is the difference between
foundation models
and frontier models? Frontier models
represent the cutting edge
of AI capabilities. They are the most
advanced models
in their respective domains. While many
frontier models are
also foundation models, like Claude
3.5sonnet, this isn't always
the case. For example, AlphaFold, while
being a frontier
model in protein structure prediction,
isn't typically considered a
foundation model because it's specialized
for a single task
rather than serving as a general
foundation for multiple
applications. Section. Generally,
foundation models use a two-stage training
process. First, they go through what we
call a
pre-training, and then second, they can be
adapted through
various mechanisms, like fine-tuning or
scaffolding, to perform specific
tasks. Rather than learning from human
labeled examples for
specific tasks, these models learn by
finding patterns in
huge amounts of unlabeled data. There is
figure 1.24
in the textbook here. It depicts on the
opportunities
and risks of foundation models. Pre-
training is the initial
phase, where the model learns general
patterns and knowledge
from massive data sets of millions or
billions of
examples. During this phase, the model
isn't trained for
any specific task. Instead, it develops
broad capabilities that
can later be specialized. This generality
is both powerful
and concerning from a safety perspective.
While it enables
the model to adapt to many different
tasks, it
also means we can't easily predict or
constrain what
the model might learn to do. The textbook
includes
figure 1.25 here. It depicts on the
opportunities and
risks of foundation models. Self-
supervised learning is the key
technical innovation that makes foundation
models possible. This is
how we actually implement the pre-training
phase. Unlike traditional
supervised learning, which requires human
labeled data, SSL leverages
the inherent structure of the data itself
to create
training signals. For example, instead of
manually labeling images,
we might just hide part of a full image
we already have and ask a model to predict
what the rest should be. So it might
predict
the bottom half of an image given the top
half, learning about which objects often
appear together. As
an example, it might learn that images
with trees
and grass at the top often have more grass
or maybe a path at the bottom. It learns
about objects and their context. Trees and
grass often
appear in parks. Dogs are often found in
these
environments. paths are usually horizontal
and so on. These
learned representations can then be used
for a wide
variety of tasks that the model was not
explicitly
trained for, like identifying dogs and
images, or recognizing
parks, all without any human-provided
labels. The same concept
applies in language. A model might predict
the next
word in a sentence, such as the cat sat
on the learning grammar, syntax, and
context, as long
as we repeat this over huge amounts of
text.
After pre-training, foundation models can
be adapted through two
main approaches, fine-tuning and in-
context prompting. Fine-tuning involves
additional
training on a specific task or data set to
specialize the model's capabilities. For
example, we might use
reinforcement learning from human
feedback, RHLF, to make language
models better at following instructions or
being more helpful.
Prompting, on the other hand, involves
providing the model
with carefully crafted inputs that guide
it toward desired
behaviors without additional training. The
training process of foundation
models creates several unique safety
challenges. First, the self-supervised
nature of pre-training means we have
limited control over
what the model learns. It might develop
unintended capabilities
or behaviors. Second, the adaptation
process needs to reliably
preserve any safety properties we've
established during pre-training. Finally,
the massive scale of training data and
compute makes
it difficult to thoroughly understand or
audit what the
model has learned. Many of the safety
challenges we'll
discuss throughout this book from goal
misgeneralization to scalable
oversight are deeply connected to how
these models are
trained and adapted. Section Properties
The ability of foundation
models to transfer knowledge, generalize
across many different domains,
and develop emergent capabilities means we
can't rely on
traditional safety approaches that assume
narrow, predictable behavior. Transfer
learning is the ability to transfer
knowledge learned during
pre-training to new tasks and domains.
Rather than starting
from scratch for each task, we can
leverage the
general knowledge these models have
already acquired. This property
enables rapid adaptation and deployment.
It also means that
both capabilities and safety risks can
transfer in unexpected
ways. For example, a model might transfer
not just
useful knowledge, but also harmful biases
or undesired behaviors
to new applications. Zero-shot and few-
shot learning is the
ability to perform new tasks with very few
examples,
or even no examples at all. For example,
GPT-4
can solve novel reasoning problems just
from a natural
language description of the task. This
emergent ability to
generalize to new situations is powerful,
but concerning from
a safety perspective. If models can adapt
to novel
situations in unexpected ways, it becomes
harder to predict
and control their behavior and deployment.
Generalization in foundation
models works differently from traditional
AI systems. Rather than
just generalizing within a narrow domain,
these models can
generalize capabilities across domains in
surprising ways. However, this
generalization of capabilities often
happens without a corresponding
generalization
of goals or constraints. A critical safety
concern will
explore in detail in our chapter on goal-
miss generalization.
For example, a model might generalize its
ability to
manipulate text in unexpected ways without
maintaining the safety
constraints we intended. At this point,
the textbook shows
Figure 1.26. It depicts on the
opportunities and risks
of foundation models. Here is a quote by
Sam
Altman. Multimodality will definitely be
important. Speech in, speech
out, images, eventually video. Clearly
people really want that.
Customizability and personalization will
also be very important.