Section 1.9 Appendix Takeoff Section
Continuity Continuity describes whether
AI capabilities improve smoothly and
predictably or through sudden
unexpected jumps. This is different from
speed. Even a
fast takeoff could be continuous if the
rabid progress
follows predictable patterns and a slow
takeoff could be
discontinuous if it involves surprising
breakthroughs. Understanding continuity
helps
us predict whether we can extrapolate from
current trends,
like the scaling laws we discussed
earlier, or if
we should expect sudden departures from
these patterns. So
if you think of speed as a measure of
how quickly the AI becomes super
intelligent, Continuity can
be thought of as a measure of surprise. In
a continuous takeoff, AI capabilities
follow smooth, predictable trends.
The improvements we've seen in language
models provide a
good example. Each new model tends to be
somewhat
better than the last at tasks like coding
or
math. Following patterns we can roughly
predict from scaling
laws and algorithmic improvements. As we
saw in the
forecasting section, many aspects of AI
progress have shown
this kind of predictable behavior.
Continuous progress doesn't mean
linear or simple progress. It might still
involve exponential
or even super-exponential growth, but the
key is that
this growth follows patterns we can
anticipate. Think of
how GPT-4 is better than GPT-3, which was
better
than GPT-2. Each improvement was
significant, but not completely
surprising, given the increase in scale
and improved training
techniques. A continuous takeoff suggests
that current trends in
scaling laws and algorithmic progress
might extend even to
transformative AI systems. This would give
us more warning
about upcoming capabilities. and more
ability to prepare appropriate
safety measures. As we'll discuss in the
governance chapter,
even though progress is fast, this kind of
predictability
makes it comparatively easier to develop
and implement regulation
before AI systems become extremely
powerful or uncontrollable. Keeping
in mind, of course, that comparatively
easier does not
mean easy. A discontinuous takeoff
involves sudden jumps and
capability that break from previous
patterns. Instead of study
improvements and performance as we add
compute or data,
we might see the emergence of entirely new
capabilities
that weren't predicted by existing trends.
One hypothetical example
would be if an AI system suddenly
developed robust
general reasoning capabilities after
appearing to only handle narrow
tasks. This would represent a
discontinuity in the pattern
of AI development. The terms fast takeoff
and discontinuous
takeoff are often used interchangeably.
However, the image is
the subtle differences between the
concepts. Discontinuities could arise
through various mechanisms. We might
discover fundamentally new training
approaches that are dramatically more
efficient than current methods.
Or we might hit tipping points for
emergent capabilities,
where quantitative improvements in scale
lead to qualitative changes
in capability. An AI system might even
discover such
improvements about itself, leading to
unexpected jumps in capability.
The historical record provides some
precedent for both continuous
and discontinuous scientific progress. The
development of nuclear weapons
represented a discontinuous jump in
explosive power, while improvements
in computer processing power have followed
more continuous trends.
However, as we saw in the forecasting
section, technological
discontinuities have historically been
rare, which some researchers cite
as evidence-favoring continuous takeoff
scenarios. At this point, the
textbook shows figure 1.62. It depicts one
example illustration
of slow, discontinuous take-off, where
even though progress keeps
increasing, we might see sudden jumps in
progress. Homogeneity
describes how similar or different AI
systems are to
each other during the takeoff period. Will
we see
many diverse AI systems with different
architectures and capabilities?
Or will most advanced AI systems be
variations of
the same basic design? This isn't just
about technical
diversity. It's about whether advanced AI
systems will share
similar behaviors limitations and safety
properties. In a homogenous
takeoff, most advanced AI systems would be
fundamentally similar.
We can see hints of this pattern today.
Many
current language models are based on the
transformer architecture
and trained on similar data, leading to
similar capabilities
and limitations. In a homogenous takeoff,
this pattern would
continue. Perhaps most AI systems would be
fine-tuned versions
of a few base models, or different
implementations of
the same core breakthrough in AI design. A
factor
that could drive homogeneity is the sheer
scale required
to train advanced AI systems. If training
transformative AI
requires massive compute resources, as
scaling law suggests, then
only a few organizations might be capable
of training
base models from scratch. Other
organizations would build on
these base models, rather than developing
entirely new architectures,
leading to more homogenous systems.
Homogenous take-off could be
safer in some ways, but riskier in others.
If
we solve alignment for one AI system, that
solution
might work for other similar systems.
However, if there's
a fundamental flaw in the common
architecture or training
approach, it could affect all systems
simultaneously. It's like
having a monoculture and agriculture.
While easier to manage,
it's also more vulnerable to shared
weaknesses. There is
Figure 1.63 in the textbook here. It
depicts an
illustration of homogenous take-off. We
can see multiple different
overarching model architectures. The
figure shows three in different
colors. Within each architecture, the
take-off is roughly the
same, due to similarity in design,
regulations, and safety
mitigations. Note, the curves here with
architectures are purely
illustrative and are not meant to indicate
predicted growth
trajectories and comparisons between
different architectures. A heterogeneous
takeoff
is when we see significant architectural
diversity among advanced
AI systems. Different organizations might
develop fundamentally different approaches
to AI, leading to systems with distinct
strengths, weaknesses,
and behaviors. Some might be specialized
for specific domains,
while others are more general. Some might
be more
transparent, while others are more opaque.
Some might be
more aligned with human values, while
others might not
be. Competitive dynamics among AI projects
could exacerbate diversity
as teams race to achieve breakthroughs
without necessarily aligning
on methodologies or sharing crucial
information. As an example,
We might have a future where AI becomes a
strategic national asset, and AI
development is closely guarded.
In this environment, the pursuit of AI
capabilities becomes
siloed. Each company or country would then
employ different
development methodologies, potentially
leading to a wide range of
behaviors, functionalities, and safety
levels. Heterogeneous takeoff creates
different
challenges for safety. We'd need to
develop safety measures
that work across diverse systems, and we
couldn't necessarily
apply lessons learned from one system to
others. However,
diversity might provide some protection
against systemic risks. If
one approach proves dangerous,
alternatives would still exist. The
degree of homogeneity during takeoff has
significant implications for
how transformative AI might develop. In a
homogenous scenario,
progress might be more predictable, but
also more prone
to winner-take-all dynamics. A
heterogeneous scenario might be more
robust against single points of failure,
but harder to
monitor and control. The textbook includes
figure 1.64 here.
It depicts one example of heterogeneous
takeoff. We can
see multiple different overarching model
architectures. The figure shows
three in different colors. Within each
architecture, the takeoff
is different due to differences in design,
regulations, and
safety medications. Note, the curves here
with architectures are
purely illustrative and are not meant to
indicate predicted
growth trajectories and comparisons
between different architectures. Polarity.
Polarity
describes whether power and capability
becomes concentrated in a
single AI system or organization or
remains distributed among
multiple actors. In other words, will one
AI system
or group pull dramatically ahead of all
others? Or
will multiple AI systems advance in
parallel with comparable
capabilities? In a unipolar takeoff, one
AI system or
organization gains a decisive lead over
all others. This
could happen through a single
breakthrough, exceptional scaling
advantages,
or recursive self-improvement. For
example, if one AI system
becomes capable enough to substantially
accelerate its own development,
it might rapidly outpace all other
systems. The mathematics
of training compute provide one path to a
unipolar
outcome. If a doubling of compute leads to
reliable
improvements in capability, then an
organization that gets far
enough ahead in acquiring compute could
maintain or extend
their lead. Their improved systems could
then help them
develop even better training methods,
hardware, and attract investment,
creating a positive feedback loop that
others can't match.
But compute isn't the only path to
unipolarity. A
single organization might discover a
fundamentally better training approach,
or develop an AI system that's better at
improving
itself than at helping humans build
alternatives. Once any
actor gets far enough ahead, it might
become practically
impossible for others to catch up. At this
point,
the textbook shows Figure 1.65. It depicts
an illustration
of unipolar takeoff. One model, dark blue
here, significantly
outperforms all others. In a multi-polar
takeoff, multiple AI
systems or organizations, develop advanced
capabilities in parallel. This
could look like several large labs
developing different but
comparably powerful AI systems, or like
many actors having
access to similar AI capabilities through
open source models
or AI services. Today's AI landscape shows
elements of
multi polarity. Multiple organizations can
train large language models,
and techniques developed by OneLab are
often quickly adopted
by others. A multi-polar take-off might
continue this pattern,
with multiple groups maintaining similar
capabilities, even as those
capabilities become transformative. A
unipolar scenario raises concerns about
the concentration of power, while a multi-
polar world presents
challenges in coordination among diverse
entities or AI systems.
Both unipolar and multipolar worlds have
the potential for
misuse of advanced AI capabilities by
human actors. There
is figure 1.66 in the textbook here. It
depicts
an illustration of multi-polar takeoff. No
model significantly outperforms
the others, and they all take off at a
roughly competitive rate relative to each
other. In a
unipolar scenario, the actions and
alignment of a single
system or organization become crucial.
They might gain the
ability to shape the long-term future
unilaterally. This concentrates
risk in a single point of failure, but
might
also make coordination easier since fewer
actors need to
agree. A multipolar scenario creates
different challenges. Multiple advanced
systems might act in conflicting ways or
compete for
resources. This could create pressure to
deploy systems quickly
or cut corners on safety. There's also an
important
interaction between polarity and the other
aspects of takeoff
we've discussed. A fast take-off might be
more likely
to become unipolar, as the first system to
make
rapid progress could quickly outpace all
others. A slow
take-off might tend toward multipolarity,
giving more actors time
to catch up to any initial leads. Factors
influencing
polarity. Several key elements influence
whether takeoff polarity leans
towards a unipolar or multipolar outcome.
Speed of AI
development, a rapid takeoff might favor a
unipolar outcome
by giving a significant advantage to the
fastest developer.
In contrast, a slower takeoff could lead
to a
multipolar world, where many entities
reach advanced capabilities more
or less simultaneously. collaboration
versus competition. The degree of
collaboration and openness in the AI
research community can
significantly affect takeoff polarity.
High levels of collaboration and
information sharing could support a
multipolar outcome, while secretive
or highly competitive environments might
push towards unipolarity. regulatory
and economic dynamics. Regulatory
frameworks and economic incentives also
play a crucial role. Policies that
encourage diversity in
AI development and mitigate against the
accumulation of too
much power in any single entity's hands
could foster
a multipolar takeoff.