Chapter 1 Capabilities Section 1.1
Introduction AI has undergone
a massive shift in the last decade. Game
playing
systems developed strategic creativity
that surprised grandmasters. Language
models
evolving from funny autocomplete failures
to software engineering assistance
handling code bases spanning thousands of
files. These types
of examples reflect a change in how
technology is
evolving and raise a question that this
entire book
tries to answer. How do you make something
safe
when you don't fully understand what it
can do
and when its abilities might change
dramatically between the
time you start reading this chapter and
the time
you finish? This first chapter is about
mapping the
territory. Before we can discuss dangerous
capabilities, alignment strategies,
technical solutions, or governance
frameworks, the subjects of chapters
2, 3, and 4, the first step is getting
a sense of what AI systems can actually do
right now, how they got here, and where
the
future trends point. The first question to
answer is
what counts as general intelligence? The
systems we are
seeing now represent a move from narrow AI
systems
that do one thing well to general-purpose
AI systems,
foundation models, that learn general
patterns, adapt to new
situations, and do many things well. The
term AGI
gets thrown around constantly, but
different people mean wildly
different things by it. We'll walk you
through a
couple of different approaches to defining
intelligence, going from
the Turing test to psychometric
frameworks, before settling on
a practical, usable definition. capability
and generality as continuous
axes rather than binary categories. The
goal is to
be able to make specific concrete
statements like this
system performs at the 85th percentile
across 30% of
cognitive domains as measured by, concrete
enough to measure,
track, and build policy around. The second
question everyone
asks Why is this happening so fast
recently? The
answer is the bitter lesson of AI
research. Massive
computation consistently beats human
engineered knowledge. We'll look at
scaling laws. The empirical relationships
showing that more data
and compute predictably produce better
performance, and various sides
of the debate about whether scale alone is
sufficient
and sustainable for transformative AI, or
whether we'll need
some other algorithmic breakthroughs. The
last part of the
chapter will look ahead at the future.
Predicting when
AI might automate all cognitive labor
determines which safety
strategies are even viable. If
transformative AI arrives by
2030, we need solutions that work with
current systems
and scale quickly. If it's 2050, we have
time
for fundamental research. This means
looking at the different
scenarios for takeoff, whether progress
will be gradual or
explosive, continuous or discontinuous,
and what that means for
our ability to respond. The specific
examples and benchmark
scores in this chapter will be outdated
soon, but
the underlying patterns will remain.
Scaling laws, emergent capabilities,
the shift from narrow to general systems,
these trends
are stable enough for you to learn about,
even
as individual benchmarks become obsolete.
By the end of
this chapter, you should have a concrete
framework for
how to define AGI and much clearer
perspective on
the debates shaping the field of AI
safety. Let's
start with what these systems can actually
do and
how quickly that list is growing. There is
figure
1.1 in the textbook here. It depicts, we
first
explain foundation models, which have been
continuously showing improved
capabilities due to scale, then examine
empirically observed scaling
laws. Based on these trends, we look at
some
techniques that researchers use to try and
forecast future
AI progress.