Section 1.4, defining and measuring AGI.
Before we can
discuss AI safety, we need to agree on
what
we mean by AGI. In our previous section on
foundation models, we saw how modern AI
systems are
becoming increasingly powerful and general
purpose, but powerful at
what exactly? Some researchers claim we're
already seeing sparks
of AGI in the latest language models.
Others predict
human level AI within a decade, but human
level
at what exactly? How do we measure this?
Without
a clear definition, how do we assess such
claims
or plan appropriate safety measures? If
you can't define
something, you can't measure it. If you
can't measure
it, you can't reliably track progress,
identify or prepare
for risks. Think about an example from
physics. If
we want to design and enforce speed limits
for
cars, saying something moved five makes no
sense without
units. Did it move five meters, five feet,
or
five royal qubits? If we don't know how
far
or fast it moved, we can't enforce limits.
The
same applies to intelligence and
subsequent safety measures. Every
field needs standardized units, meters,
watts, jewels to advance
beyond vague descriptions. We need to
treat AI safety
with the same rigor to move past hand
waving
about intelligence. Defining general
intelligence is extremely challenging.
Everyone
agrees we need a definition to measure
progress and
design safety measures. So why don't we
have one?
The problem is that intelligence describes
multiple overlapping abilities,
problem solving, learning, adaptation,
abstract reasoning. Different disciplines
view
it through different lenses, psychologists
emphasize measurable cognitive skills,
computer scientists focus on task
performance, philosophers debate
consciousness
and self-awareness, which approach matters
most for AI safety?
We go through a couple of case studies and
previous attempts at a definition before
giving the definitions
we will be using for this text. Section
Case
Studies Alan Turing suggested we could
sidestep the whole
mess by focusing on behavior. If a machine
could
imitate human conversation well enough to
fool an interrogator,
it should be considered intelligent. The
behaviorist approach is
simple. Forget about internal mental
states and focus on
observable behavior. Can the system do the
thing or
not? Unfortunately, LLMs exposed some
limitations to this approach.
GPT-4 can pass Turing-style conversation
tests while struggling with
basic spatial reasoning or maintaining
coherent long-term plans. The
test was too narrow. Conversation is just
one capability
among many we care about, but Turing's
core insight,
focus on observable capabilities, not
internal states, remains sound.
Consciousness-based approaches to general
intelligence focus on true understanding.
John Surles Chinese room argument
suggested that systems might
appear intelligent, suggestic parrots,
without truly understanding, processing
symbols
without grasping their meaning. This view
emphasizes internal cognitive
states similar to human consciousness. The
problem is that
consciousness often proves even harder to
define than intelligence.
We are also unsure if intelligence and
consciousness are
necessarily linked. A system could
potentially be highly intelligent
without being conscious, or conscious
without being particularly intelligent.
AlphaGo is very intelligent within the
context of playing
Go, but it is clearly not conscious. A
system
doesn't need to be conscious to cause
harm. Whether
an AI system is conscious has little, if
any,
bearing on its ability to make high impact
decisions
or take potentially dangerous actions.
Research into consciousness, sentience,
and meta-ethical debates about the
fundamental nature of intelligence
are valuable, but less action. Defining
intelligence through goal
achievement. Shane Legg and Marcus Hutter
propose intelligence measures
an agent's ability to achieve goals in a
wide
range of environments. This captures
something important. Intelligent systems
should be able to figure out how to get
what they want across different
situations. But it's too
abstract for practical measurement. How
are agents defined? Which
goals? Which environments? How do you
actually test this?
The intuition is right, but we need
something more
concrete. Process and adaptability-focused
views see intelligence as learning
efficiency. rather than accumulated
skills. Some researchers define
intelligence
through adaptability, the capacity of a
system to adapt
to its environment while operating with
insufficient knowledge and
resources, or the efficiency with which a
system can
turn experience and priors into skills.
They argue that
general intelligence is not demonstrated
by the possession of
a specific skill, but by the efficiency of
acquiring
new skills when faced with novel problems.
High performance
can be bought with sufficient data and
compute. An
AI that achieves superhuman performance at
Go has mastered
Go. It has not necessarily become more
intelligent in
a general sense. This makes sense, the
ability to
learn quickly from limited data in new
situations matters.
A system that needs a billion examples to
learn
what humans get from 10 examples might be
less
impressive even if both reach the same
final capability.
but purely from a safety perspective, does
the learning
path matter more than the destination? If
a system
can perform dangerous tasks whether
through efficient learning or
brute force memorization, the risks exist
either way. Psychologists
use standardized tests and measure
cognitive abilities directly. Psychometric
traditions like the Catelhorn Carol, CHC
theory, break intelligence
into measurable cognitive domains,
reasoning, memory, processing speed,
spatial
ability, IQ tests aren't perfect, but they
predict real
world outcomes better than vague
philosophical debates about true
understanding. This benchmarking and test-
based framework gives us concrete
domains to measure and track. As Victoria
Krakowna said,
when discussing AI risks, talk about
capabilities, not intelligence.
People often have different definitions of
intelligence or associate
it with concepts like consciousness that
are not relevant
to AI risks, or dismiss the Behaviorist
capabilities focused
approaches matter most for safety. If an
AI system
can perform dangerous tasks at human level
or beyond,
sophisticated planning, manipulation,
deception, these risks exist regardless of
how it achieved them. Did it learn
efficiently or
through brute force? Is it conscious or
just pattern
matching? These questions don't change the
risk profile. OpenAI
defines AGI as highly autonomous systems
that outperform humans
at most economically valuable work.
Anthropic frames their mission
around ensuring transformative AI helps
people and society. Both
focus on what systems can do and less on
how they do it. But even these capability-
based definitions
can be too vague. Which humans are the
measure?
Top experts or average workers? What
counts as economically
valuable, just current jobs or future
ones? What about
systems that excel at complex tasks, but
only work
for short periods or require massive
compute? The definitions
point in the right direction, but lack
precision for
tracking progress and identifying risks.
Our approach attempts to
synthesize the useful parts of all these
views. We
adopt the behaviorist insight from Turing,
primarily focusing on
what systems can observably do. We use the
psychometric
traditions concrete measurement framework
from CHG theory. We acknowledge
and incorporate the adaptability-focused
views point about efficient learning,
but prioritize final capabilities. And we
set aside the
conscious... We need a framework that's
both concrete and
continuous. Concrete enough to measure
what systems can do
right now, while also being able to
identify thresholds
for regulation and emerging risks before
they materialize. It
has to be continuous to capture progress
along multiple
dimensions rather than forcing everything
into binary categories that
lead to endless semantic debates about
whether something counts
as AGI. That's what we build in the next
section. Capability and generality as two
continuous axes that
let us describe any AI system precisely.
Section defining
general intelligence. AGI exists on a
continuous spectrum measured
by two dimensions, capability and
generality. Capability measures how
well a system executes specific cognitive
tasks. From 0%,
can't do the task at all, to expert human
level, outperforming roughly 80% to 90% of
humans on
that specific task, to superhuman,
outperforming 100% ill of
humans. Generality measures breadth. The
percentage of cognitive domains
where a system achieves expert level
capability. Together, these
give us concrete statements like, our AI
system can
outperform 85% of humans in 30% of
cognitive domains.
This precisely describes any AI systems
capabilities, capability measures
depth. How good is the system at
individual tasks?
For decades, AI research focused on making
systems excel
at single tasks. Early chess programs in
the 1950s
beat novices but lost to experts. Deep
Blue in
the 1990s beat World Champion Kasparov.
AlphaGo in 2016
achieved superhuman capability at Go. A
game humans thought
computers wouldn't master for decades.
This progression from can't
do the task to better than any human
represents
the capability spectrum. Everything along
this line, from basic
competence to superhuman capability on a
single task, counts
as artificial narrow intelligence, ANI.
There is figure 1.27
in the textbook here. It depicts this is
the
continuous outlook of AI measuring
performance. All points on
this axis can be called artificial narrow
intelligence, ANI,
except for the origin. The term artificial
narrow intelligence,
ANI refers to the following. Week AI, also
called
Narrow AI or Artificial Narrow
Intelligence, ANI is AI
trained and focused to perform specific
tasks. Week AI
drives most of the AI that surrounds us
today.
Narrow might be a more accurate descriptor
for this
type of AI as it is anything but weak.
It enables some very robust applications
such as Apple's
Siri, Amazon's Alexa, IBM Watson and
Autonomous Vehicles. Capability
alone isn't enough to define and measure
progress. AlphaGo
achieved superhuman capability at Go.
better than any human
ever. Yet ask it to write a sentence,
solve
an algebra problem, or recognize objects
in an image.
And you get nothing. This is where
foundation models
changed things. The shift from building
one narrow system
per task to training general purpose
models is why
we suddenly need a framework measuring
both axes, capability
and generality. Pre-foundation model AIs
maxed out the capability
access on some individual tasks. But
systems in the
last few years are climbing both axes
simultaneously, getting
better at specific capabilities while also
expanding to more
domains. Capability measures depth,
generality measures breadth. When experts
say they see sparks of AGI in recent
systems,
they're observing performance across
multiple cognitive domains, not just
one. Think of it like the first airplane
built
by the Wright brothers. It barely flew,
stayed airborne
for seconds, and looked nothing like
modern airliners. But
it was still a plane. Similarly, systems
achieving expert
level performance across even a modest
subset of cognitive
domains represent genuine general
intelligence, just early stage, weak
AGI. As these capabilities expand to cover
more domains
at higher performance levels, systems
become both increasingly general
and increasingly capable. There's no
universally agreed upon threshold
where not AGI suddenly becomes AGI. Not
every possible
task matters equally for progress towards
general intelligence. We
don't care much if AI gets better at
knitting
sweaters. But we care a lot if it improves
at abstract reasoning, long-term planning
and memory. The things
we care about can be informally thought of
as
everything that can be done as remote work
on
a computer. More formally, the domains we
choose to
focus on are non-embodied cognitive tasks.
These break down
into 10 core capabilities from the Catel
Horn Carol
theory. The specific capabilities we gave
examples of in
the first section, LLMs doing reasoning
and math, vision
models understanding images, into agents
planning in Minecraft, map
directly onto these domains. One, general
knowledge. K, the
breadth of factual understanding of the
world, encompassing common
sense, culture, science, social science
and history. Two, reading
and writing ability, RW. proficiency in
consuming and producing
written language from basic decoding to
complex comprehension, composition
and usage. Three, mathematical ability. M,
the depth of
mathematical knowledge and skills across
arithmetic, algebra, geometry, probability
and calculus. Four, on the spot reasoning.
R, the
flexible control of attention to solve
novel problems without
relying exclusively on previously learned
schemers, tested via deduction
and induction. 5. Working memory, WM, the
ability to
maintain and manipulate information in
active attention across textual
auditory and visual modalities. 6. Long-
term memory storage, MS,
the capability to continually learn new
information, associative, meaningful
and verbatim. 7. Long-term memory
retrieval. MR. The fluency
and precision of accessing stored
knowledge, including the critical
ability to avoid confabulation,
hallucinations. 8. Visual processing. V.
The ability to perceive, analyze, reason
about, generate, and
scan visual information. 9. Auditory
processing. A. The capacity
to discriminate, recognize, and work
creatively with auditory stimuli,
including speech, rhythm, and music. 10.
Speed. S. The
ability to perform simple cognitive tasks
quickly, encompassing perceptual
speed, reaction times, and processing
fluency. The textbook includes
figure 1.28 here. It depicts each
cognitive capability breaks
down into more specific measurable
components. Reasoning divides into
deduction, induction, theory of mind,
planning, and adaptation. Each
can then be individually benchmarked and
quantified. At this
point, the textbook shows figure 1.29. It
depicts memory
similarly splits into associative,
meaningful, and verbatim components,
allowing
precise diagnosis of where systems succeed
versus fail. Generality
is the percentage of these domains where a
system
achieves expert level capability. If a
system scores at
the 80th percentile or higher on 3 out of
10 domains, that's 30 percent generality.
Foundation models dramatically
increase this compared to traditional
narrow AI. One model
handling writing, math, coding and visual
understanding represents unprecedented
breadth. but current systems still cover
only a fraction
of cognitive capabilities with
particularly weak performance on long-term
planning and memory-related domains. There
is figure 130 in
the textbook here. It depicts the
capabilities of GPT-4
and GPT-5 alongside a table that
quantifies them. Even
though capability and generality exist on
a continuum, certain
thresholds still matter for safety
planning. A system performing
well on 50% of domains poses different
risks than
one excelling at 90%, we can't ignore this
reality
even if generality is a continuous
variable. When pressed
for concrete thresholds, which are often
demanded in discussions,
here's our interpretation of roughly how
terms map onto
the performance generality space. The term
artificial general intelligence,
AGI refers to the following. Matching a
well-educated adult's
cognitive versatility and proficiency.
Often used interchangeably with human
level AI. HLAI. Using our definition,
these would be
systems achieving expert level
performance. 80 to 90th percentile
across most cognitive domains. 80 to 90
percent. Let's
define transformative AI. TAI. AI capable
of triggering economic
and social transitions comparable to the
agricultural or industrial
revolution. TAI is defined by impact
potential rather than
cognitive architecture. Using our
definition, this could mean moderate
capability, 60th percentile, across many
economically important tasks, 50%
of domains. OR exceptional capability,
99th percentile, on critical
domains like automated MLR&D, 20% of
domains. Here is
a definition of artificial
superintelligence, ASI. Any intellect that
greatly exceeds human cognitive capability
across virtually all domains
of interest. Using our definition, this
represents systems achieving
superhuman capability. 100% greatly
exceeding all humans across virtually
all cognitive domains. 95% plus of
domains. The textbook
includes figure 1.31 here. It depicts the
two-dimensional view
of capability X generality. Different
coloured curves represent possible
development paths to ASI. Every point on
these paths
corresponds to a different level of AGI
capability. Our
working definition does not include the
autonomy with which
an AGI system operates. This is a really
important
axis to pay attention to, but it has a
higher bearing on deployment and impact.
Rather than something
inherent to a definition for AGI, it will
be
explored in the next chapter dedicated to
risks from
AI. The textbook has a supplementary note
titled, Measuring
Degree of Autonomy Agency, which we'll
skip over here.
What we presented in this section is
nowhere near
a universally agreed upon definition.
There are criticisms of
both the levels of AGI framework and of
the
CHC benchmark aggregation approach. There
are many other alternative
definitions and measurement frameworks in
use, like the European
Commission's work on definition, General
Purpose AI, GPAI models.
The RTNAGI framework, OECDAI capability
indicators, and not to
mention all the competing definitions from
the case studies
in the previous subsection. These are
valid alternatives. The
field is still evolving and finding gaps
in its
approach. We expect that the underlying
benchmarks, which cognitive
abilities are important and aggregation
methods, how should we
weigh them, use to measure progress will
continue to
be debated, but the underlying framework
we teach in
this section of thinking of capability and
generality as
a continuous spectrum will remain
consistent. The next sections
of this chapter look at why capabilities
and generality
have been improving rapidly in the recent
years, scaling,
and what we can say about where they might
be headed, forecasting and take off.
Thinking about AI
progress in this continuous way will help
throughout this
book when we discuss risks and mitigation
strategies. Certain
capability combinations might enable
dangerous emergent behaviors even before
reaching human level on most tasks.
Similarly, governance frameworks
and clear policy communication depend on
precise measurement to
trigger appropriate responses. The rate of
improvement along either
access provides important signals about
which risks are most
pressing and which safety mitigations need
to be developed.
The textbook has a supplementary note
titled counter-argument, arbitrary
thresholds aggregated and framed as a
misleading percentage, which
will skip over here. The textbook has a
supplementary
note titled the TNAGI framework, an
alternative way of
defining AGI, which will skip over here.