Section 1.10 Appendix expert surveys. The
textbook includes video
1.4 here, which you may want to watch
separately.
It covers optional video outlining some
views that AI
experts have on safety and risk. The
textbook has
interactive figure 1.12 here, which you
can explore in
the online version. It shows views about
AI's impact
on society in the next 20 years, 2001.
Survey
respondents were asked, will artificial
intelligence help or harm
people in the next 20 years? At this
point,
there is interactive figure 1.1 teen in
the textbook
available in the online version. It shows
views of
Americans about robot versus human
intelligence. Survey respondents were
asked, which one, if any of the following
statements
do you most agree with? Section surveys,
according to
a recent survey conducted by AI Impact,
expected time
to human level performance dropped one to
five decades
since the 2022 survey. As always, our
questions about
high-level machine intelligence, HLMI, and
full automation of labour,
FAOL, got very different answers, and
individuals disagreed a
lot, shown as thin lines below. But the
aggregate
forecasts for both sets of questions
dropped sharply. For
context between 2016 and 2022 surveys, the
forecast for
HLMI had only shifted about a year. The
textbook
includes Figure 1.67 here. It depicts 2024
survey of
AI experts. It is also possible to compare
the
predictions of the same study in 2022 to
current results. It is interesting to note
that the
community has generally underestimated the
speed of progress over
the year 2-3 and has adjusted its
predictions downward.
Some predictions are quite surprising. For
example, tasks like
right high school essay and transcribed
speech are arguably
already automated with chat GPT and
Whisper respectively. However,
it appears that researchers are not aware
of these
results. Additionally, it is surprising
that the forecast for
when we are able to build an AI researcher
has longer timelines than when we are able
to
build high-level machine intelligence, all
human tasks. The median
of the 2024 expert survey predicts human-
level machine intelligence.
HLMI, in 2049, section quotes, here are
many quotes
from people regarding transformative AI,
subsection, AI experts. Note
that Hinton, Benjiro, and Sutskava are
some of the
most cited researchers in the field of AI.
And
that Hinton, Benjiro, and Likun are the
recipients of
the Turing Award in deep learning. Some
users on
Reddit have put together a comprehensive
list of publicly
stated AI timelines forecasts from famous
researchers and industry
leaders. As Jeffrey Hinton said, the
research question is,
how do you prevent them from ever wanting
to
take control? And nobody knows the answer.
The alarm
bell I'm ringing has to do with the
existential
threat of them taking control. If you take
the
existential risk seriously, as I now do,
it might
be quite sensible to just stop developing
these things
any further. It's as if aliens had landed
and
people haven't realized because they speak
very good English,
in the words of your Shu-Abenyayo. It's
very hard
in terms of your ego and feeling good
about
what you do. To accept the idea that the
thing you've been working on for decades
might actually
be very dangerous to humanity. I think
that I
didn't want to think too much about it,
and
that's probably the case for others. Rogue
AI may
be dangerous for the whole of humanity.
Banning powerful
AI systems say beyond the abilities of
GPT-4 that
a given autonomy and agency would be a
good
start. Here is a quote by Stuart Russell.
If
we pursue our current approach, then we
will eventually
lose control over the machines. Here is a
quote
by Damis Hassabis. We must take the risks
of
AI as seriously as other major global
challenges, like
climate change. It took the international
community too long
to coordinate an effective global response
to this, and
we're living with the consequences of that
now. We
can't afford the same delay with AI. Then
maybe
there's some kind of equivalent one day of
the
Dario Emote once wrote, When I think of
why
am I scared, I think the thing that's
really
hard to argue with is like, there will be
powerful models, they will be agentic,
we're getting towards
them. If such a model wanted to wreak
havoc
and destroy humanity or whatever, I think
Musta for
Suleiman once wrote about a pause. I don't
rule
it out. And I think that at some point
over the next five years or so, we're
going
to have to consider that question very
seriously. As
Ilya Sudskieva said, the future is going
to be
good for the AI's regardless. It would be
nice
if it would be good for humans as well.
It's not that it's going to actively hate
humans
and want to harm them, but it's just going
to be too powerful. And I think a good
analogy would be the way humans treat
animals. And
I think by default, that's the kind of
relationship
that's going to be between us and AGI's,
which
are truly autonomous and operating on
their own behalf.
To quote Shane Legg, do possible risks
from AI
outweigh other possible existential risks?
It's my number one
risk for this century. A lack of concrete
AGI
projects is not what worries me. It's the
lack
of concrete plans on how to keep these
safe
that worries me. To quote Jan Leica. After
resigning
at OpenAI, talking about sources of risks,
these problems
are quite hard to get right, and I am
concerned we aren't on a trajectory to get
there.
OpenAI is shouldering an enormous
responsibility on behalf of
all of humanity. But over the past years,
safety,
culture and processes have taken a
backseat to shiny
products. We are long overdue in getting
incredibly serious
about the implications of AGI. Here is a
quote
by Sam Altman, suggesting about how to ask
for
a global regulatory body. Any compute
cluster above a
certain extremely high power threshold,
and given the cost
here, we're talking maybe five in the
world, something
like that. Any cluster like that has to
submit
to the equivalent of international weapons
inspectors. I did
a big trip around the world this year and
talked to heads of state in many of the
countries that would need to participate
in this. And
there was almost universal support for it.
In the
words of Greg Brockman, the exact way the
post-AGI
world will look is hard to predict. That
world
will likely be more different from today's
world than
today's is from the 1500s. We do not yet
know how hard it will be to make sure
AGI's act according to the values of their
operators.
Some people believe it will be easy. Some
people
believe it'll be unimaginably difficult,
but no one knows
for sure, in the words of John Schulman.
Talking
about times near the creation of the first
AGI,
you have the race dynamics where
everyone's trying to
stay ahead, and that might require
compromising on safety.
So I think you would probably need some
coordination
among the larger entities that are doing
this kind
of training. pause either further training
or pause deployment
or avoiding certain types of training that
we think
might be riskier. To quote John Tallinn,
I've not
met anyone in AI labs who says the risk
from training a next-gen model is less
than 1%
of blowing up the planet. It's important
that people
know lives are being risked. One thing
that a
pause achieves is that we will not push
the
frontier in terms of risky pre-training
experiments, subsection academics.
In the words of IJ Good, an ultra-
intelligent machine
could design even better machines. There
would then unquestionably
be an intelligence explosion. and the
intelligence of man
would be left far behind. Thus, the first
ultra-intelligent
machine is the last invention that man
need ever
make, provided that the machine is docile
enough to
tell us how to keep it under control, as
Alan Turing said. It seems probable that
once the
machine-thinking method had started, it
would not take long
to outstrip our feeble powers. They would
be able
to converse with each other to sharpen
their wits.
At some stage, therefore, we should have
to expect
the machines to take control. To quote
Stephen Hawking,
the development of full artificial
intelligence could spell the
end of the human race. It would take off
on its own and redesign itself at an ever-
increasing
rate. To quote Eliezer Yudkowski, I do not
expect
something actually smart to attack us with
marching robot
armies with glowing red eyes where there
could be
a fun movie about us fighting them. I
expect
an actually smarter and uncaring entity
will figure out
strategies and technologies that can kill
us quickly and
reliably and then kill us. Subsection,
tech entrepreneurs, to
quote Elon Musk, AI is a rare case where
I think we need to be proactive in
regulation
than be reactive. I think that digital
superintelligence is
the single biggest existential crisis that
we face and
the most pressing one. It needs to be a
public body that has insight and then
oversight to
confirm that everyone is developing AI
safely. and mark
my words, AI is far more dangerous than
nukes,
far. So why do we have no regulatory
oversight?
This is insane. As Bill Gates said, super
intelligent
AIs are in our future. There's the
possibility that
AIs will run out of control. Possibly, a
machine
could decide that humans are a threat,
conclude that
its interests are different from ours, or
simply stop
caring about In the words of the Bletchley
Declaration,
substantial risks may arise from potential
intentional misuse or
unintended issues of control relating to
alignment with human
intent. These issues are in part because
those capabilities
are not fully understood. There is
potential for serious,
even catastrophic harm, either deliberate
or unintentional, stemming from
the most significant capabilities of these
AI models.