Section 1 subsection, hardware efficiency,
the first factor in
increasing effective computers, how
efficient is the hardware that
we produce at doing computation? iChips
are getting about
35-10 more powerful each year, but we're
approaching physical
limits. Since around 2010, the raw
computational performance, FLOPS,
of GPUs in FP32 precision, has grown by
roughly
1.35X per year. The improvement comes from
things like
denser transistors, specialized AI
circuitry, and switching to lower
precision number formats. Performance per
dollar has improved rapidly,
and hardware at any given precision and
fixed performance
level becomes 30% cheaper each year. At
the same
time, manufacturers continue to introduce
more powerful and expensive
hardware. In the near future, this trend
seems likely
to continue, but thermodynamic limits will
eventually stop this
trend. Chips can only get so energy
efficient before
physics says no. Every computation
generates heat as a
fundamental law of physics, not an
engineering problem. Current
analysis suggests there is room for a 50
to
1,000X improvement in energy efficiency
before we hit fundamental
CMOS limits with a 50% chance that
improvement cease
before a roughly 200X improvement on
existing technology. These
estimates suggest that CMOS processors are
likely sufficiently efficient
to power substantially larger AI training
runs than today.
This implies we have significant headroom
to scale using
current silicon paradigms through 2030 and
beyond, although hardware
R&D returns may eventually diminish as we
approach physical
limits. Beyond these limits, training runs
would likely require
radical changes to computing paradigms,
like a shift to
adiabatic computing. The textbook includes
figure 1.49 here. It
depicts currently observed trends in the
efficiency of hardware
used for ML over the last decades. we can
see a clear year by year increase in peak
computational performance. At this point,
the textbook shows figure
150. It depicts a forecast of the future
using
the growth and AI transition endogenous,
gate, playground. This
graph shows investments in hardware R&D,
improving the efficiency
of AI chips, measured in units of flu PE-
Yashi
year per hour's. Eventually, hardware
efficiency is capped by
physical limits. The red line showcases
aggressive parameter settings.
Green is conservative parameter settings.
The red zone highlights
the difference in timelines to full
automation between aggressive
and conservative models. Subsection,
software and algorithmic efficiency, the
second factor in increasing effective
computers, how well we
can utilize all the existing hardware that
we have.
This is separate from just making the
physical hardware
itself more efficient. Better algorithms
have cut the compute
needed for a given result by three X per
year. The level of compute needed to
achieve a
given level of performance has halved
roughly every eight
months. This rapid improvement means that
the compute required
to achieve specific levels of capability
on benchmarks can
drop by orders of magnitude over just a
few
years of algorithmic progress. The
improvements to compute efficiency
explain roughly 35% of performance
improvements in language modeling
since 2014, with the other 65% coming from
just
building more chips and running them
longer. Overall, this
means we're getting smarter about using
available hardware and
not just throwing more compute at
problems. There is
figure 1.51 in the textbook here. It
depicts estimates
of the contributions of scaling and
algorithmic innovation in
terms of the raw compute that would be
naively
needed to achieve a state-of-the-art level
of performance. The
contribution of algorithmic progress is
roughly half as much
as that of compute scaling. The textbook
includes figure
1.52 here. It depicts a forecast of the
future
using the growth and AI transition
endogenous, gate, playground.
This graph shows algorithmic improvements
over time. By developing
better algorithms and using higher quality
data, it becomes
possible to do more with the same
hardware, measured
in units of effective flop, per stained
flop, The
red line showcases aggressive parameter
settings. Green is conservative
parameter settings. The red zone
highlights the difference in
timelines to full automation between
aggressive and conservative models.
Subsection, semiconductor production, the
third factor in increasing effective
computers, how many chips can you actually
build? Total
available computing power from Nvidia
chips has grown by
approximately 2.3x per year since 2019,
enabling the training
of ever larger models. Nvidia designs a
dominant share
of AI training chips, and Taiwan's TSMC
serves as
the primary chip fab for these
manufacturers. The AI
chip supply chain is highly concentrated.
In 2024, TSMC
dedicated roughly 5% of their advanced
chip production to
AI accelerators. The rest goes to phones,
computers, and
other electronics. If AI labs want
dramatically more chips,
TSMC would need to shift priorities,
expand capacity, and
compete with other customers who also want
cutting-edge semiconductors.
At this point, the textbook shows Figure
1.53. It
depicts an estimate the world's installed
Nvidia GPU compute
capacity, broken down by GPU model. There
is figure
1.54 in the textbook here. It depicts
tables showcasing
estimates, costs and times to overcome
various constraints in
scaling up compute production. The
textbook has interactive figure
1.7 here, which you can explore in the
online
version. It shows quarterly revenue of
Nvidia Corporation across
its main market segments reported in US
dollars. Nvidia
manufactures, graphics processing units,
GPUs, which were originally used
for gaming and are now used to train AI
models. This data is not adjusted for
inflation. Investment
doesn't immediately make chip production
go faster. If some
country wants to build their own TSMC
equivalent, then
it can take four or five years to build
a new cutting-edge fab, accounting for
construction and permitting.
Though upgrading an existing fab takes
less time around
two years in addition to billions in
investment. besides
the existing competition for chips from
TSMC. Another factor
is that the machine's TSMC needs to
manufacture the
chips. These are almost exclusively made
by a single
company, ASML in the Netherlands. These
extreme ultraviolet EUV
lithography machines cost between $150
million to $380 million
each. If, when someone, EG TSMC wants to
expand
production, they can't just order 50 more
next month.
They join an already long wait list. The
textbook
includes Figure 1.55 here. It depicts a
forecast using
the growth and AI transition endogenous,
GATA, playground. This
graph shows potential scale-up of AI chip
fabrication to
meet demand for AI workloads. Due to the
exponential
cost of rapid expansions, growth is
reduced by an
adjustment costs parameter. The red line
showcases aggressive parameter
settings. Green is conservative parameter
settings. The red zone
highlights the difference in timelines to
full automation between
aggressive and conservative models.
Section, investment and training cost,
the cost in USD of training frontier
models has
grown by 3.5x per year per year since
2020.
If trends continue, we'll see the training
cost for
a single model approach billion dollar
training runs by
2007. The cost breaks down roughly as
$50.65 for
hardware, spread across its useful life,
30-45% for the
researchers and engineers, and 2-6% for
electricity. This is
venture capital and big tech money so far,
but
these numbers are approaching scales where
only nations or
the largest corporations can compete. At
this point, the
textbook shows figure 1.56. It depicts
breakdown of model
development costs for selected models.
Hardware costs are amortized
to the total number of chip hours spent on
experiments and training. R&D staff costs
cover the duration
of development from initial experiments to
publication. At this
point, there is interactive figure 1.8 in
the textbook,
available in the online version. It shows
hardware and
energy cost to train notable AI systems.
This data
is expressed in US dollars, adjusted for
inflation. There
is figure 1.57 in the textbook here. It
depicts
amortized hardware, cost plus energy cost
for the final
training run of frontier models. The
selected models are
among the top 10 most compute intensive
for their
time. Amortized hardware costs are the
product of training
chip hours and a depreciated hardware
cost, with 23%
overhead added for cluster-level
networking. OpenCircles indicate costs
which
used an estimated production cost of
Google TPU hardware.
These costs are generally more uncertain
than the others,
which used actual price data rather than
estimates. The
acquisition cost in USDR of the hardware
used to
train frontier AI models has grown by 2.5x
per
year since 2016. To give you a sense of
how much training a frontier model costs,
the total
amortized cost of developing GROC4,
released in July 2025,
including hardware and electricity, is
estimated at $480 million
USD. The acquisition cost of the hardware
to train
GROC3, including GPUs, other server
components and networking, is
estimated at $3 billion USD. The hardware
used to
train GROC4 may have been even more
expensive. The
textbook has interactive figure 1.9 here,
which you can
explore in the online version. It shows
money put
into privately held AI companies by
private investors. This
excludes publicly traded companies, e.g.
big tech companies and
companies internal spending such as R&D or
infrastructure. expressed
in US dollars, adjusted for inflation. An
unknown question
is whether the returns to productivity
gains will justify
continued investment. 2025 saw a lot of
news headlines
about circular investment and an AI
bubble. If AI
can automate significant portions of
cognitive work, capturing even
a fraction of the global labour market
makes trillion
dollar investments rational. However,
massive investments face increasing
hurdles
due to structural constraints. As compute
scales up, the
lead time between project initiation and
deployment lengthened significantly,
roughly one year for every tenfold
increase in scale,
creating a feedback loop that naturally
slows the pace
of scaling. This uncertainty regarding
long-term returns over extended
periods may drive investors to prefer
incremental scaling, breaking
up projects into smaller chunks to gauge
returns before
committing further, rather than making
massive upfront investments. Several
things could break the pattern entirely.
Models hitting a
capability ceiling where more compute
doesn't help, regulations capping
training runs or data center sizes, energy
costs making
large runs un-economical or economic
recession drying up capital.
Each represents a distinct way scaling
could stop independent
of technical feasibility. The textbook
includes figure 1.58 here.
It depicts a forecast using the growth and
AI
transition endogenous gate playground.
Gate predicts high levels of
investment in AI-related capital and R&D
to support massive
expansions of the effective compute stock.
This involves major
reallocations away from conventional
capital investments and consumption and
occurs before AI generates significant
economic value motivated by
the large payoffs from AI automation. The
red line
showcases aggressive parameter settings.
Green is conservative parameter settings.
The red zone highlights the difference in
timelines to
full automation between aggressive and
conservative models. At this
point, the textbook shows figure 1.59. It
depicts large
investments in AI, precede the economic
benefits of automation,
driven by expectations of large future
payoffs. At the
start of simulations, there is a brief
period with
substantial AI investment, but with little
generated economic value.
However, as automation proceeds, the value
generated by AI
grows rapidly, comprising the majority of
output within a
few years. The gate model thus captures
the dynamic
where it is worth making major upfront
investments to
enjoy the value generated by AI. The
investment is
measured as the fraction of yearly
economic output that
is reinvested in AI, while the benefit is
measured
as the fraction of yearly output that can
be
attributed to the deployment of digital
workers. The red
line showcases aggressive parameter
settings. Green is conservative parameter
settings. The red zone highlights the
difference in timelines
to full automation between aggressive and
conservative models. Section,
power consumption, training frontier
models requires enough electrical power
to run a small city. GPT-4's training run
likely
consumed around 50 MW, equivalent to
powering roughly 40,000
US homes. If compute scaling continues at
4 or
5x per year, frontier training runs will
require 4
to 16 gigawatts by 2030, matching the
Grand Cooley
Dam America's largest power plant. Energy
costs remain small
relative to hardware costs, but this could
change. Currently
electricity costs represent only 2 to 6%
of total
training costs, with hardware and labour
dominating the budget.
But if training runs scale to 10 plus
gigawatts,
while hardware efficiency improvements
slow down, energy could become
a much larger fraction of costs. At $0.05
per
kilowatt hour, a 10-gear W-training run
running for 100
days costs roughly $120 million just for
electricity. That's
still less than the hardware, but it's no
longer
negligible. And in practice, securing
multi-gigawatt power supplies might
cost significantly more than wholesale
electricity rates suggest. There
is figure 1.6e in the textbook here. It
depicts
historic trend and forecast for the
electricity demand of
the largest individual frontier training
runs. The textbook includes
figure 1.61 here. It depicts the projected
power consumption
for planned frontier data centers for
selected AI companies.
Scaling AI systems to the forecasted
levels of 2030
will require substantial power
infrastructure. A training run of
two times ten to the 29th flop would
require
approximately six GW Arts of Power,
assuming improvements in
hardware efficiency. This scale
necessitates data center campuses ranging
from one to five GWs by the end of
the decade. Lead times increase with
scale, every additional
10X increase in compute stock adds roughly
one year
to project timelines. Constructing the
necessary large-scale power plants
typically takes two to three years.
Despite these hurdles,
the cost of power remains a small fraction
of
data center expenses, roughly one-tenth
the cost of the
chips. making the capital investment
rational given the potential
returns. The textbook has interactive
figure 1.10 here, which
you can explore in the online version. It
shows
total electricity generated in each
country or region measured
in terawatt hours. At this point, there is
interactive
figure 1.11 in the textbook available in
the online
version. It shows the levelized cost of
energy, LCOE,
accounts for everything, the cost of
building the power
plant, plus the ongoing costs in keeping
it operational
over the lifetime of the plant. The cost
of
energy generation per watt has been
falling for decades,
and even more dramatically for renewable
sources.